[
    {
      "question": "What are the distinctive features of modern Indian political thinkers?",
      "options": [
        "The ideas of modern Indian political thinkers are historically rooted in the context of colonialism.",
        "An amalgamation of political activism and theoretical reflection is peculiar to modern Indian political thinkers.",
        "Modern Indian political thinkers have unique metaphysical and epistemological questions that may substantially differ from the Western thinkers.",
        "All of these."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "All of these.",
      "year": 2025,
      "week": 1,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Raja Rammohan Roy was a vocal proponent of the freedom of the press. From the following, choose the one that was not among those grounds that he presented to the British Crown to relax press regulation in India.",
      "options": [
        "Press as a necessity for the sustainability and durability of British rule.",
        "Press as a grievance redressal mechanism.",
        "Press as a rightful platform for the revolutionary nationalist activities of Indians.",
        "Press as a means to keep a check on Christian missionaries who are meddling with the religious practices of natives."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Press as a rightful platform for the revolutionary nationalist activities of Indians.",
      "year": 2025,
      "week": 1,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following sentences is not correct regarding the interlinkages between political thought and political theory?",
      "options": [
        "Both political theory and political thought are concerned with the understanding of politics.",
        "Political thought is less systematic and generalized than political theory.",
        "To be considered as political theory, it should inevitably be developed in the West.",
        "Political thought is narrower in scope than political theory."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "To be considered as political theory, it should inevitably be developed in the West.",
      "year": 2025,
      "week": 1,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "\u2018Mirat-ul-Akhbar\u2019 was founded and edited by which of the following political thinkers?",
      "options": [
        "Abul Fazl",
        "Sheikh Mujibur Rahman",
        "Raja Rammohan Roy",
        "Muhammad Iqbal"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Raja Rammohan Roy",
      "year": 2025,
      "week": 1,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following is not correct regarding Raja Rammohan Roy\u2019s approach to religion?",
      "options": [
        "Raja Rammohan Roy was a proponent of monotheism.",
        "Raja Rammohan Roy held that sacred religious texts should only be available for the orthodox Brahmins as making them publicly accessible could result in their misinterpretation.",
        "Raja Rammohan Roy opposed the monopoly of orthodox Brahmins over the sacred texts.",
        "Raja Rammohan Roy argued that religious associations could bring social and political transformations in society."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Raja Rammohan Roy held that sacred religious texts should only be available for the orthodox Brahmins as making them publicly accessible could result in their misinterpretation.",
      "year": 2025,
      "week": 1,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "\u201cFrom India may come influences which will widen the horizons of Western political thinkers and which will give political ideas a sounder foundation of philosophical and metaphysical speculation.\u201d -Which of the following scholars made the above statement?",
      "options": [
        "Norman D Palmer",
        "Shefali Jha",
        "Ramachandra Guha",
        "Anthony Parel"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Norman D Palmer",
      "year": 2025,
      "week": 1,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Raja Rammohan Roy was not influenced by which of the following events or ideas?",
      "options": [
        "French Revolution",
        "Freedom movement in Spain",
        "Cultural Revolution in China",
        "Freedom movement in Latin America"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Cultural Revolution in China",
      "year": 2025,
      "week": 1,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Why did Raja Rammohan Roy promote modern Western education?",
      "options": [
        "Raja Rammohan Roy promoted modern Western education due to its mere instrumentality for career advancements for the Indians.",
        "Raja Rammohan Roy considered modern Western education to be a medium for social transformation.",
        "Raja Rammohan Roy promoted modern Western education because he didn\u2019t value Indian customs and traditions.",
        "None of these."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Raja Rammohan Roy considered modern Western education to be a medium for social transformation.",
      "year": 2025,
      "week": 1,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "On 5th April 1823, the colonial government issued an order restricting the freedom of the press in India. What was not among the grounds on which a publication could be restricted according to this order?",
      "options": [
        "Any publication that propagated native religions.",
        "Any publication that could threaten the peace, harmony and order in society.",
        "Any publication that could create suspicion and hatred among the Indians towards the colonial government.",
        "Any publication that was considered harmful and defamatory towards the royal family, government officials, and their allied powers."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Any publication that propagated native religions.",
      "year": 2025,
      "week": 1,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following is not correct regarding Raja Rammohan Roy\u2019s outlook towards the British rule?",
      "options": [
        "Raja Ram Mohan Roy thought that British rule would promote civil liberties.",
        "The only reason why Raja Rammohan Roy opposed the British rule was the denial of civil liberties to the Indians.",
        "Raja Ram Mohan Roy had chosen civil and religious liberty over political liberty.",
        "Raja Ram Mohan Roy considered that the natives of his period lacked the capacity for self-governance."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "The only reason why Raja Rammohan Roy opposed the British rule was the denial of civil liberties to the Indians.",
      "year": 2025,
      "week": 1,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "On what grounds did Rabindranath Tagore oppose the Non-cooperation Movement?",
      "options": [
        "Rabindranath Tagore regarded the Non-cooperation Movement as being based on blind national pride.",
        "Rabindranath Tagore also argued that parochial anti-West tendencies within the Indian National Movement could hinder India\u2019s relationship with the international community.",
        "Rabindranath Tagore was sceptical of Gandhiji\u2019s call for boycotting foreign goods or clothes, based on the belief that Western textiles were impure. Tagore considered that as propagating untruths to sustain a political agitation.",
        "All of these."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "All of these.",
      "year": 2025,
      "week": 2,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one of the following sentences is not correct about Rabindranath\u2019s views on the idea of man?",
      "options": [
        "Tagore was radical in his understanding of man and individual freedom.",
        "Tagore did not believe in the moral or ethical side of man.",
        "Tagore emphasised both the moral and the spiritual aspects of human nature.",
        "Tagore also spoke about the duality in human nature."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Tagore did not believe in the moral or ethical side of man.",
      "year": 2025,
      "week": 2,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "From the following statements, choose the one that is not correct regarding Rabindranath Tagore\u2019s ideas on the East and the West.",
      "options": [
        "Rabindranath Tagore is known for his anti-West approach.",
        "Rabindranath Tagore advocated for a symbiosis of the East and the West.",
        "Rabindranath Tagore sought a deep association between the cultures of the East and the West.",
        "Rabindranath Tagore believed that a creative unity between the East and the West was only possible when the East had discovered its soul and identity for that reason."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Rabindranath Tagore is known for his anti-West approach.",
      "year": 2025,
      "week": 2,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is/are not correct regarding Rabindranath Tagore\u2019s ideas on cosmopolitanism?",
      "options": [
        "Rabindranath Tagore considered all human beings as world citizens and argued that they owe their primary allegiance to the world community.",
        "Rabindranath Tagore argued that the motivation behind cosmopolitanism is based on an existential orientation- a way of being in this world.",
        "Rabindranath Tagore\u2019s ideas on cosmopolitanism draws its justifications from theoretical abstractions devoid of any existential orientation.",
        "Rabindranath Tagore\u2019s cosmopolitanism is partly a consequence of his philosophical and historiographical understanding that statist conceptions of history cannot totally capture social life."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Rabindranath Tagore\u2019s ideas on cosmopolitanism draws its justifications from theoretical abstractions devoid of any existential orientation.",
      "year": 2025,
      "week": 2,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following is not correct regarding Tagore\u2019s views on the Zamindari system?",
      "options": [
        "Tagore argued that the zamindari system was for the benefit of the masses.",
        "Tagore believed that the zamindari system, which claimed to represent the people's interests, was flawed.",
        "As a practitioner of zamindari, Tagore could sense the cruelty associated with the zamindari system.",
        "Tagore was genuinely apologetic and embarrassed about the whole system of zamindari."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Tagore argued that the zamindari system was for the benefit of the masses.",
      "year": 2025,
      "week": 2,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "According to Rabindranath Tagore, what does the \u2018Universal Man\u2019 strive for?",
      "options": [
        "Happiness",
        "Necessities",
        "Magnificence",
        "Beauty"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Magnificence",
      "year": 2025,
      "week": 2,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "What was Rabindranath Tagore\u2019s position on the Charkha Programme?",
      "options": [
        "Rabindranath Tagore was apprehensive about the charkha and didn\u2019t think that the mere burning of foreign clothes was a solution to India\u2019s problems.",
        "The economic efficiency of the Charkha Programme was questionable for Rabindranath Tagore.",
        "Rabindranath Tagore was also skeptical of the use of moral language instead of economic language in the programme.",
        "All of these."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "All of these.",
      "year": 2025,
      "week": 2,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "In response to which of the following events did Rabindranath Tagore renounce his Knighthood?",
      "options": [
        "Jallianwala Bagh Massacre",
        "Partition of India",
        "Non-Cooperation Movement",
        "The Holocaust"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Jallianwala Bagh Massacre",
      "year": 2025,
      "week": 2,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "From the following sentences, choose the one that is not correct regarding Rabindranath Tagore\u2019s ideas on nationalism.",
      "options": [
        "Tagore was an ardent nationalist of his time.",
        "Tagore viewed nationalism as the breeding ground for imperialism.",
        "Tagore viewed nationalism as a danger to humanity.",
        "Tagore argued that the obsession with nationalism could lead to war, hatred and mutual suspicion among the nations."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Tagore was an ardent nationalist of his time.",
      "year": 2025,
      "week": 2,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Tagore can also be regarded as a rooted cosmopolitan thinker because-",
      "options": [
        "Tagore believed in the universal values of the East.",
        "Tagore respected the Indian tradition.",
        "Tagore respected various individual traditions and nationalities but also believed in universal values.",
        "Tagore believed in the universal values of the West."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Tagore respected various individual traditions and nationalities but also believed in universal values.",
      "year": 2025,
      "week": 2,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "The political thought of Aurobindo engages with-",
      "options": [
        "Only the political dimensions of human life.",
        "Only the spiritual dimensions of human life.",
        "Both the political and spiritual dimensions of human life.",
        "Neither the political nor the spiritual dimensions of human life."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Both the political and spiritual dimensions of human life.",
      "year": 2025,
      "week": 3,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "During the early phases of his life, Aurobindo actively participated in the national movement of India. During this time, his companionship is known with which of the following political leaders?",
      "options": [
        "Bipin Chandra Pal",
        "Bal Gangadhar Tilak",
        "Both Bipin Chandra Pal and Bal Gangadhar Tilak",
        "B.R. Ambedkar."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Both Bipin Chandra Pal and Bal Gangadhar Tilak",
      "year": 2025,
      "week": 3,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "What does \u2018True Self\u2019 mean as articulated by Aurobindo?",
      "options": [
        "Rational mind",
        "Truthful self",
        "Spiritual individual",
        "Physical self"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Spiritual individual",
      "year": 2025,
      "week": 3,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Who founded the journal \u2018Karmayogin\u2019?",
      "options": [
        "Mahatma Gandhi",
        "Aurobindo",
        "Bal Gangadhar Tilak",
        "Jawaharlal Nehru"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Aurobindo",
      "year": 2025,
      "week": 3,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following sentences is incorrect about Aurobindo\u2019s views on Nationalism?",
      "options": [
        "Aurobindo had a religious conception of nationalism.",
        "Aurobindo believed that nationalism was a religion gifted by God and argued that God was immortal, and so was nationalism.",
        "Aurobindo viewed nationalism as a hindrance towards attaining human unity.",
        "Aurobindo argued that nationalism is not merely a political programme."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Aurobindo viewed nationalism as a hindrance towards attaining human unity.",
      "year": 2025,
      "week": 3,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "From the following statements, choose the one that is not correct regarding Aurobindo\u2019s conceptualisation of a \u2018spiritual religion of humanity\u2019.",
      "options": [
        "A spiritual religion of humanity emphasises a universal religion for all human beings.",
        "A spiritual religion of humanity is considered as the means for universal human unity.",
        "A spiritual religion of humanity indicates the increasing realisation of a divine reality in which we are all one.",
        "Aurobindo advocates a spiritual religion of humanity because, in his view, spiritual foundation can lead to the psychological unification of people."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "A spiritual religion of humanity emphasises a universal religion for all human beings.",
      "year": 2025,
      "week": 3,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "During the freedom movement in India, Aurobindo was associated with which one of the following?",
      "options": [
        "Moderate section of the Congress",
        "Extremist section of the Congress",
        "Indian National Army",
        "Muslim League"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Extremist section of the Congress",
      "year": 2025,
      "week": 3,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Read the following statements and choose the correct option from below- Statement I: Aurobindo talks about the \u2018economics of a spiritualised society\u2019, which intends to provide everyone with the pleasure of work in accordance with their nature and leisure as required for their inner development. Statement II: According to Aurobindo, the prime objective of that society is to ensure a stable machinery of production for a longer time.",
      "options": [
        "Only Statement-I is correct.",
        "Only Statement-II is correct.",
        "Both Statement-I & Statement-II are correct.",
        "Neither Statement-I nor Statement-II are correct."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Only Statement-I is correct.",
      "year": 2025,
      "week": 3,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Rajas element denotes -",
      "options": [
        "A state of illumination",
        "A state of ignorance",
        "The will to action",
        "A state of luxury"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "The will to action",
      "year": 2025,
      "week": 3,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one of the following sentences is not correct about Aurobindo\u2019s views on the Gita?",
      "options": [
        "Aurobindo argued that the Gita should not be understood merely in its metaphysical connotations of ancient times.",
        "Aurobindo argued that the Gita should be understood in its renewed relevance to the living truths that it contains.",
        "Aurobindo believed that the Gita could not offer much in discovering the horizons of the future.",
        "Rather than focusing on the relevance of the Gita in understanding the past, Aurobindo\u2019s approach towards it was more future-oriented."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Aurobindo believed that the Gita could not offer much in discovering the horizons of the future.",
      "year": 2025,
      "week": 3,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "In the first World's Parliament of Religions, held at the Art Institute of Chicago in 1893, Vivekananda delivered a profound speech that moved the attendees. What was his speech about?",
      "options": [
        "Universal education",
        "Universal tolerance",
        "Universal democracy",
        "Universal religion"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Universal tolerance",
      "year": 2025,
      "week": 4,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one of the following sentences is not correct about Vivekananda's views on the idea of freedom?",
      "options": [
        "Vivekananda believed that freedom was the key to a spiritual, social, and political life.",
        "Vivekananda opined that social and political liberty could be realized without paying attention to moral, ethical, and religious concerns.",
        "For Vivekananda, freedom was essential for an individual's social, political, or economic growth.",
        "Vivekananda considered that freedom is needed to maintain religious harmony and realize individual personality."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Vivekananda opined that social and political liberty could be realized without paying attention to moral, ethical, and religious concerns.",
      "year": 2025,
      "week": 4,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following statements accurately captures Vivekananda's views on politics and religion?",
      "options": [
        "Politics and religion are two different domains.",
        "Politics and religion are inseparable.",
        "Religion is only a manifestation of politics.",
        "Politics is dependent on religion."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Politics and religion are two different domains.",
      "year": 2025,
      "week": 4,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "From the statements below, choose the most accurate regarding the philosophy of 'Advaita Vedanta,' as propounded by Vivekananda.",
      "options": [
        "The philosophy of 'Advaita Vedanta' believes in the non-dualistic ultimate reality.",
        "The philosophy of 'Advaita Vedanta' aims to break down the existing privileges among people.",
        "In the philosophy of 'Advaita Vedanta,' man is considered no different from God, and it is held that human actions and thoughts should be guided by the principles of the divinity of the soul and the solidarity of mankind.",
        "All of these are correct."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "All of these are correct.",
      "year": 2025,
      "week": 4,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "In the views of Vivekananda, which of the following was not among the three ways of tackling the existing social concerns in India?",
      "options": [
        "Emancipation of Women",
        "Positive Education",
        "Cultural Assimilation",
        "Upliftment of the Masses"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Cultural Assimilation",
      "year": 2025,
      "week": 4,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "How did Vivekananda approach the colonial rule in India?",
      "options": [
        "Vivekananda held that the colonial rule had hypnotised the Indian mind and taken away its dignity and self-belief.",
        "Vivekananda defended the colonial rule on the grounds of its promotion of civil liberties.",
        "Although Vivekananda was apprehensive about colonial rule, he believed that bringing social legislation could ensure justice in that situation.",
        "Vivekananda was very skeptical of the West and opposed colonial rule for that very reason."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Vivekananda held that the colonial rule had hypnotised the Indian mind and taken away its dignity and self-belief.",
      "year": 2025,
      "week": 4,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Who among the following was the spiritual guru of Vivekananda?",
      "options": [
        "Shri Ramakrishna Paramhans",
        "Mahatma Gandhi",
        "Raja Ram Mohan Roy",
        "Shankaracharya"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Shri Ramakrishna Paramhans",
      "year": 2025,
      "week": 4,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Read the following two statements and choose the correct option from below- Statement-I: Vivekananda believed in the Varnashrama system. Statement-II: Vivekananda criticised the Brahmanical practice of excluding the Shudras from accessing Vedic knowledge.",
      "options": [
        "Only Statement I is correct.",
        "Only Statement II is correct.",
        "Both Statements I and II are correct.",
        "Neither Statement I nor II is correct."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Both Statements I and II are correct.",
      "year": 2025,
      "week": 4,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following statements represents Vivekananda's thoughts on democracy?",
      "options": [
        "Vivekananda understood democracy as a process that inculcates faith, self-reliance, and self-government.",
        "For Vivekananda, democracy was equal to any form of direct rule.",
        "For Vivekananda, democracy was a mode of anarchy.",
        "By democracy, Vivekananda only referred to the indirect forms of representation."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Vivekananda understood democracy as a process that inculcates faith, self-reliance, and self-government.",
      "year": 2025,
      "week": 4,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "The compilation of the lectures given by Vivekananda in London was published as _________.",
      "options": [
        "Karma Yoga",
        "Philosophical Vedanta",
        "Practical Vedanta",
        "A Memoir of London"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Practical Vedanta",
      "year": 2025,
      "week": 4,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Mahatma Gandhi started his political activism in which of the following countries?",
      "options": [
        "Sri Lanka",
        "South Africa",
        "Morocco",
        "Cuba"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "South Africa",
      "year": 2025,
      "week": 5,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Mahatma Gandhi started his political activism in India with which of the following agitations?",
      "options": [
        "Quit India Movement",
        "Non-cooperation Movement",
        "Champaran Satyagraha",
        "Civil Disobedience Movement"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Champaran Satyagraha",
      "year": 2025,
      "week": 5,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Mahatma Gandhi was a voracious reader interested in writings from around the world. One of the major writings that greatly influenced him was \u2018Life Without Principles\u2019. Who among the following writers had authored this text?",
      "options": [
        "Henry David Thoreau",
        "Martin Luther King",
        "Nelson Mandela",
        "Ruskin Bond"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Henry David Thoreau",
      "year": 2025,
      "week": 5,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "According to Mahatma Gandhi, which one among the following is not an ideal virtue of a Satyagrahi?",
      "options": [
        "Chastity",
        "Selfishness",
        "Truthfulness",
        "Fearlessness"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Selfishness",
      "year": 2025,
      "week": 5,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "From the following statements, choose the one that is not correct regarding Mahatma Gandhi\u2019s ideas on Satyagraha.",
      "options": [
        "Satyagraha, understood as the combination of two words- satya and agraha, implies the insistence on truth.",
        "Satyagraha is not merely a means of opposing authority, but it equally emphasises the practice of love and morality to strengthen society.",
        "Satyagraha relies on both violent and non-violent methods of opposition.",
        "Satyagraha relies on the self-suffering of the satyagrahi."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Satyagraha relies on both violent and non-violent methods of opposition.",
      "year": 2025,
      "week": 5,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Read the following two statements and choose the correct option from below- Statement I: Mahatma Gandhi was sceptical of the uncontrolled madness behind the machinery. In his view, the usage of machinery should be guided by moral considerations regarding how men should conduct their lives. Statement II: Mahatma Gandhi also argued that the increasing use of technology and machinery could result in massive unemployment.",
      "options": [
        "Only Statement I is correct.",
        "Only Statement II is correct.",
        "Both Statement I & II are correct.",
        "Neither statement I nor II is correct."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Both Statement I & II are correct.",
      "year": 2025,
      "week": 5,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Who classified the political philosophy of Mahatma Gandhi as 'Pax Gandhiana'?",
      "options": [
        "Ramchandra Guha",
        "Granville Austin",
        "Anthony J Parel",
        "V R Mehta"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Anthony J Parel",
      "year": 2025,
      "week": 5,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "From the following statements, choose the one that is not correct regarding Mahatma Gandhi\u2019s vision for future India.",
      "options": [
        "Mahatma Gandhi envisioned India as a spiritually enlightened society.",
        "Mahatma Gandhi argued that self-purification could bring spiritual emancipation and lead to a spiritually enlightened society.",
        "In the vision of Mahatma Gandhi, a spiritually enlightened society will be an egalitarian society.",
        "Mahatma Gandhi held that a centralised polity with modern technologies is a prerequisite for the existence of a spiritually enlightened society."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Mahatma Gandhi held that a centralised polity with modern technologies is a prerequisite for the existence of a spiritually enlightened society.",
      "year": 2025,
      "week": 5,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "According to Mahatma Gandhi, the European society was-",
      "options": [
        "A politically corrupt society",
        "A spiritual society",
        "A non-violent society",
        "An embodiment of social justice"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "A politically corrupt society",
      "year": 2025,
      "week": 5,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "On which of the following issues was there a significant disagreement between Mahatma Gandhi and B.R. Ambedkar?",
      "options": [
        "Swaraj",
        "Varnashrama Dharma",
        "Ahimsa",
        "Sarvodaya"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Varnashrama Dharma",
      "year": 2025,
      "week": 5,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Read the following two statements and choose the correct option from below- Statement-I: Muhammad Iqbal criticised the Indian National Congress as it was mostly dominated by the Hindus. Statement-II: However, Iqbal equally appreciated the secular outlook of the Indian National Congress towards politics and the state.",
      "options": [
        "Only Statement-I is correct.",
        "Only Statement-II is correct.",
        "Both Statements-I &II are correct.",
        "Neither Statement-I nor Statement II is correct."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Only Statement-I is correct.",
      "year": 2025,
      "week": 6,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one among the following best describes the meaning of the term \u2018Khudi\u2019 as described by Iqbal?",
      "options": [
        "Respect",
        "Self-Affirmation or ego",
        "Ethics",
        "Morality"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Self-Affirmation or ego",
      "year": 2025,
      "week": 6,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "In his book, \u2018The Reconstruction of Religious Thought in Islam\u2019, Iqbal emphasises the re-examination and reconstruction of the philosophy of Islam. From the following statements, choose the one that is not correct regarding Iqbal\u2019s views on that matter.",
      "options": [
        "Iqbal\u2019s emphasis on the need to reconstruct the philosophy of Islam originated in his understanding that Islam was experiencing a period of stagnation, which was leaving it behind other philosophical traditions.",
        "For such a reconstruction to be made possible, Iqbal argued, a sharp break from the past was more than necessary.",
        "Iqbal believed that modern knowledge, reason and democracy could lead to such reconstruction.",
        "Iqbal considered such reconstruction necessary because it could help men achieve moral perfection, thus leading to socio-economic transformation and justice."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "For such a reconstruction to be made possible, Iqbal argued, a sharp break from the past was more than necessary.",
      "year": 2025,
      "week": 6,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following political organizations was Iqbal associated with?",
      "options": [
        "Justice Party",
        "Azad Hind Fauj",
        "Muslim League",
        "Hindu Mahasabha"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Muslim League",
      "year": 2025,
      "week": 6,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "What was \u2018Islam\u2019 for Muhammad Iqbal?",
      "options": [
        "For Iqbal, Islam was a philosophy of life.",
        "For Iqbal, Islam was a way of living.",
        "For Iqbal, Islam was the embodiment of certain historical and cultural traditions and social and legal institutions.",
        "All of these."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "All of these.",
      "year": 2025,
      "week": 6,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "From the following statements, choose the one that is not correct regarding Iqbal\u2019s views on Sufism.",
      "options": [
        "Iqbal was very critical of the negative attitude of Sufism towards reason and rationalistic philosophy.",
        "Iqbal accepted the teachings of Sufism on the role of intuition in the process of cognition.",
        "Iqbal acknowledged that the mysticism of Sufism was essential for the overall development of human personality.",
        "Iqbal was also critical of Sufism\u2019s preaching of men\u2019s withdrawal from the real world."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Iqbal acknowledged that the mysticism of Sufism was essential for the overall development of human personality.",
      "year": 2025,
      "week": 6,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Who among the following is considered the national poet of Pakistan?",
      "options": [
        "Mirza Galib",
        "Muhammad Iqbal",
        "Kaifi Azmi",
        "Akbar Allahabadi"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Muhammad Iqbal",
      "year": 2025,
      "week": 6,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "According to Iqbal, what are the essential components of an ideal Muslim community?",
      "options": [
        "Only Homogeneity",
        "Only Unity",
        "Neither unity nor homogeneity",
        "Both the unity and homogeneity."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Both the unity and homogeneity.",
      "year": 2025,
      "week": 6,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one among the following sentences is not correct regarding the religious and political thought of Muhammad Iqbal?",
      "options": [
        "Muhammad Iqbal emphasised the self and the human spirit.",
        "Muhammad Iqbal emphasised the capacity for self-determination.",
        "Muhammad Iqbal emphasised the self at the service of the divine.",
        "Muhammad Iqbal did not emphasise the self within a community."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Muhammad Iqbal did not emphasise the self within a community.",
      "year": 2025,
      "week": 6,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Read the following two statements and choose the correct option from below- Statement I- Muhammad Iqbal tried to find a spiritual expression of anticolonialism in religion. Statement II- Through religion, Iqbal searched for an alternate path of development distinct from the West.",
      "options": [
        "Only Statement-I is correct.",
        "Only Statement-II is correct.",
        "Both Statements -I &II are correct.",
        "Neither Statement-I nor Statement II is correct."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Both Statements -I &II are correct.",
      "year": 2025,
      "week": 6,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "From the following political thinkers, choose the one who was not associated with the tradition of Hindu Nationalism.",
      "options": [
        "Bal Gangadhar Tilak",
        "Lala Lajpat Rai",
        "Jawaharlal Nehru",
        "V.D. Savarkar"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Jawaharlal Nehru",
      "year": 2025,
      "week": 7,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following is not correct regarding the social and political thought of Savarkar?",
      "options": [
        "Savarkar thought that only the fittest can survive the struggle of life while the others get eliminated eventually.",
        "Savarkar supported the principle of absolute non-violence.",
        "Savarkar believed in relative morality and argued that the morality of an action should be judged in accordance with the specificity of the action concerned.",
        "Savarkar believed that violence is natural to human society."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Savarkar supported the principle of absolute non-violence.",
      "year": 2025,
      "week": 7,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "The book \u2018Life of Barrister Savarkar\u2019 was written by",
      "options": [
        "M.S. Golwalkar",
        "V.D. Savarkar",
        "K.B. Hedgewar",
        "Nathuram Godse"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "V.D. Savarkar",
      "year": 2025,
      "week": 7,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Read the following two statements and choose the correct option from below- I. Savarkar did not negate the right of minorities to co-exist, but he made it conditional on the ground of their acceptance of Hindu dominance. II. Savarkar supported preferential treatment to those minorities who accepted his condition of accepting the domination of Hindus.",
      "options": [
        "Only the statement (I) is correct.",
        "Only the statement (II) is correct.",
        "Both (I &II) statements are correct.",
        "Both (I & II) statements are incorrect."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Only the statement (I) is correct.",
      "year": 2025,
      "week": 7,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "According to V.D. Savarkar, which of the following terms can be the closest parallel to his philosophy of \u2018Hindutva\u2019?",
      "options": [
        "Hinduism",
        "Hinduness",
        "Hindi",
        "Hindustan"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Hinduness",
      "year": 2025,
      "week": 7,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "From the following statements choose the one that is not correct regarding Savarkar\u2019s views on the definition of \u2018Hindu\u2019.",
      "options": [
        "According to Savarkar, to be categorised as a Hindu, one must consider this land as both their fatherland as well as holy land.",
        "Savarkar minimised the significance of the religious criterion in the definition of a Hindu.",
        "Savarkar held that the religious criterion- that being a follower of Hinduism- was the most essential feature of defining a Hindu.",
        "Savarkar argued that Hindus were primarily the descendants of the Aryans."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Savarkar held that the religious criterion- that being a follower of Hinduism- was the most essential feature of defining a Hindu.",
      "year": 2025,
      "week": 7,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "According to Savarkar, which of the following Indian languages has the potential to preserve Hindu culture?",
      "options": [
        "Sanskrit",
        "Braj Bhasha",
        "Marathi",
        "Prakrit"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Sanskrit",
      "year": 2025,
      "week": 7,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "From the following statements, choose the one that is not correct regarding Savarkar\u2019s ideological differences with Mahatma Gandhi.",
      "options": [
        "In contrast to Gandhi, Savarkar advocated for science and rationality in the age of machines and technologies.",
        "Savarkar was more vocal against dogmatic religious practices than Gandhi.",
        "Savarkar was opposed to absolute non-violence, as propounded by Gandhi.",
        "Both Savarkar and Gandhi emphasised the practice of absolute non-violence in any political situation."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Both Savarkar and Gandhi emphasised the practice of absolute non-violence in any political situation.",
      "year": 2025,
      "week": 7,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "From the following statements, choose the one that is not correct regarding Savarkar\u2019s ideas on nationalism.",
      "options": [
        "Savarkar viewed culture, religion, race, and historical affinity as contributors to the formation of nations.",
        "Savarkar\u2019s ideas on nationalism were a synthesis of territorial nationalism offered by Congress and cultural-religious nationalism put forward by the Muslim League.",
        "Savarkar argued that, in the formation of a national unit, territorial unity had a bigger role to play than religious, racial or cultural attributes.",
        "Savarkar regarded one language and one culture (ek bhasha ek sanskriti) as the basis of the formation of modern nations."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Savarkar argued that, in the formation of a national unit, territorial unity had a bigger role to play than religious, racial or cultural attributes.",
      "year": 2025,
      "week": 7,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Who among the following inspired V D Savarkar\u2019s ideas on nation and nationalism?",
      "options": [
        "Vivekananda",
        "Mazzini",
        "Mahatma Gandhi",
        "Ernest Renan"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Mazzini",
      "year": 2025,
      "week": 7,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following sentences is incorrect regarding Jawaharlal Nehru\u2019s vision of Indian Nationalism?",
      "options": [
        "Jawaharlal Nehru envisioned Indian nationalism to be secular.",
        "Jawaharlal Nehru envisioned Indian nationalism to be rational.",
        "Jawaharlal Nehru envisioned Indian nationalism to be guided by the principles of Hinduism.",
        "Jawaharlal Nehru envisioned Indian nationalism to be international in its outlook."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Jawaharlal Nehru envisioned Indian nationalism to be guided by the principles of Hinduism.",
      "year": 2025,
      "week": 8,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "In which of the following sessions Congress passed a Resolution on 'Fundamental Rights and Economic and Social Change'?",
      "options": [
        "Karachi Session of 1931",
        "Kanpur Session of 1925",
        "Nagpur Session of 1920",
        "Madras Session of 1927"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Karachi Session of 1931",
      "year": 2025,
      "week": 8,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Read the following two statements and choose the correct option from below- Statement-I: In his initial years, Jawaharlal Nehru favoured the radical politics of extremists like that of Bal Gangadhar Tilak. Statement-II: Nehru particularly admired the religious underpinnings of the extremists in that period.",
      "options": [
        "Only Statement-I is correct.",
        "Only Statement-II is correct.",
        "Both Statement-I &II are correct.",
        "Neither Statement-I nor Statement-II is correct."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Only Statement-I is correct.",
      "year": 2025,
      "week": 8,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following sentences is incorrect regarding Nehru's views on socialism?",
      "options": [
        "Nehru considered socialism as the most appropriate way of reducing poverty in India.",
        "Nehru added a moral concern to the idea of socialism.",
        "Nehru held that democracy and socialism are complementary to each other.",
        "Despite his inclination towards socialism, Nehru didn\u2019t advocate for the Indian state to adopt socialist principles."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Despite his inclination towards socialism, Nehru didn\u2019t advocate for the Indian state to adopt socialist principles.",
      "year": 2025,
      "week": 8,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "The monumental speech that Nehru delivered on the eve of India\u2019s independence is known as",
      "options": [
        "The Future of India",
        "My Vision for India",
        "Tryst with Destiny",
        "Swaraj is my Birth Right"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Tryst with Destiny",
      "year": 2025,
      "week": 8,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "How did Jawaharlal Nehru approach the doctrine of secularism?",
      "options": [
        "For Nehru, secularism was not merely a political doctrine but also a social one.",
        "For Nehru, secularism meant a social structure wherein individuals would not be subjected to any hierarchy based on their religion.",
        "Nehru also held that, in secularism, inter-group and inter-personal relations would not be adversely affected by religious considerations.",
        "All of these."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "All of these.",
      "year": 2025,
      "week": 8,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Read the following two statements and choose the correct option from below- Statement-I: Nehru had a broader understanding of democracy, emphasising its social and economic dimensions. Statement-II: Nehru also held that it is only with the presence of equality that democracy can be sustained.",
      "options": [
        "Only Statement-I is correct.",
        "Only Statement-II is correct.",
        "Both Statement- I & II are correct.",
        "Neither Statement-I nor Statement-II is correct."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Both Statement- I & II are correct.",
      "year": 2025,
      "week": 8,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Jawaharlal Nehru is known for his secularist outlook towards politics. He focused on how a secular state should act in a society marked with religious diversity. From the following statements, choose the one that is incorrect regarding his ideas on the functions of a secular state in a religiously diverse society.",
      "options": [
        "It is the duty of the secular state to protect religious diversity.",
        "A secular state should be committed to the rights of the minorities.",
        "Inter-religious domination is a natural consequence of a religiously diverse society, and it can be resolved spontaneously. Under no circumstances should a secular state intervene in the mutual affairs among existing religious communities.",
        "A secular state should intervene in the majoritarian acts of a religious community in order to undermine inter-religious domination."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Inter-religious domination is a natural consequence of a religiously diverse society, and it can be resolved spontaneously. Under no circumstances should a secular state intervene in the mutual affairs among existing religious communities.",
      "year": 2025,
      "week": 8,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Read the following two statements on Gandhi and Nehru's vision of state and economic development, and choose the correct option from below- Statement-I: Gandhi and Nehru were unanimous on their idea of the state as a soulless machine and stated that it could hardly achieve any substantive development for the people. Statement-II: While Gandhi supported decentralization and small-scale industries, Nehru, on the other hand, was an advocate of centralized and planned economic development.",
      "options": [
        "Only Statement-I is correct.",
        "Only Statement-II is correct.",
        "Both Statement- I & II are correct.",
        "Neither Statement-I nor Statement-II is correct."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Only Statement-II is correct.",
      "year": 2025,
      "week": 8,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Nehru was the founding editor of which of the following newspapers?",
      "options": [
        "Times of India",
        "The Hindu",
        "National Herald",
        "Dainik Bhaskar"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "National Herald",
      "year": 2025,
      "week": 8,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "From the following ideologies, choose the one that Jawaharlal Nehru did not associate with.",
      "options": [
        "Socialism",
        "Internationalism",
        "Imperialism",
        "Nationalism"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Imperialism",
      "year": 2025,
      "week": 9,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "The Mahad Satyagraha in 1927, led by B R Ambedkar, mainly aimed at",
      "options": [
        "Asserting the right to access public tanks and wells by the untouchables.",
        "Securing voting rights for the Mahad caste.",
        "Attaining a separate electorate for the Dalits",
        "Propagating the ideals of Gandhian satyagraha among members of the Mahad caste."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Asserting the right to access public tanks and wells by the untouchables.",
      "year": 2025,
      "week": 9,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "From the given statements, choose the one that is not correct regarding Nehru\u2019s overall conception of foreign policy.",
      "options": [
        "Nehru viewed that a country\u2019s foreign policy should promote international peace and security.",
        "Nehru viewed that a country\u2019s foreign policy should aim to maintain just and honourable relations between nations.",
        "Nehru viewed that a country\u2019s foreign policy should be respectful towards international laws and treaties.",
        "Nehru believed that a country\u2019s foreign policy should be guided solely by national interests."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Nehru believed that a country\u2019s foreign policy should be guided solely by national interests.",
      "year": 2025,
      "week": 9,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following statements is incorrect regarding Nehru\u2019s views on nationalism and internationalism?",
      "options": [
        "Nehru believed that nationalism and internationalism could co-exist.",
        "Nehru considered cooperation among the nations necessary for their survival and progress.",
        "Nehru advocated eliminating war as it creates an environment of mutual hatred and fear",
        "Nehru was a vocal critic of the idea of nation and nationalism."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Nehru was a vocal critic of the idea of nation and nationalism.",
      "year": 2025,
      "week": 9,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following political parties was founded by B R Ambedkar?",
      "options": [
        "Swatantra Party",
        "Praja Socialist Party",
        "Independent Labour Party",
        "Bahujan Samaj Party"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Independent Labour Party",
      "year": 2025,
      "week": 9,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Read the following two statements and choose the correct option from below- Statement-I: Ambedkar argued that caste was the major hindrance towards the formation of a united political community in India. Statement-II: The caste system, Ambedkar argued, maintained its hierarchies primarily by voluntary submissions of people characterised by \u2018an ascending scale of reverence and a descending scale of contempt\u2019.",
      "options": [
        "Only Statement-I is correct.",
        "Only Statement-II is correct.",
        "Both Statement-I &II are correct.",
        "Neither Statement-I nor Statement-II is correct."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Both Statement-I &II are correct.",
      "year": 2025,
      "week": 9,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "In 1924, Ambedkar founded the Bahishkrit Hitakarini Sabha (Group for the Wellbeing of the Excluded). From the following sentences, choose the one that is not correct regarding the same.",
      "options": [
        "Bahishkrit Hitakarini Sabha was an embodiment of Ambedkar\u2019s intensive campaign for social reform",
        "Bahishkrit Hitakarini Sabha was primarily formed to participate in electoral politics.",
        "Bahishkrit Hitakarini Sabha was formed to promote socio-political awareness among the Dalits.",
        "Bahishkrit Hitakarini Sabha also aimed to raise public awareness about the grievances faced by the Dalits."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Bahishkrit Hitakarini Sabha was primarily formed to participate in electoral politics.",
      "year": 2025,
      "week": 9,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "From the following statements, choose the correct one regarding Ambedkar\u2019s criticism of the caste system.",
      "options": [
        "Ambedkar held that caste had killed the public spirit in India.",
        "Ambedkar held that caste had destroyed the sense of public charity in India.",
        "Ambedkar held that caste had made public opinion impossible in India.",
        "All of these."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "All of these.",
      "year": 2025,
      "week": 9,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following was not one among the five tenets of the Panchsheel Agreement as signed in 1954?",
      "options": [
        "Peaceful co-existence.",
        "Respect towards each other\u2019s sovereignty and territorial integrity.",
        "Non-interference in each other\u2019s domestic matters.",
        "Mediation by a third party during conflict."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Mediation by a third party during conflict.",
      "year": 2025,
      "week": 9,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Who among the following is the author of Foreign Elements in the Hindu Population?",
      "options": [
        "B R Ambedkar",
        "Jawaharlal Nehru",
        "D R Bhandarkar",
        "V D Savarkar"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "D R Bhandarkar",
      "year": 2025,
      "week": 9,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following statements is incorrect regarding Ambedkar's understanding of democracy?",
      "options": [
        "For Ambedkar, democracy is the means and ends of forming an ideal society.",
        "Ambedkar argued that scientific outlook and rationality are not necessarily linked to the practice of democracy.",
        "In Ambedkar\u2019s view, democracy is not merely a form of government but also a mode of associated living where everybody is treated with respect.",
        "Ambedkar envisioned democracy as a medium of social transformation and human progress."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Ambedkar argued that scientific outlook and rationality are not necessarily linked to the practice of democracy.",
      "year": 2025,
      "week": 10,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is Ramabai\u2019s idea of true religion?",
      "options": [
        "Religion is about following sacred scriptures, and the priestly class",
        "Ancient Hinduism is the true religion",
        "Christianity is the true religion",
        "Religion is about acting according to one\u2019s conscience"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Religion is about acting according to one\u2019s conscience",
      "year": 2025,
      "week": 10,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "According to Ambedkar, which of the following institutions was the representative of the modern forms of parliamentary democracy in India?",
      "options": [
        "Buddhist Sanghas",
        "Mughal Durbars",
        "Islamic Madrasas",
        "Khap Panchayats."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Buddhist Sanghas",
      "year": 2025,
      "week": 10,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "\u201cA democratic form of government presupposes a democratic form of a society; the formal framework of democracy is of no value and would indeed be a misfit if there was no social democracy\u201d. The above statement was made by",
      "options": [
        "Jawaharlal Nehru",
        "Pandita Ramabai",
        "B.R. Ambedkar",
        "Mahatma Gandhi"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "B.R. Ambedkar",
      "year": 2025,
      "week": 10,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Pandita Ramabai is known as a devoted champion of women\u2019s rights in India. From the following statements, choose the one that most adequately explains her approach towards women\u2019s emancipation.",
      "options": [
        "Ramabai argued that the emancipation of women was possible through social reforms.",
        "Ramabai argued that the emancipation of women could be brought about through education.",
        "Ramabai\u2019s vision for women\u2019s emancipation was not limited to social reform and education alone. Liberating women through self-reliance was another essential aspect of women\u2019s emancipation for Ramabai.",
        "Ramabai held that it was only through Western liberal education that women could be emancipated."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Ramabai\u2019s vision for women\u2019s emancipation was not limited to social reform and education alone. Liberating women through self-reliance was another essential aspect of women\u2019s emancipation for Ramabai.",
      "year": 2025,
      "week": 10,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following institutions was not founded by Ramabai?",
      "options": [
        "Arya Mahila Samaj",
        "Mukti Sadan",
        "Sharda Sadan",
        "Seva Sadan"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Seva Sadan",
      "year": 2025,
      "week": 10,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Who among the following regarded Ramabai's conversion to Christianity as a radical act that challenged the upper caste Hindu patriarchal system?",
      "options": [
        "Kanshi Ram",
        "B.R. Ambedkar",
        "Jyotirao Phule",
        "Bal Gangadhar Tilak"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Jyotirao Phule",
      "year": 2025,
      "week": 10,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following, according to Ambedkar, is crucial for preserving and strengthening democracy in India?",
      "options": [
        "Embracing extra-constitutional methods in politics",
        "Fostering hero-worship of leaders",
        "Upholding political democracy alongside social and economic democracy",
        "None of these."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Upholding political democracy alongside social and economic democracy",
      "year": 2025,
      "week": 10,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "During the pilgrimages that Ramabai undertook during her childhood with her parents, she had the opportunity to learn many languages. Which among the following was not one of those?",
      "options": [
        "Marathi",
        "Bengali",
        "Hindustani",
        "Kannada"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Bengali",
      "year": 2025,
      "week": 10,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following is not an element of constitutional morality?",
      "options": [
        "Freedom and self-restraint.",
        "Recognition of plurality.",
        "Being sceptical of any personification of authority.",
        "Right to violent protest when necessary."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Right to violent protest when necessary.",
      "year": 2025,
      "week": 10,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "From the following statements, choose the one that is not correct regarding Ramabai\u2019s ideas as explicated in her book \u2018Stri Dharma Niti\u2019.",
      "options": [
        "In \u2018Stri Dharma Niti\u2019, Ramabai advised the wife not to disobey her husband.",
        "In \u2018Stri Dharma Niti\u2019, Ramabai presumed that domestic works were the primary responsibility of women.",
        "In \u2018Stri Dharma Niti\u2019, Ramabai supported child marriage.",
        "In \u2018Stri Dharma Niti\u2019, Ramabai supported marriage after attaining an appropriate age."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "In \u2018Stri Dharma Niti\u2019, Ramabai supported child marriage.",
      "year": 2025,
      "week": 11,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Ram Manohar Lohia is known as-",
      "options": [
        "A socialist thinker",
        "A capitalist thinker",
        "A spiritual thinker",
        "A communist thinker"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "A socialist thinker",
      "year": 2025,
      "week": 11,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "According to Yogendra Yadav, what was not among the three \u2018sins\u2019 that Lohia committed which ultimately led to the absence of Lohia\u2019s ideals in the public political discourse in India after his death?",
      "options": [
        "Lohia\u2019s personal attack on Nehru in a period when the latter was considered God-like.",
        "Lohia\u2019s campaign against English.",
        "Lohia\u2019s campaign against Hindi.",
        "Lohia\u2019s questioning of upper-caste dominance."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Lohia\u2019s campaign against Hindi.",
      "year": 2025,
      "week": 11,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Read the following two statements and choose the correct option from below- Statement-I: Ramabai argued that neither the male members from their own race nor any female teacher from a foreign land was appropriate for educating Indian women. Statement-II: Ramabai argued that the diffusion of knowledge should come from within, and native women teachers were more suitable for that task.",
      "options": [
        "Only Statement-I is correct.",
        "Only Statement-II is correct.",
        "Both Statement-I &II are correct.",
        "Neither Statement-I nor Statement-II is correct."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Both Statement-I &II are correct.",
      "year": 2025,
      "week": 11,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "In her autobiographical account, A Testimony of Our Inexhaustible Treasure, Ramabai had a critical outlook towards the Hindu Dharma Shastras. She particularly stated that all Hindu scriptures exhibited one feature in common: the marginalisation of women and ___________.",
      "options": [
        "Marginalisation of the Kshatriyas",
        "Marginalisation of the lower castes",
        "Marginalisation of the transgender community",
        "Marginalisation of the non-Aryans."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Marginalisation of the lower castes",
      "year": 2025,
      "week": 11,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "According to Ramabai, what were the presumed beliefs which led to the unwantedness of a girl child in India?",
      "options": [
        "It was presumed that a girl child was the property of someone else.",
        "It was presumed that a girl child would be of no use to her parents in their old age.",
        "It was presumed that it was only through the male child that salvation could be attained.",
        "All of these."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "All of these.",
      "year": 2025,
      "week": 11,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "On the questions of caste and modernity, which among the following thinkers can be regarded as a bridge between Gandhi and Ambedkar?",
      "options": [
        "Pandita Ramabai",
        "Jawaharlal Nehru",
        "Jyotiba Phule",
        "Ram Manohar Lohia"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Ram Manohar Lohia",
      "year": 2025,
      "week": 11,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Read the following two statements and choose the correct option from below- Statement-I: Ramabai argued that Indian women had a better status in the past in comparison to her contemporary degradation. Statement-II: Ramabai explains this degradation in the status of women in terms of the degradation of the Hindu nation.",
      "options": [
        "Only Statement-I is correct.",
        "Only Statement-II is correct.",
        "Both Statement-I &II are correct.",
        "Neither Statement-I nor Statement-II is correct."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Both Statement-I &II are correct.",
      "year": 2025,
      "week": 11,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "From the following statements, choose the one that is not correct regarding Lohia\u2019s \u2018principle of immediacy\u2019.",
      "options": [
        "Each action has an ethical justification intrinsic to itself.",
        "The ethical justification of each action is based on the present and not on the distant future.",
        "The principle of immediacy would save people from the politics of greed or fear.",
        "Human actions can only be justified in relation to their future implications, not their present ramifications."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Human actions can only be justified in relation to their future implications, not their present ramifications.",
      "year": 2025,
      "week": 11,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "According to Ramabai, which among the following stages of the life of a high-caste Hindu woman can be considered the most dreadful period for her?",
      "options": [
        "Childhood",
        "Adolescence",
        "Widowhood/Old Age",
        "Married Life"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Widowhood/Old Age",
      "year": 2025,
      "week": 11,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Ram Manohar Lohia\u2019s approach towards understanding social stratifications and inequality can be termed as",
      "options": [
        "A class-based approach",
        "A linguistic approach",
        "An intersectional approach",
        "A gender-based approach"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "An intersectional approach",
      "year": 2025,
      "week": 12,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Despite agreeing with Periyar on many political aspects, Ram Manohar Lohia also differed from him on certain occasions. What is not correct regarding Lohia\u2019s disagreements with Periyar?",
      "options": [
        "Lohia differed from Periyar on the issues of violent anti-Brahmanism.",
        "Lohia differed from Periyar in the latter\u2019s campaigns against Gandhi.",
        "Lohia differed from Periyar in the latter\u2019s campaigns against Hindi.",
        "Lohia differed from Periyar on the need to annihilate caste."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Lohia differed from Periyar on the need to annihilate caste.",
      "year": 2025,
      "week": 12,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "From the following statements, choose the one that is not correct regarding Lohia\u2019s views on the reservation system.",
      "options": [
        "Lohia was a major proponent of the reservation system in India as he thought that it would enable the entry of the marginalised sections of society into public life and administration.",
        "Lohia viewed that reservation was a means to secure selfish and individualistic objectives.",
        "Lohia viewed reservation as a means to bring social equality.",
        "Lohia also viewed that reservation could act towards the enhancement of national prosperity."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Lohia viewed that reservation was a means to secure selfish and individualistic objectives.",
      "year": 2025,
      "week": 12,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "From the following statements, choose the one that is not correct regarding Lohia\u2019s approach towards the caste system.",
      "options": [
        "Lohia regarded caste as both a discriminating social structure\u2019 and a disabling cultural phenomenon\u2019.",
        "Lohia argued that caste had a uniform mode of operation across the country.",
        "Lohia argued that the destruction of the caste system was not an easy task and required a multi-sided attack on the political, historical, philosophical and economic roots of the system.",
        "Lohia argued that in its form and operation, caste exhibited region-specific variations in the country."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Lohia argued that caste had a uniform mode of operation across the country.",
      "year": 2025,
      "week": 12,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Read the following two statements and choose the correct option given below- Statement I: Lohia was a prominent leader of the \u2018Angrezi Hatao Movement\u2019, and he advocated the replacement of English with the Hindi language as the lingua franca of India. Statement II: Lohia opposed English not because it was a foreign language but because it was, in the Indian context, a vehicle of inequality and social exclusion.",
      "options": [
        "Only Statement I is correct.",
        "Only Statement II is correct.",
        "Both Statements I &II are correct.",
        "Neither Statement I nor Statement II is correct."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Both Statements I &II are correct.",
      "year": 2025,
      "week": 12,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "The book entitled \u2018Marx, Gandhi and Socialism\u2019 was authored by which of the following political thinkers?",
      "options": [
        "B.R. Ambedkar",
        "Ram Manohar Lohia",
        "M.N. Roy",
        "Jayaprakash Narayan"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Ram Manohar Lohia",
      "year": 2025,
      "week": 12,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is/are not among the four key areas that Lohia considered important to root out the double oppression of the women of depressed castes?",
      "options": [
        "Re-examination of the institution of marriage and the hypocrisies involved.",
        "Equality in educational and property rights.",
        "Preferential treatment in politics and employment.",
        "Educating women on performing their duties as ideal wives and mothers."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Educating women on performing their duties as ideal wives and mothers.",
      "year": 2025,
      "week": 12,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "According to Lohia, the Indian ruling caste had three distinctive features. What was not one among those?",
      "options": [
        "English education",
        "Wealth",
        "Religion",
        "High caste"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Religion",
      "year": 2025,
      "week": 12,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "What was/were not included in Lohia\u2019s \u2018Sapt Kranti\u2019 (Seven Revolutions)?",
      "options": [
        "Satyagraha",
        "Destruction of castes",
        "Protection of private property",
        "Equality between men and women"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Protection of private property",
      "year": 2025,
      "week": 12,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Who among the following had proposed the idea of Chaukhambha Raj (Four Pillar States) that included: village, district, province, and center?",
      "options": [
        "Jayaprakash Narayan",
        "Rammanohar Lohia",
        "Jawaharlal Nehru",
        "Madan Mohan Malviya"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Rammanohar Lohia",
      "year": 2025,
      "week": 12,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Who wrote the text Hind Swaraj?",
      "options": [
        "Bal Gangadhar Tilak",
        "Jayaprakash Narayan",
        "Mahatma Gandhi",
        "Ram Mohan Roy"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Mahatma Gandhi",
      "week": 0,
      "year": 2020,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Who among the following argued about 'Integrated Theory of Evolution'?",
      "options": [
        "Sri Aurobindo",
        "M. K. Gandhi",
        "M. N. Roy",
        "B. R. Ambedkar"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Sri Aurobindo",
      "week": 0,
      "year": 2020,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which among the following texts was authored by B. R. Ambedkar?",
      "options": [
        "Annihilation of Caste",
        "The Life Divine",
        "Hind Swaraj",
        "Discovery of India"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Annihilation of Caste",
      "week": 0,
      "year": 2020,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Who wrote the text Reconstruction of Religious Thought in Islam?",
      "options": [
        "V.D. Savarkar",
        "Muhammad Iqbal",
        "Muhammad Ali Jinnah",
        "M. K. Gandhi"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Muhammad Iqbal",
      "week": 0,
      "year": 2020,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "The High Caste Hindu Woman was written by",
      "options": [
        "Mahatma Gandhi",
        "Sri Aurobindo",
        "Pandita Ramabai",
        "Tarabai Shinde"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Pandita Ramabai",
      "week": 0,
      "year": 2020,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one among the following sentences is correct about modern Indian political thought?",
      "options": [
        "It emerged merely as an Indian response to western challenges.",
        "It is a decisive break from the ancient and medieval Indian past",
        "It emerged in the context of colonialism and formation of nation-state in modern India",
        "There was hardly any difference among the modern Indian political thinkers about the 'idea of India'"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "It emerged in the context of colonialism and formation of nation-state in modern India",
      "week": 1,
      "year": 2020,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one among the following is a more appropriate method to study modern Indian political thought in contemporary times?",
      "options": [
        "Thinker centric approach",
        "Thematic approach",
        "Contemplative approach",
        "Traditional or conventional approach"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Thematic approach",
      "week": 1,
      "year": 2020,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one among the following sentences is not correct?",
      "options": [
        "Modern Indian political thinkers did not differ from their Western counterpart in terms of their metaphysical and epistemological assumptions",
        "Modern Indian political thinkers differed from their Western counterpart in terms of their metaphysical and epistemological assumptions",
        "They emphasized more upon synthesis rather than binaries",
        "Most of the political thinkers in modern India were deeply involved in the politics of their times"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Modern Indian political thinkers did not differ from their Western counterpart in terms of their metaphysical and epistemological assumptions",
      "week": 1,
      "year": 2020,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Who among the following is regarded as the father of modern Indian political thought?",
      "options": [
        "Ishwar Chandra Vidyasagar",
        "Raja Rammohan Roy",
        "Mahatma Gandhi",
        "Pt. Jawaharlal Nehru"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Raja Rammohan Roy",
      "week": 1,
      "year": 2020,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one among the following sentences is not correct about Raja Rammohan Roy?",
      "options": [
        "He supported the new system of education started by the Britishers.",
        "He was not an ardent supporter of modern liberal education in colonial India.",
        "He wanted Britishers to employ English gentlemen to instruct the natives of India in mathematics, philosophy, chemistry, anatomy.",
        "He wanted to promote modern scientific liberal education because of their practical values and necessity."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "He was not an ardent supporter of modern liberal education in colonial India.",
      "week": 1,
      "year": 2020,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one among the following texts is not written by Raja Rammohun Roy?",
      "options": [
        "Tuhfat-ul-Muwahhiddin",
        "Sambad Kaumudi",
        "Miraat-ul-Akbaar",
        "Third Answer"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Third Answer",
      "week": 1,
      "year": 2020,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Raja Rammohan Roy's Persian text Tuhfat-ul-Muwahhiddin is translated into English as",
      "options": [
        "A Gift to Theist",
        "A Gift to Atheists",
        "A Gift to Deists",
        "None of the Above"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "A Gift to Theist",
      "week": 1,
      "year": 2020,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one among the following sentences is not correct about the Brahmo Samaj?",
      "options": [
        "It was formed by Raja Rammohan Roy in 1828",
        "It sought to abolish the practice of idol worshipping",
        "It fought against the ritual practices",
        "It was open only for the Brahmins"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "It was open only for the Brahmins",
      "week": 1,
      "year": 2020,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one among the following sentences is not correct about Raja Rammohan Roy?",
      "options": [
        "He supported the monopoly of sacred education started by the Brahmins.",
        "He was an ardent supporter of modern liberal education in colonial India.",
        "He was in favour of employing English gentlemen to instruct the natives of India in mathematics, philosophy, chemistry, anatomy, and other sciences to promote modern scientific-liberal education because of their practical value and necessity.",
        "He was an ardent supporter of modern liberal education in colonial India."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "He supported the monopoly of sacred education started by the Brahmins.",
      "week": 1,
      "year": 2020,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Raja Rammohan Roy undertook the task of translating Sanskrit texts into vernacular language, because",
      "options": [
        "He thought that vernacular language was already started translation of Sanskrit texts into vernacular",
        "He completely learned and mastered language over Sanskrit",
        "He thought that it would end the monopoly of Brahmins over the sacred texts",
        "He thought that it would end the monopoly of Brahmins over the sacred texts"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "He thought that it would end the monopoly of Brahmins over the sacred texts",
      "week": 1,
      "year": 2020,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one of the following texts is not written by Rabindranath Tagore?",
      "options": [
        "Gitanjali",
        "Gora",
        "Ghare-Baire",
        "Anand Math"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Anand Math",
      "week": 2,
      "year": 2020,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Rabindranath Tagore renounced his knighthood in response to",
      "options": [
        "Jallianwala Bagh Massacre",
        "Partition of Bengal",
        "Non Cooperation Movement",
        "Simon Commission"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Jallianwala Bagh Massacre",
      "week": 2,
      "year": 2020,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one of the following statements is not correct about Rabindranath 2019s views on Zamindari system?",
      "options": [
        "He was a supporter of zamindari, he could sense the cruelty associated with the zamindari system.",
        "He was deeply apologetic and embarrassed about the whole system of zamindari.",
        "He was not able to associate himself with the system of zamindari.",
        "He believed that the manner in which zamindari system claimed to represent the interests of the people was flawed."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "He was a supporter of zamindari, he could sense the cruelty associated with the zamindari system.",
      "week": 2,
      "year": 2020,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "According to Tagore, the real problem of India is",
      "options": [
        "Economic",
        "Religious",
        "Social",
        "Political"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Social",
      "week": 2,
      "year": 2020,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one of the following thinkers defines nationalism as 'an imagined political community'?",
      "options": [
        "Benedict Anderson",
        "Rabindranath Tagore",
        "Mahatma Gandhi",
        "Jawaharlal Nehru"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Benedict Anderson",
      "week": 2,
      "year": 2020,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one of the following sentences is not correct about Rabindranath 2019s views on Nationalism?",
      "options": [
        "He identified the presence of specific challenges faced by India in developing its national self-consciousness.",
        "He wanted India to develop a nationalist self-consciousness grounded in the Indian cultural sensibility.",
        "He believed that India can develop its own national self-consciousness by imitating or accumulating ideas present in modern western texts.",
        "He emphasized the ideas of nation, nationalism to be grounded in the social."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "He believed that India can develop its own national self-consciousness by imitating or accumulating ideas present in modern western texts.",
      "week": 2,
      "year": 2020,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Tagore can also be regarded as a rooted cosmopolitan thinker. Because",
      "options": [
        "He respected Indian tradition",
        "He rejected the universal values of the West",
        "He respected the variety of traditions and nationalities, but also believed in the universal values",
        "He believed in the universal values of the East only"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "He respected the variety of traditions and nationalities, but also believed in the universal values",
      "week": 2,
      "year": 2020,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one of the following sentences is not correct about Rabindranath 2019s views on idea of man?",
      "options": [
        "He emphasised the emotional and ethical side of man",
        "He did not believe in the more or ethical aspect of human nature",
        "He was not keen on the more artificial side of man",
        "He believed that the best understanding of man is achieved through emotional and ethical side rather than the structural unity in man 2019s nature"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "He did not believe in the more or ethical aspect of human nature",
      "week": 2,
      "year": 2020,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Tagore was not in favour of Gandhian Satyagraha because",
      "options": [
        "He was not a practical idealist",
        "He was against using fasting by some of the followers of Gandhi to promote bigotry",
        "He believed that Satyagraha alone could not bring about independence",
        "None of the above"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "He was against using fasting by some of the followers of Gandhi to promote bigotry",
      "week": 2,
      "year": 2020,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one of the following modern Indian thinkers developed the idea of 'oceanic circle'?",
      "options": [
        "Rabindranath Tagore",
        "Jawaharlal Nehru",
        "Mahatma Gandhi",
        "Raja Ram Mohan Roy"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Mahatma Gandhi",
      "week": 2,
      "year": 2020,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one among the following sentences is not correct about Aurobindo 2019s political thought?",
      "options": [
        "For Aurobindo, nation was mother which he worshipped as divine",
        "He gave the idea of national education to be used as an instrument of political freedom",
        "He related the attainment of nationhood to the just about attainment of political freedom",
        "He believed that involvement of other revolutionary political activities was guided by his understanding of nation as a mother"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "He related the attainment of nationhood to the just about attainment of political freedom",
      "week": 3,
      "year": 2020,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Aurobindo was convicted and jailed for one year in which of the following events?",
      "options": [
        "Alipore Bomb trial",
        "Chauri Chaura incident",
        "Non-cooperation movement",
        "Khilafat movement"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Alipore Bomb trial",
      "week": 3,
      "year": 2020,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "After the freedom struggle in India, Aurobindo was associated with which one of the following groups?",
      "options": [
        "Extremist section of the Congress",
        "Moderate section of the Congress",
        "Servants of India Society",
        "Home Rule League"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Extremist section of the Congress",
      "week": 3,
      "year": 2020,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one among the following texts is written by Aurobindo?",
      "options": [
        "The Ideal of Human Unity",
        "Hind Swaraj",
        "Discovery of India",
        "Gita Rahasya"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "The Ideal of Human Unity",
      "week": 3,
      "year": 2020,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one among the following sentences is not correct about Aurobindo 2019s thought on self?",
      "options": [
        "For him, the first element in the universe of evolution which he calls Virat Purusha or supreme-being",
        "He argued that the individual self is the utmost development of his egoistic intellect or emotional cravings",
        "He believed that the individual self is the utmost development of his egoistic intellect or emotional cravings",
        "For him, the first element in the universe of evolution which he calls Virat Purusha or supreme-being"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "He argued that the individual self is the utmost development of his egoistic intellect or emotional cravings",
      "week": 3,
      "year": 2020,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one of the following signifies the true self as defined by Aurobindo?",
      "options": [
        "Ego",
        "Rational mind",
        "Spiritual individual or Virat Purusha",
        "Physical self"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Spiritual individual or Virat Purusha",
      "week": 3,
      "year": 2020,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one among the following sentences is not correct about Aurobindo 2019s views on Nationalism?",
      "options": [
        "Aurobindo envisioned nationalism merely as a political programme",
        "He had a religious conception of nationalism",
        "He believed nationalism as a religion offered by god and argued that god is immortal and so is nationalism",
        "He believed that nationalism can contribute in the larger human unity"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Aurobindo envisioned nationalism merely as a political programme",
      "week": 3,
      "year": 2020,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one among the following journals was published by Aurobindo?",
      "options": [
        "Karmayogi",
        "Kesari",
        "Samvad Kaumudi",
        "Young India"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Karmayogi",
      "week": 3,
      "year": 2020,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one of the following sentences is not correct about Aurobindo 2019s views on Gita?",
      "options": [
        "He argued that the text should not to be understood in its metaphysical constructs of ancient times",
        "He argued that Gita should be understood in its renewed relevance for the truth that it contains",
        "He believed that Gita shows us one was more future oriented rather than reverting to or reviving the past and did not believe that Gita could be a way to discover the future horizons",
        "He accepted and believed that Gita could be a way to discover the future horizons"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "He believed that Gita shows us one was more future oriented rather than reverting to or reviving the past and did not believe that Gita could be a way to discover the future horizons",
      "week": 3,
      "year": 2020,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one among the following characteristics is represented by Tamas as described by Aurobindo?",
      "options": [
        "The will to action",
        "The will to know",
        "The will to discover the truth of oneself and the world",
        "State of ignorance"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "State of ignorance",
      "week": 3,
      "year": 2020,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Who among the following was the spiritual guru of Vivekananda?",
      "options": [
        "Sri Ramakrishna",
        "Raja Rammohan Roy",
        "Mahatma Gandhi",
        "Gopal Krishna Gokhale"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Sri Ramakrishna",
      "week": 4,
      "year": 2020,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Where did Vivekananda deliver his famous speech on universal tolerance?",
      "options": [
        "World Parliament of Religion, Chicago",
        "Banaras",
        "Parliament House, London",
        "Brahmo Samaj"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "World Parliament of Religion, Chicago",
      "week": 4,
      "year": 2020,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which among the following sentences is not correct about Vivekananda 2019s political thought?",
      "options": [
        "He gave a new vision to Hinduism and the task to reinterpret Hinduism and distil it from dogmas, irrational beliefs and rituals",
        "He was a Vedantic scholar who believed in supreme truth or Brahma and we are all manifestations of that supreme reality",
        "He believed that the world was driven by mind or spirit and not by matter",
        "He believed that the world was driven by matter or physical things"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "He believed that the world was driven by matter or physical things",
      "week": 4,
      "year": 2020,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which among the following sentences is not correct about Vivekananda 2019s views on education?",
      "options": [
        "He believed that education is the process of man-making",
        "He believed that education is the process of learning from the hope and self-belief in achieving something",
        "He believed that education is the manifestation of perfection already in man",
        "He believed that education is the process of learning the scientific or technological teachings of the West"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "He believed that education is the process of learning the scientific or technological teachings of the West",
      "week": 4,
      "year": 2020,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which among the following sentences is not correct about Vivekananda 2019s views on religion?",
      "options": [
        "For him, the essence of religion was self-realization, social regeneration and harmony",
        "For him, religion was the realization of the self",
        "For him, religion was the realization of the universal and universal religion and universal integration of self and society",
        "For him, religion was a wider concept or universal in nature"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "For him, religion was a wider concept or universal in nature",
      "week": 4,
      "year": 2020,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which among the following sentences is not correct about Vivekananda 2019s views on freedom?",
      "options": [
        "Vivekananda believed that freedom was the key to a spiritual, social and political life",
        "For him, social and political liberty could be realized without moral, ethical and religious grant",
        "For him, freedom was essential for the growth of individual, social, political or economic life",
        "He considered that freedom is needed for keeping religious harmony and in realization of individual personality"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "For him, social and political liberty could be realized without moral, ethical and religious grant",
      "week": 4,
      "year": 2020,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which among the following is not the characteristic feature of democracy as put forth by Vivekananda?",
      "options": [
        "By democracy, he meant a representative or indirect form of democracy",
        "He saw democracy as a true making process which inculcates faith, self-reliance and self-government",
        "He said democracy is a process which enables individual to realize his true or true objectives in life",
        "He saw the same in inalienability of freedom, equality and unity made him espouse democracy as a way of life"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "By democracy, he meant a representative or indirect form of democracy",
      "week": 4,
      "year": 2020,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Who said that Vivekananda  2018was not politician, he was greatest of nationalists 2019?",
      "options": [
        "Mahatma Gandhi",
        "Sister Nivedita",
        "Subhas Chandra Bose",
        "Aurobindo Ghosh"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Aurobindo Ghosh",
      "week": 4,
      "year": 2020,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Where did Vivekananda establish the headquarter of Ramakrishna mission or Belur math?",
      "options": [
        "Jabalpur",
        "Jaipur",
        "Kolkata",
        "Ahmedabad"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Kolkata",
      "week": 4,
      "year": 2020,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Vivekananda was associated with which one of the following groups?",
      "options": [
        "Brahman Brahmo Samaj",
        "Christian Missionary",
        "Moderate section of Congress",
        "Extremist section of Congress"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Brahman Brahmo Samaj",
      "week": 4,
      "year": 2020,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one among the following books is written by Mahatma Gandhi?",
      "options": [
        "Hind Swaraj",
        "Gora",
        "Geetanjali",
        "Savitri"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Hind Swaraj",
      "week": 5,
      "year": 2020,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Mahatma Gandhi started his political activism in India with which of the following agitations?",
      "options": [
        "Champaran Satyagraha 1917",
        "Dandi March",
        "Khilafat movement",
        "Civil Disobedience movement"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Champaran Satyagraha 1917",
      "week": 5,
      "year": 2020,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which among the following sentences is not correct about the concept of Satyagraha?",
      "options": [
        "Satyagraha is a combination of two words Satya and Agraha",
        "Satyagraha neither implies the insistence on truth, but truth is ultimate and it is absolute",
        "Satyagraha enables the individual to stay put in the social reality until truth shall triumph",
        "Satyagraha can be understood only as truth or through violence"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Satyagraha can be understood only as truth or through violence",
      "week": 5,
      "year": 2020,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which among the following is not the correct virtue of a Satyagrahi?",
      "options": [
        "Non-violence",
        "Fearlessness",
        "Self-purification",
        "Hatred"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Hatred",
      "week": 5,
      "year": 2020,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which among the following sentences is not correct about the concept of Swaraj?",
      "options": [
        "Swaraj can be attained only through means of non-violence.",
        "Swaraj is the quest for self-rule and the quest for self-improvement.",
        "Swaraj is the quest for home rule.",
        "Swaraj is the quest for the quest for home rule."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Swaraj is the quest for the quest for home rule.",
      "week": 5,
      "year": 2020,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which among the following was not supported by Mahatma Gandhi?",
      "options": [
        "Satyagraha",
        "Sarvodaya",
        "Kinglynomy",
        "Brahmacharini"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Kinglynomy",
      "week": 5,
      "year": 2020,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Ambedkar's criticism of Mahatma Gandhi was based on Gandhi's views on ____________.",
      "options": [
        "Varnashrama Dharma",
        "Sarvodaya",
        "Swaraj",
        "Ahimsa"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Varnashrama Dharma",
      "week": 5,
      "year": 2020,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Who among the following thinkers believed that 'the necessity of ends and means was to attain ends and ends justify means' contrary to Mahatma Gandhi's ideas on means and ends relationship?",
      "options": [
        "Aurobindo Ghosh",
        "Raja Ram Mohan Roy",
        "Bal Gangadhar Tilak",
        "Rabindranath Tagore"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Bal Gangadhar Tilak",
      "week": 5,
      "year": 2020,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "With whom did Mahatma Gandhi sign the Poona Pact?",
      "options": [
        "Jawaharlal Nehru",
        "B. R. Ambedkar",
        "Sarojini Naidu",
        "Swami Vivekananda"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "B. R. Ambedkar",
      "week": 5,
      "year": 2020,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Mahatma Gandhi was critical of which of the followings?",
      "options": [
        "Ramrajya",
        "Village life",
        "Varnashrama dharma",
        "Modern civilization of the West"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Modern civilization of the West",
      "week": 5,
      "year": 2020,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one among the following sentences is not correct about the religious and political thought of Muhammad Iqbal?",
      "options": [
        "He emphasized on the self and human spirit",
        "He was an advocate for the capacity for self determination",
        "He emphasized on the self within a community",
        "He emphasized on the self at the service of divine"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "He emphasized on the self within a community",
      "week": 6,
      "year": 2020,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Who among the following thinkers has divided Iqbal 2019s works into three domains -  2018world of India 2019,  2018of Islam 2019 and  2018of Western thought 2019?",
      "options": [
        "M. H. Rizvi",
        "M. H. Askari",
        "M. H. Syed",
        "M. H. Azad"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "M. H. Rizvi",
      "week": 6,
      "year": 2020,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which among the following sentences is not correct about Iqbal 2019s views on Islam?",
      "options": [
        "He argued that the world of Islam has witnessed stagnation for centuries that has left it behind other traditions and the need for reconstruction of Islam without breaking away from the past",
        "He saw Islam as a moral and ethical ideal, independent from time and space",
        "He believed that Islam was a living tradition, which required the moral regeneration of man",
        "He believed that Islam was a static tradition, which required the moral regeneration of man"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "He believed that Islam was a static tradition, which required the moral regeneration of man",
      "week": 6,
      "year": 2020,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which among the following sentences is not correct about Iqbal 2019s views on Sufism?",
      "options": [
        "He was critical of the excessive emphasis on the mystical aspects of Sufism",
        "He believed that Sufism had contributed to the decline of the Muslim community",
        "He believed that Sufism had contributed to the moral and spiritual regeneration of human beings",
        "He believed that Sufism had contributed to the revival of the moral and spiritual values of Islam"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "He believed that Sufism had contributed to the moral and spiritual regeneration of human beings",
      "week": 6,
      "year": 2020,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which among the following best describes the meaning of the term  2018Khudi 2019 as described by Iqbal?",
      "options": [
        "Morality",
        "Empathy",
        "Self-realization",
        "Egalitarianism"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Self-realization",
      "week": 6,
      "year": 2020,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Who among the following people form the term  2018Millat 2019 refers to?",
      "options": [
        "Individual",
        "Nation",
        "Religious community",
        "Nationality"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Religious community",
      "week": 6,
      "year": 2020,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one among the following sentences is not correct about Iqbal 2019s views on Nationalism?",
      "options": [
        "His critique of the nation-state and call for the political re-organization of India were to relocate nation along the lines of religion",
        "He argued that the concept of nation and nationalism should not be understood as re-assertion of Pan-Islamism",
        "He did not view nationalism as a threat to the principles of Islam",
        "He considered western civilization and  2018nationhood 2019 as  2018handmaids of imperialism 2019"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "He did not view nationalism as a threat to the principles of Islam",
      "week": 6,
      "year": 2020,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "In Iqbal 2019s religious and political thought term  2018Qaumi 2019 refers to -",
      "options": [
        "National community",
        "Religious community",
        "Society",
        "Ethnicity"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "National community",
      "week": 6,
      "year": 2020,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Iqbal was associated to which of the following organizations during the freedom struggle in India?",
      "options": [
        "Hindu Mahasabha",
        "Muslim League",
        "Indian National Congress",
        "Swatantra Party"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Muslim League",
      "week": 6,
      "year": 2020,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one among the following texts is not a work by Iqbal?",
      "options": [
        " 2018Khudi 2019(Bang-i-Dara: S 0101yir-i-Iqbal/ Kala Iqbal)",
        " 2018The Development of Metaphysics in Persia 2019",
        " 2018Reconstruction of Religious Thought in Islam 2019",
        " 2018The Varieties of Religious Experience 2019"
      ],
      "correct_answer": " 2018The Varieties of Religious Experience 2019",
      "week": 6,
      "year": 2020,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Who among the following had inspired V D Savarkar 2019s thinking on nation and nationalism?",
      "options": [
        "Vivekananda",
        "Raja Ram Mohan Roy",
        "Rabindranath Tagore",
        "Mahatma Gandhi"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Vivekananda",
      "week": 7,
      "year": 2020,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "VD Savarkar was associated with which one of the following organizations?",
      "options": [
        "Arya Samaj",
        "Hindu Mahasabha",
        "Muslim League",
        "Indian National Congress"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Hindu Mahasabha",
      "week": 7,
      "year": 2020,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one among the following books is authored by V.D Savarkar?",
      "options": [
        "Gita Rahasya",
        "The First War of Independence",
        "The Reconstruction of Religious Thought in Islam",
        "The Spirit of Metaphysics in Persia"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "The First War of Independence",
      "week": 7,
      "year": 2020,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Who among the following is not associated with the nature of state 2019s authority for Savarkar 2019s political thought?",
      "options": [
        "The Hindu rulers of the past",
        "Shivaji, who according to him represented the rule of Swadharma and Swaraj",
        "The Muslim rebels of protest in the 1857 mutiny",
        "The British colonial authority"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "The British colonial authority",
      "week": 7,
      "year": 2020,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one among the following statements is not correct about Savarkar 2019s views on Hindutva?",
      "options": [
        "He wrote his famous tract for Hindu Rashtra in his major work Essentials of Hindutva 1923",
        "He defined a Hindu as one who regards India as his/her fatherland",
        "He defined a Hindu as one who regards India as his/her holy land",
        "He defined a Hindu in terms of a community that is not particular for religious ground or any other"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "He defined a Hindu in terms of a community that is not particular for religious ground or any other",
      "week": 7,
      "year": 2020,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Savarkar 2019s idea of Indian nationhood was not related to which one among the following major Indian languages?",
      "options": [
        "Hindi",
        "Maithili",
        "Marathi",
        "Sanskrit"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Maithili",
      "week": 7,
      "year": 2020,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "According to Savarkar which one among the following is not the correct criterion of Hindutva?",
      "options": [
        "Language",
        "Common laws",
        "Territorial unity",
        "Racial unity"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Racial unity",
      "week": 7,
      "year": 2020,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "With which one among the following thinkers did Savarkar have serious differences?",
      "options": [
        "Rabindranath Tagore",
        "Mahatma Gandhi",
        "Aurobindo",
        "Raja Ram Mohan Roy"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Mahatma Gandhi",
      "week": 7,
      "year": 2020,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "In which one of the following books did Savarkar critically examine the question of what constitutes a Hindu?",
      "options": [
        "The Creators of Hinduism",
        "The First War of Independence",
        "Six Glorious Epochs of Indian History",
        "Hindutva: Who is a Hindu"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Hindutva: Who is a Hindu",
      "week": 7,
      "year": 2020,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Savarkar defined Hindus in terms of three essential features. Which one among the following is not part of such features?",
      "options": [
        "As a race (Jati)",
        "As a religion (Dharma)",
        "As a culture (Sanskriti)",
        "As a language (Bhasha)"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "As a language (Bhasha)",
      "week": 7,
      "year": 2020,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one among the following books was not written by Jawaharlal Nehru?",
      "options": [
        "Glimpses of World History",
        "Discovery of India",
        "An Autobiography",
        "Hind Swaraj"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Hind Swaraj",
      "week": 8,
      "year": 2020,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one among the following sentences is not correct regarding Nehru 2019s views on socialism?",
      "options": [
        "Democracy and socialism are complementary to each other",
        "Nehru 2019s socialism is not congenial only in the presence of individual freedom",
        "Nehru 2019s socialism is not predicated as a moral concern",
        "The process of socialization in India should be a blind imitation of the Western model"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "The process of socialization in India should be a blind imitation of the Western model",
      "week": 8,
      "year": 2020,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one among the following is the idea of  2018Union of Democracies 2019 propounded by which among the following theorists?",
      "options": [
        "Harold Laski",
        "Florence Stansfield",
        "Ramsay Muir",
        "Gilbert Murray and Lionel Curtis"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Gilbert Murray and Lionel Curtis",
      "week": 8,
      "year": 2020,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Jawaharlal Nehru was the founder editor of which one of the following newspapers?",
      "options": [
        "The Leader",
        "National Herald",
        "The Hindu",
        "Amrita Bazar Patrika"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "National Herald",
      "week": 8,
      "year": 2020,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one among the following sentences is not correct regarding Nehru 2019s views on religion?",
      "options": [
        "He was critical of the traditional religious orthodoxy for its role in fostering religious dogmas and superstitions",
        "He argued that Indian society was divided by religious beliefs and practices",
        "He was in favour of the scientific temper in society",
        "He argued that Indian society was divided by religious beliefs and practices"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "He argued that Indian society was divided by religious beliefs and practices",
      "week": 8,
      "year": 2020,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one among the following sentences is not correct about Nehru 2019s secularism?",
      "options": [
        "His secular philosophy was based on neither irreligiosity nor just material well-being",
        "For him secularism was not about granting equal status to all religions",
        "For him no religion should have special privileges",
        "For him no community should be deprived of their legitimate rights on the basis of religion"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "For him secularism was not about granting equal status to all religions",
      "week": 8,
      "year": 2020,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one among the following is not part of essential features of secularism as argued by Nehru?",
      "options": [
        "Neutrality in religious matters",
        "No discrimination to all fellow religions",
        "No hatred and ill-feelings among different religions",
        "Secularization of all areas of life"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "No hatred and ill-feelings among different religions",
      "week": 8,
      "year": 2020,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Nehru had himself justified state intervention in which among the following areas?",
      "options": [
        "To curb the majoritarianism",
        "To assert the power of majority religious community",
        "To defend sectarianism",
        "To defend majoritarianism"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "To curb the majoritarianism",
      "week": 8,
      "year": 2020,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one among the following sentences is not correct about Nehru 2019s Discovery of India?",
      "options": [
        "Discovery of India was in many ways his own journey to understand and comprehend the timeless India",
        "He advocated a scientific temper of Indian history and philosophy",
        "He argued that India being based on religion and was not a secular democratic country",
        "He advocated for a scientific and rationalist worldview"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "He argued that India being based on religion and was not a secular democratic country",
      "week": 8,
      "year": 2020,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one among the following sentences is not correct about Nehru 2019s views on liberal democracy?",
      "options": [
        "He was in favour of democracy as the best means to secure both principle and in practice",
        "His conception of democracy was holistic to the individual and society",
        "For him democracy or democracy alone has both economic as well as social freedom",
        "For him democracy is not essential for both the individuals and society"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "For him democracy is not essential for both the individuals and society",
      "week": 8,
      "year": 2020,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one among the following sentences is not correct about Nehru 2019s views on internationalism?",
      "options": [
        "He believed that nationalism and internationalism can co-exist and emphasized on maintaining a balance between the two",
        "He was critical of excess nationalism and not merely nationalism which will be the unifying force in the future world",
        "For the peaceful co-existence of the international community, he preferred adjustments in national interests",
        "He was of the view that each nation can and should sustain and develop itself in isolation from each other"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "He was of the view that each nation can and should sustain and develop itself in isolation from each other",
      "week": 9,
      "year": 2020,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Nehru signed the Panchsheel Agreement, 1954 with which of the following countries?",
      "options": [
        "China",
        "Pakistan",
        "Nepal",
        "Sri Lanka"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "China",
      "week": 9,
      "year": 2020,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one among the following is not the correct feature of the Panchsheel Agreement?",
      "options": [
        "Peaceful co-existence",
        "Respect for sovereignty and territorial integrity",
        "Non-interference in each other 2019s internal affairs",
        "Promotion of military alliances"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Promotion of military alliances",
      "week": 9,
      "year": 2020,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one among the following was not the ground for Nehru to oppose the idea of  2018Union of Democracies 2019?",
      "options": [
        "It will be the elimination of war as dependent upon elimination of the roots of war",
        "It will be the perfect order of humanity",
        "In this world union nations will enjoy autonomy in their internal matters",
        "In this world union nations will not have equal representation at global level"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "In this world union nations will not have equal representation at global level",
      "week": 9,
      "year": 2020,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one among the following sentences is not correct about Nehru 2019s opposition to war?",
      "options": [
        "He was of the view that elimination of war is dependent upon elimination of the roots of war",
        "He believed that the world union nations will enjoy autonomy in their internal matters",
        "In this world union nations will not have equal representation at global level",
        "It will be the perfect order of humanity"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "In this world union nations will not have equal representation at global level",
      "week": 9,
      "year": 2020,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one among the following was not written by BR Ambedkar?",
      "options": [
        "National Problem: A Historical and Analytical Study",
        "The Problem of the Rupee: Its Origin and Its Solution",
        "Annihilation of Caste",
        "State and Minorities: Their Mechanism, Genesis and Development"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "National Problem: A Historical and Analytical Study",
      "week": 9,
      "year": 2020,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one of the following sentences is not correct about Ambedkar 2019s activities on Dalit rights?",
      "options": [
        "He used the facilities provided by the British government to petition for political rights of the Dalits",
        "He formed the Independent Labour Party to fight elections",
        "He formed the All India Schedule Caste Federation, 1942 for uniting the untouchables in India",
        "He did not introduce the Hindu Code Bill"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "He did not introduce the Hindu Code Bill",
      "week": 9,
      "year": 2020,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Ambedkar successfully negotiated with the British for the Dalit 2019s rights in which of the following events?",
      "options": [
        "Communal or Ramsay MacDonald Award",
        "Round Table Conference",
        "Poona Pact",
        "Simon Commission meeting"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Communal or Ramsay MacDonald Award",
      "week": 9,
      "year": 2020,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one among the following sentences is not correct about Ambedkar 2019s views on caste?",
      "options": [
        "He was in favour of caste prevailing in western societies",
        "He was in favour of caste system which is based on science",
        "In the pre-modern era, caste system was the Hindu social order",
        "He did not believe that caste system was the governing principle of the Hindu society"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "He did not believe that caste system was the governing principle of the Hindu society",
      "week": 9,
      "year": 2020,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one among the following is not referred to as a 'grammar of anarchy' by B R Ambedkar?",
      "options": [
        "Political parties",
        "Satyagraha",
        "Civil disobedience",
        "Non-cooperation"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Political parties",
      "week": 9,
      "year": 2020,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one among the following sentences is not correct about Ambedkar's views on liberal democracy?",
      "options": [
        "He was in favour of the parliamentary form of government. However, in his opinion, democracy is more than just representation",
        "He considered democracy as a mode of associated living and not just a political institution of representation",
        "He was critical of the idea of social good being served by democracy",
        "He supported the proposition that democracy is the medium of social transformation and human progress"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "He was critical of the idea of social good being served by democracy",
      "week": 10,
      "year": 2020,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "According to Ambedkar, preservation and strengthening of democracy require that it is guarded against three things. Which one among the following is not one of them?",
      "options": [
        "Denial of constitutional rights of politics",
        "Denial of social and economic democracy",
        "Denial of constitutional morality",
        "Denial of parliamentary democracy"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Denial of parliamentary democracy",
      "week": 10,
      "year": 2020,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one among the following is not correct regarding B R Ambedkar's conception of constitutional morality?",
      "options": [
        "Constitutional morality means effective coordination between conflicting interests of people",
        "It is not a natural sentiment and has to be cultivated",
        "It requires a government that is sensitive to the needs and aspirations of the people",
        "He believed that natural relations in human beings do not require cultivation of constitutional morality"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "He believed that natural relations in human beings do not require cultivation of constitutional morality",
      "week": 10,
      "year": 2020,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one among the following scholars has argued about Ambedkar as 'the caste leader, not the national statesman and a national statesman'?",
      "options": [
        "Eleanor Zelliot",
        "M N Srinivas",
        "Gail Omvedt",
        "Kancha Ilaiah"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Eleanor Zelliot",
      "week": 10,
      "year": 2020,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Ramabai is the author of which one of the following books?",
      "options": [
        "Guleri-Bag",
        "The High Caste Hindu Woman",
        "Gene-Barge",
        "The Discovery of India"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "The High Caste Hindu Woman",
      "week": 10,
      "year": 2020,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one among the following sentences is not correct?",
      "options": [
        "Ramabai played an active role in reform movement and tirelessly worked for women's emancipation",
        "She opened shelter homes 'Sharada Sadan' and 'Mukti Sadan' for destitute women",
        "She never argued about liberating women through self-reliance",
        "While championing the cause of women, she transcended the limits of gender reforms set by the male reformers"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "She never argued about liberating women through self-reliance",
      "week": 10,
      "year": 2020,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one among the following organizations was formed by Ramabai?",
      "options": [
        "Arya Mahila Samaj",
        "Bharat Stree Mahamandal",
        "All India Women's Conference",
        "Bharatiya Stree Sangh"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Arya Mahila Samaj",
      "week": 10,
      "year": 2020,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one among the following sentences is not correct regarding Ramabai's views on religion?",
      "options": [
        "For her, religion did not mean any particular religious doctrine whether Hindu or Christianity",
        "She said that religion is conduct and action in accordance with one's conscience",
        "In her book 'Stree Dharma Neeti' (Morals for Women, 1885), Ramabai emphasized more upon Hindu religion and Hindu nation and said that the Vedic text is not a source of salvation",
        "She was not in favour of salvation"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "She was not in favour of salvation",
      "week": 10,
      "year": 2020,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one among the following universities bestowed upon Ramabai the title of Pandita (Women Scholar) and Saraswati (Goddess of Learning)?",
      "options": [
        "University of Punjab",
        "University of Calcutta",
        "University of Cambridge, England",
        "University of Allahabad"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "University of Calcutta",
      "week": 10,
      "year": 2020,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which among the following sentences is not correct regarding Ramabai 2019s views on gender?",
      "options": [
        "She quoted Dharmar Nirnaya, Ramabai talks about the deplorable conditions of women in Hindu society",
        "She rejected child marriage and supported the idea that both men and women should choose their life partners",
        "Ramabai was one of the pioneers of the women 2019s education",
        "She did not ask to surpass the immediate gender roles ascribed upon women by society"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "She did not ask to surpass the immediate gender roles ascribed upon women by society",
      "week": 10,
      "year": 2020,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "According to Ramabai, Hindu sacred laws divide a Hindu woman 2019s life into three stages of life. Which one among the following is not in these stages?",
      "options": [
        "Childhood",
        "Marriage",
        "Widowhood",
        "Old age"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Old age",
      "week": 11,
      "year": 2020,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Who among the following shared the view that there is no hymn in the Rig-Veda which supports self-immolation of widows?",
      "options": [
        "Jyotirao Phule",
        "Raja Ram Mohan Roy",
        "Pandita Ramabai",
        "Ishwar Chandra Vidyasagar"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Raja Ram Mohan Roy",
      "week": 11,
      "year": 2020,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "According to Ramabai, which among the following was not the correct way to uplift the conditions of marginalized upper caste Hindu women?",
      "options": [
        "Economic independence of Hindu women",
        "Wider social reforms",
        "Wider access to education",
        "Wider access to property"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Wider access to property",
      "week": 11,
      "year": 2020,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which among the following books is an autobiographical account of Ramabai?",
      "options": [
        "The High Caste Hindu Woman",
        "Stree Dharma Neeti",
        "The Life and Letters of Pandita Ramabai",
        "A Testimony: An Autobiographical Treasure"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "A Testimony: An Autobiographical Treasure",
      "week": 11,
      "year": 2020,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Rammanohar Lohia was affiliated to which of the following political parties during the freedom struggle?",
      "options": [
        "Communist Party of India",
        "Congress Socialist Party",
        "Khilafat Dal",
        "Hindu Mahasabha"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Congress Socialist Party",
      "week": 11,
      "year": 2020,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following Indian languages did Rammanohar Lohia support to be recognized as the official language of India?",
      "options": [
        "Bengali",
        "Marathi",
        "Hindi",
        "Punjabi"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Hindi",
      "week": 11,
      "year": 2020,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one among the following is not the correct characteristic of a cosmopolite as mentioned by Rammanohar Lohia?",
      "options": [
        "A premature Universalist",
        "An inhabitant of superficial attainments of dominant civilizations",
        "An inhabitant of upper caste milieus without real contact with the people",
        "Both B and C are correct"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "A premature Universalist",
      "week": 11,
      "year": 2020,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Rammanohar Lohia sought the support of which among the following leaders to build a just society in 1960s?",
      "options": [
        "Jawaharlal Nehru",
        "Jayaprakash Narayan",
        "B R Ambedkar",
        "L K Advani"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Jayaprakash Narayan",
      "week": 11,
      "year": 2020,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Rammanohar Lohia was associated with which of the following Gandhian movements during the freedom struggle in India?",
      "options": [
        "Salt Satyagraha",
        "Non-Cooperation movement",
        "Civil Disobedience movement",
        "Quit India movement"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Quit India movement",
      "week": 11,
      "year": 2020,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which among the following book was not written by Rammanohar Lohia?",
      "options": [
        "Caste System",
        "Fragments of a World Mind",
        "The Wheel of History",
        "The High Caste Hindu Woman"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "The High Caste Hindu Woman",
      "week": 12,
      "year": 2020,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which among the following sentence is not correct about Lohia 2019s views on caste?",
      "options": [
        "He called himself anti-brahminism, campaigned against Gandhi, constitution for fighting caste based discriminators",
        "He considered caste as primary form of inequality existing in Indian society",
        "He gave a plan for caste reform different from the Marxists which/they focuses on class",
        "He placed greater emphasis on the gender based oppression along with caste"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "He called himself anti-brahminism, campaigned against Gandhi, constitution for fighting caste based discriminators",
      "week": 12,
      "year": 2020,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "According to Lohia, the process of modernisation of women Lohia focused on the four key areas. Which one among the following is not one of them?",
      "options": [
        "Abolition of the institution of marriage",
        "Abolition of purdah system",
        "Abolition of dowry",
        "Abolition of caste restrictions on marriage"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Abolition of the institution of marriage",
      "week": 12,
      "year": 2020,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "The formation of the Socialist Party convention in Panchmarhi, 1932 was famous for which of the following reasons?",
      "options": [
        "It was the first attempt at Socialist Party consolidation in post-independent India",
        "It was the first attempt at Indian Socialism independent of both communism and capitalism",
        "It was the first attempt at Indian Socialism independent of both communism and capitalism",
        "None of the above"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "It was the first attempt at Indian Socialism independent of both communism and capitalism",
      "week": 12,
      "year": 2020,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following is not part of Lohia 2019s conception of Sapt Kranti?",
      "options": [
        "Abolition of inequality based on colour and race",
        "Abolition of inequality based on colour and race",
        "Abolition of inequality based on gender",
        "Abolition of inequality based on caste"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Abolition of inequality based on colour and race",
      "week": 12,
      "year": 2020,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following is not part of Lohia 2019s conception of Chauhathkranti?",
      "options": [
        "Village",
        "Cottage",
        "Province",
        "Capital"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Capital",
      "week": 12,
      "year": 2020,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "To address the sensibilities and concerns of non-Hindi speakers, Rammanohar Lohia came up with a proposal. Which one among the following is not part of that proposal?",
      "options": [
        "He proposed Hindi as the official language of the central government with central government jobs reserved for non-Hindi speakers for a specific period",
        "He did not propose any group to abolish English both from internal and external communications",
        "He suggested a multi-lingual centre",
        "He suggested that a group of states could retain English to communicate with the central government"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "He did not propose any group to abolish English both from internal and external communications",
      "week": 12,
      "year": 2020,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following is not correct about the study of modern Indian Political Thought?",
      "options": [
        "It helps us to understand and interpret modern Indian society and politics better",
        "It helps us to understand the history of India, its various ups and downs as interpreted by the men and women who helped them shape",
        "Modern Indian political thinkers did not have metaphysical and epistemological assumptions different from West",
        "It helps us to understand the political and social ideas in the context of colonialism to orientalist thinking"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Modern Indian political thinkers did not have metaphysical and epistemological assumptions different from West",
      "week": 12,
      "year": 2020,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one among the following is the movement proposed by Rammanohar Lohia?",
      "options": [
        "Tebhaga Movement",
        "Civil Disobedience",
        "Salt Satyagraha",
        "Angrezi Hatao Andolan"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Angrezi Hatao Andolan",
      "week": 12,
      "year": 2020,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which among the following thinkers was the proponent of Hindutva?",
      "options": [
        "Mahatma Gandhi",
        "V.D. Savarkar",
        "Rammanohar Lohia",
        "Jawaharlal Nehru"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "V.D. Savarkar",
      "week": 12,
      "year": 2020,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Raja Ram Mohan Roy applied which approach to religious inquiry in public life?",
      "options": [
        "Rational approach",
        "Syncretic approach",
        "Submission to teachings of religious heads of an organized religion",
        "Total rejection of religion in public life"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Rational approach",
      "week": 1,
      "year": 2024,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which among the following sentences is correct regarding interlinkages between political thought and political theory?",
      "options": [
        "To be considered as political theory, it should inevitably be developed in the West",
        "Political theory is narrower in scope than political thought",
        "Both political theory and political thought are concerned with the understanding of politics",
        "Political thought is more systematic and generalized than political theory"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Both political theory and political thought are concerned with the understanding of politics",
      "week": 1,
      "year": 2024,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Raja Ram Mohan Roy was not influenced by which of the following events or ideas?",
      "options": [
        "Freedom movement in Spain",
        "Confucianism",
        "French Revolution",
        "Freedom movement in Latin America"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Confucianism",
      "week": 1,
      "year": 2024,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following does not qualify as the purpose of modern education for Indians?",
      "options": [
        "Modern education as an enabler of shaping the idea of an Indian nation in the psyche",
        "To facilitate the general public in engaging with the colonial administration",
        "Modern education as a tool for career advancement under British rule",
        "A means of social transformation"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Modern education as a tool for career advancement under British rule",
      "week": 1,
      "year": 2024,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following is not the reason presented by Raja Ram Mohan Roy to the British Crown to relax press regulation in India?",
      "options": [
        "Press as a grievance redressal mechanism",
        "Press as a necessity for the sustainability and durability of British rule",
        "Press as a rightful platform for revolutionary nationalist activities of Indians",
        "To keep a check on Christian missionaries who are meddling with the religious practices of natives"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Press as a rightful platform for revolutionary nationalist activities of Indians",
      "week": 1,
      "year": 2024,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which concept, rooted in the Indian tradition of political thought, moves beyond the binary of East and West, tradition and modernity?",
      "options": [
        "Shastrath",
        "Samvad",
        "Prativad",
        "Yoga"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Samvad",
      "week": 1,
      "year": 2024,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following sentences best characterizes modern Indian political thought?",
      "options": [
        "Modern Indian political thought emerged in the context of colonialism and the formation of a nation-state in modern India",
        "Modern Indian political thought represents a decisive break from the ancient and medieval Indian past",
        "Modern Indian political thought emerged merely as an Indian response to Western challenges",
        "There were hardly any differences among the modern Indian political thinkers about the \u2018idea of India\u2019"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Modern Indian political thought emerged in the context of colonialism and the formation of a nation-state in modern India",
      "week": 1,
      "year": 2024,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Raja Ram Mohan Roy has a favorable outlook towards the British Raj as -",
      "options": [
        "Raja Ram Mohan Roy considered that the natives of his period lacked the capacity for self-governance",
        "Raja Ram Mohan Roy thought that British rule would promote civil liberties",
        "Raja Ram Mohan Roy had chosen civil and religious liberty over political liberty",
        "All of the above."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "All of the above.",
      "week": 1,
      "year": 2024,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Who among the following is regarded as the father of modern Indian political thought?",
      "options": [
        "Pt. Jawaharlal Nehru",
        "Feroz Shah Mehta",
        "Jyotirao Phule",
        "Raja Ram Mohan Roy"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Raja Ram Mohan Roy",
      "week": 1,
      "year": 2024,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "According to The Press Regulation Act 1823, what were the grounds for restricting the publication of any document?",
      "options": [
        "Anything defamatory and harmful to the royal family, government officials, and their allied powers",
        "Publications threatening the peace, harmony, and social order",
        "Publication creating suspicion and hatred among the natives against the government",
        "All of the above"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "All of the above",
      "week": 1,
      "year": 2024,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following statements correctly describes the philosophy of Tagore?\ni) Rabindranath Tagore was a cosmopolitan thinker.\nii) He was a preacher of nationalism.",
      "options": [
        "Only i) is correct",
        "Only ii) is correct",
        "Both i) and ii) are correct",
        "Neither i) nor ii) is correct"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Only i) is correct",
      "week": 2,
      "year": 2024,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which aspect of nation and nationalism was most problematic for Tagore?",
      "options": [
        "That nation is an abstract entity",
        "Mechanical organization of State",
        "Grounded in the cultural sensibilities of the land",
        "Rootedness in spiritual imagination"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Mechanical organization of State",
      "week": 2,
      "year": 2024,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which work of Tagore signifies his disillusionment with the Swadeshi Movement?",
      "options": [
        "Birpurush",
        "Nationalism",
        "Geetanjali",
        "Ghare Baire"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Ghare Baire",
      "week": 2,
      "year": 2024,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which among the following does not explain the idea of cosmopolitanism envisioned by Tagore?",
      "options": [
        "It presupposes imitation of other nations",
        "It is rooted in one\u2019s own culture",
        "It is a critique of the statist conception of history",
        "Its ultimate end is to imbibe the unity of humankind"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "It presupposes imitation of other nations",
      "week": 2,
      "year": 2024,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "According to Tagore, Gandhi's basic education scheme was problematic on what grounds?",
      "options": [
        "It overemphasized material utility at the cost of the overall development of the students",
        "It limited the poor students to a definite vocation",
        "On both \u2013 a) and b) grounds",
        "Neither on ground a) nor b)"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "On both \u2013 a) and b) grounds",
      "week": 2,
      "year": 2024,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "In response to which of the following events, did Rabindranath Tagore renounce his Knighthood?",
      "options": [
        "Partition of India",
        "Non-Cooperation Movement",
        "The Holocaust",
        "Jallianwala Bagh Massacre"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Jallianwala Bagh Massacre",
      "week": 2,
      "year": 2024,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following is correct about Tagore's views on the Zamindari system?",
      "options": [
        "Tagore believed that the zamindari system which claimed to represent the people's interests was flawed.",
        "Tagore was genuinely apologetic and embarrassed about the whole system of zamindari",
        "As a practitioner of zamindari, Tagore could sense the cruelty associated with the zamindari system",
        "All of the above"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "All of the above",
      "week": 2,
      "year": 2024,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Tagore can also be regarded as a rooted cosmopolitan thinker because................",
      "options": [
        "He respected various individual traditions and nationalities but also believed in universal values",
        "He believed in the universal values of the East only",
        "He respected the Indian tradition",
        "He believed in the universal values of the West"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "He respected various individual traditions and nationalities but also believed in universal values",
      "week": 2,
      "year": 2024,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following sentences is not correct about Tagore's views on the idea of man?",
      "options": [
        "Tagore emphasized both the moral and the spiritual aspects of human nature",
        "Tagore was radical in his understanding of man and individual freedom",
        "Tagore also spoke about the duality in human nature",
        "Tagore did not believe in the moral or ethical side of man"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Tagore did not believe in the moral or ethical side of man",
      "week": 2,
      "year": 2024,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following sentences best describes Tagore's disapproval of Gandhi's Satyagraha?",
      "options": [
        "Satyagraha did not seem to be a practical idea for Tagore",
        "Tagore thought that Satyagraha alone could not bring about independence",
        "Tagore thought that Satyagraha was being misused by some of the followers of Gandhi to promote bigotry",
        "None of the above"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Tagore thought that Satyagraha was being misused by some of the followers of Gandhi to promote bigotry",
      "week": 2,
      "year": 2024,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Why do we need to revisit Aurobindo's thoughts today?",
      "options": [
        "While Aurobindo is selectively appropriated by the right-wing, secularists tend to distance themselves from engaging with his thoughts",
        "Although being a prominent philosopher of twentieth-century India, Aurobindo's work is not often read in totality",
        "Aurobindo is often relegated to a religious/spiritual figure",
        "All the above options are true"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "All the above options are true",
      "week": 3,
      "year": 2024,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "What did Aurobindo mean by the term 'passive resistance'?",
      "options": [
        "The nature of response must depend upon the nature of repression by the oppressor",
        "Violent revolution against the Raj",
        "Total submission to British rule",
        "Only constitutional engagement with the Raj"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "The nature of response must depend upon the nature of repression by the oppressor",
      "week": 3,
      "year": 2024,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one among the following sentences is correct about Aurobindo's political thought?",
      "options": [
        "For Aurobindo, the nation was symbolically a mother that he worshipped as a divine",
        "For Aurobindo, the struggle for nation and nationhood was not just about the attainment of political freedom",
        "Aurobindo's engagement with Swadeshi or other revolutionary political activities was guided by his understanding of the nation as a mother",
        "All the above options are true"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "All the above options are true",
      "week": 3,
      "year": 2024,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the meaning of 'True Self' as articulated by Aurobindo?",
      "options": [
        "Rational mind",
        "Truthful self",
        "Spiritual individual or Virat Purusha",
        "Physical self"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Spiritual individual or Virat Purusha",
      "week": 3,
      "year": 2024,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one of the following sentences is not correct about Aurobindo's views on the Gita?",
      "options": [
        "Rather than focusing on the relevance of the Gita in understanding the past, Aurobindo's approach towards it was more future-oriented",
        "Aurobindo argued that the text should not be understood merely in its metaphysical connotations of ancient times",
        "Aurobindo believed that the Gita could not offer anything in discovering the horizons of the future",
        "Aurobindo argued that the Gita should be understood in its renewed relevance of living truths that it contains"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Aurobindo believed that the Gita could not offer anything in discovering the horizons of the future",
      "week": 3,
      "year": 2024,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which among the following sentences does not explain Aurobindo's idea of the 'economics of spiritualized society'?",
      "options": [
        "It is to provide all men leisure for their inner development",
        "It is a way to offer all a prosperous and beautiful life",
        "It is to provide all men with the joy of work according to their nature",
        "It aims to create a machinery of production"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "It aims to create a machinery of production",
      "week": 3,
      "year": 2024,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one among the following sentences is not correct about Aurobindo's views on Nationalism?",
      "options": [
        "Aurobindo had a religious conception of nationalism",
        "Aurobindo believed that nationalism was a religion gifted by God and argued that God was immortal and so was nationalism",
        "Aurobindo envisioned nationalism merely as a political programme",
        "Aurobindo believed that nationalism could contribute toward greater human unity"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Aurobindo envisioned nationalism merely as a political programme",
      "week": 3,
      "year": 2024,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Rajas element denotes:",
      "options": [
        "A state of illumination",
        "A state of ignorance",
        "The will to action",
        "None of the above is correct"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "The will to action",
      "week": 3,
      "year": 2024,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "During the freedom movement in India, Aurobindo was associated with which one of the following?",
      "options": [
        "Extremist section of the Congress",
        "Moderate section of the Congress",
        "Azad Hind Fauj",
        "Muslim League"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Extremist section of the Congress",
      "week": 3,
      "year": 2024,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following texts was written by Aurobindo?",
      "options": [
        "New Lamps for Old",
        "Annihilation of Caste",
        "Hind Swaraj",
        "The Ideals of Hindutva"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "New Lamps for Old",
      "week": 3,
      "year": 2024,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following statements represents Vivekananda's thoughts on democracy?",
      "options": [
        "Vivekananda understood democracy as a process that inculcates faith, self-reliance, and self-government.",
        "For Vivekananda, democracy was equal to any form of direct rule.",
        "For Vivekananda, democracy was a mode of anarchy.",
        "By democracy, Vivekananda only referred to the indirect forms of representation."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Vivekananda understood democracy as a process that inculcates faith, self-reliance, and self-government.",
      "week": 4,
      "year": 2024,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "The compilation of the lectures given by Vivekananda in London was published as",
      "options": [
        "Karma Yoga",
        "Philosophical Vedanta",
        "A Memoir of London",
        "Practical Vedanta"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Practical Vedanta",
      "week": 4,
      "year": 2024,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following sentences is not correct about Vivekananda's views on the idea of freedom?",
      "options": [
        "Vivekananda believed that freedom was the key to a spiritual, social, and political life.",
        "For Vivekananda, freedom was essential for the growth of an individual's social, political. or economic life.",
        "Vivekananda opined that social and political liberty could be realized without paying attention to moral, ethical, and religious concerns.",
        "Vivekananda considered that freedom is needed for keeping religious harmony and in the realization of individual personality."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Vivekananda opined that social and political liberty could be realized without paying attention to moral, ethical, and religious concerns.",
      "week": 4,
      "year": 2024,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following statements captures Vivekananda's views on politics and religion most accurately?",
      "options": [
        "Politics and religion are two different domains.",
        "Politics and religion are inseparable.",
        "Religion is dependent on politics.",
        "All the above options are true."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Politics and religion are two different domains.",
      "week": 4,
      "year": 2024,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following statements does not correctly reflect Vivekananda's views on education?",
      "options": [
        "Education was to develop a holistic or complete personality, for which Vivekananda wanted a new and positive education.",
        "Vivekananda wanted the spiritual or religious teachings of the East to be combined with the scientific or technological teachings of the West.",
        "For Vivekananda, education was just about memory or the accumulation of facts and information.",
        "For Vivekananda, education could revitalize the masses or give them hope and self-belief in achieving something."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "For Vivekananda, education was just about memory or the accumulation of facts and information.",
      "week": 4,
      "year": 2024,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following is correct about the religion that Vivekananda wanted to promote?",
      "options": [
        "Masculine",
        "Rational",
        "Linear",
        "All of the above options are correct"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "All of the above options are correct",
      "week": 4,
      "year": 2024,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "In the views of Vivekananda, which of the following was not among the three ways of tackling the existing social concerns in India?",
      "options": [
        "Emancipation of Women",
        "Cultural Assimilation",
        "Positive Education",
        "Upliftment of the Masses"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Cultural Assimilation",
      "week": 4,
      "year": 2024,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Who among the following was the spiritual guru of Vivekananda?",
      "options": [
        "Mahatma Gandhi",
        "Shri RamaKrishna",
        "Raja Ram Mohan Roy",
        "Sankarcharyya"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Shri RamaKrishna",
      "week": 4,
      "year": 2024,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Where did Vivekananda deliver his famous speech on universal tolerance?",
      "options": [
        "UN General Assembly",
        "Brahmo Samaj",
        "World Parliament of Religion, Chicago",
        "Kasturba Ashram"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "World Parliament of Religion, Chicago",
      "week": 4,
      "year": 2024,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Where did Vivekananda establish the headquarters of Ramakrishna Mission which is known as Belur Math?",
      "options": [
        "Mumbai",
        "Kolkata",
        "Delhi",
        "Hrishikesh"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Kolkata",
      "week": 4,
      "year": 2024,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "According to Gandhi, what is the central quest of his work, Hind Swaraj?",
      "options": [
        "To envision a polity based on moral and ethical principles.",
        "To envision an ideal social structure.",
        "To chart out statecraft for an ideal polity.",
        "All the above options are true."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "All the above options are true.",
      "week": 5,
      "year": 2024,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "According to Gandhi, which one among the following is not an ideal virtue of a satyagrahi?",
      "options": [
        "Brahmacharya",
        "Selfishness",
        "Truthfulness or satya",
        "Fearlessness"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Selfishness",
      "week": 5,
      "year": 2024,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Who classified the political philosophy of Mahatma Gandhi as 'Pax Gandhiana'?",
      "options": [
        "Anthony J Parel",
        "Ramchandra Guha",
        "Granville Austin",
        "V R Mehta"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Anthony J Parel",
      "week": 5,
      "year": 2024,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Mahatma Gandhi was skeptical of which of the following?",
      "options": [
        "Ramrajya",
        "Varnashrama dharma",
        "Ahimsa",
        "None of the above"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "None of the above",
      "week": 5,
      "year": 2024,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "The Poona Pact was signed between:",
      "options": [
        "Mahatma Gandhi and Muhammad Ali Jinnah",
        "Mahatma Gandhi and Lord Mountbatten",
        "Mahatma Gandhi and B R Ambedkar",
        "Mahatma Gandhi and Jawaharlal Nehru"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Mahatma Gandhi and B R Ambedkar",
      "week": 5,
      "year": 2024,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following writers stated that Mahatma Gandhi was 'the single most important organizer of the numerous movements that cohered loosely as a nationalist movement against imperial rule in India'?",
      "options": [
        "Judith M Brown",
        "Ranajit Guha",
        "Ramchandra Guha",
        "Partha Chatterjee"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Judith M Brown",
      "week": 5,
      "year": 2024,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "According to Mahatma Gandhi, the European society was:",
      "options": [
        "A politically corrupt society.",
        "An embodiment of social justice",
        "A spiritual society",
        "A non-violent society"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "A politically corrupt society.",
      "week": 5,
      "year": 2024,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Mahatma Gandhi started his political activism in India with which of the following agitations?",
      "options": [
        "Quit India Movement",
        "Non-cooperation Movement",
        "Civil Disobedience Movement",
        "Champaran Satyagraha"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Champaran Satyagraha",
      "week": 5,
      "year": 2024,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "On which of the following issues, does Ambedkar have a significant disagreement with Mahatma Gandhi?",
      "options": [
        "Swaraj",
        "Ahimsa",
        "Varnashrama Dharma",
        "Sarvodaya"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Varnashrama Dharma",
      "week": 5,
      "year": 2024,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one among the following sentences is not correct about the concept of Swaraj?",
      "options": [
        "Swaraj is about self-government or the quest for home rule.",
        "Swaraj as self-rule is also about one's self and the quest for self-improvement.",
        "Swaraj can only be attained through means of violence.",
        "Gandhi wrote about Swaraj in his text Hind Swaraj."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Swaraj can only be attained through means of violence.",
      "week": 5,
      "year": 2024,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "According to Iqbal, what are the essential components of an ideal Muslim community?",
      "options": [
        "Only homogeneity",
        "Only unity",
        "Neither unity nor homogeneity",
        "Both the unity and homogeneity"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Both the unity and homogeneity",
      "week": 6,
      "year": 2024,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "From the following, choose the one that is not correct regarding the political thought of Iqbal-",
      "options": [
        "Qawm is understood as a national community",
        "Millat is understood as a religious community",
        "Qawm and Millat are not clearly separated by Iqbal",
        "Qawm and Millat are entirely exclusive of each other"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Qawm and Millat are entirely exclusive of each other",
      "week": 6,
      "year": 2024,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "In the political thought of Iqbal, the term 'Islam' denotes-",
      "options": [
        "A philosophy of life",
        "A way of living",
        "An embodiment of historical and cultural traditions",
        "All the above options are true"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "All the above options are true",
      "week": 6,
      "year": 2024,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one among the following does not correctly reflect Iqbal's views on Sufism?",
      "options": [
        "Iqbal did not repudiate the negative role of Sufis towards rationalistic philosophy",
        "Iqbal accepted the teachings of Sufism because it focused on the role of intuitions in the cognitive processes.",
        "Iqbal was critical of Sufi's preaching of men's withdrawal from the real world",
        "Iqbal believed that the mysticism of Sufis could not bring the overall development of human beings"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Iqbal did not repudiate the negative role of Sufis towards rationalistic philosophy",
      "week": 6,
      "year": 2024,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one among the following best describes the meaning of the term 'Khudi' as described by Iqbal?",
      "options": [
        "Respect",
        "Self-Affirmation or ego",
        "Ethics",
        "Morality"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Self-Affirmation or ego",
      "week": 6,
      "year": 2024,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "From which of the following philosophers, did Iqbal draw his ideas of 'ego' and 'superman'?",
      "options": [
        "Nietzsche",
        "Hegel",
        "Kant",
        "Socrates"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Nietzsche",
      "week": 6,
      "year": 2024,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Iqbal was associated with which of the following political organizations?",
      "options": [
        "Justice Party",
        "Azad Hind Fauj",
        "All-India Muslim League",
        "Hindu Mahasabha"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "All-India Muslim League",
      "week": 6,
      "year": 2024,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one among the following sentences is not correct about the religious and political thought of Muhammad Iqbal?",
      "options": [
        "Muhammad Iqbal emphasized the self and human spirit",
        "Muhammad Iqbal emphasized the capacity for self-determination",
        "Muhammad Iqbal emphasized the self at the service of the divine",
        "Muhammad Iqbal did not emphasize the self within a community"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Muhammad Iqbal did not emphasize the self within a community",
      "week": 6,
      "year": 2024,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "What was the title of Iqbal's doctoral dissertation?",
      "options": [
        "The Reconstruction of Religious Thought in Islam",
        "The Development of Metaphysics in Persia",
        "Gabriel's Wing",
        "The Secrets of the Self"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "The Development of Metaphysics in Persia",
      "week": 6,
      "year": 2024,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one among the following sentences is not correct about Iqbal's views on Nationalism?",
      "options": [
        "Iqbal's critique of the nation-state and call for the political re-organization of India were to reconstruct the nation along the lines of religion",
        "Iqbal did not view the nationalism as a threat to the principles of Islam",
        "Iqbal described 'Western civilization' and 'nationhood' as 'narcotics of imperialism'",
        "Iqbal's reformulation of the concept of nation and nationalism should not be understood as a re-assertion of Pan-Islamism"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Iqbal did not view the nationalism as a threat to the principles of Islam",
      "week": 6,
      "year": 2024,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "V.D. Savarkar was a proponent of which of the following ideologies?",
      "options": [
        "Socialism",
        "Marxism",
        "Hindutva",
        "Feminism"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Hindutva",
      "week": 7,
      "year": 2024,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Savarkar\u2019s idea of \u2018Hindu\u2019 had three essential criteria. Which one among the following does not constitute those?",
      "options": [
        "Hindu as a religion",
        "Hindu as a race",
        "Hindu as a civilization",
        "Hindu as a nation"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Hindu as a religion",
      "week": 7,
      "year": 2024,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following is not correct regarding the social and political thought of Savarkar?",
      "options": [
        "Savarkar thought that only the fittest can survive the struggle of life while the others get eliminated eventually.",
        "Savarkar believed in absolute morality and stated that the morality of an action can only be examined with its context.",
        "Savarkar believed that violence is natural to human society.",
        "Savarkar supported the principle of absolute non-violence."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Savarkar supported the principle of absolute non-violence.",
      "week": 7,
      "year": 2024,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "From the following statements, choose the one that is not correct regarding Savarkar\u2019s ideas on nationalism.",
      "options": [
        "Savarkar viewed culture, religion, race, and historical affinity as contributors to the formation of nations.",
        "Savarkar\u2019s ideas on nationalism were a synthesis of territorial nationalism offered by Congress and cultural-religious nationalism put forward by the Muslim League.",
        "Savarkar rejected the idea of territorial nationalism.",
        "Savarkar regarded one language and one culture (ek bhasha ek sanskriti) as the basis of the formation of modern nations."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Savarkar rejected the idea of territorial nationalism.",
      "week": 7,
      "year": 2024,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following works is authored by Savarkar?",
      "options": [
        "Six Glorious Epochs of Indian History",
        "Annihilation of Caste",
        "Nationalism without a Nation in India",
        "An Indian Pilgrim"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Six Glorious Epochs of Indian History",
      "week": 7,
      "year": 2024,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Read the following statements regarding Savarkar\u2019s idea of \u2018Hindutva\u2019 and \u2018Hinduism\u2019 and choose the incorrect one.",
      "options": [
        "For Savarkar, \u2018Hindutva\u2019 is a political doctrine.",
        "\u2018Hindutva\u2019 is a derivative of the larger category of \u2018Hinduism\u2019.",
        "\u2018Hinduism\u2019 is different from \u2018Hindutva\u2019, and it is only a fraction of the latter.",
        "\u2018Hindutva\u2019 is also about the history of Indian civilization."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "\u2018Hindutva\u2019 is a derivative of the larger category of \u2018Hinduism\u2019.",
      "week": 7,
      "year": 2024,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Savarkar wrote Life of Barrister Savarkar under the pen name of _________?",
      "options": [
        "Desabandhu",
        "Chitragupta",
        "Deenabandhu",
        "Chanakya"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Chitragupta",
      "week": 7,
      "year": 2024,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "According to Savarkar, which of the following Indian languages has the potential to preserve Hindu culture?",
      "options": [
        "Sanskrit",
        "Braj Bhasha",
        "Marathi",
        "Prakrit"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Sanskrit",
      "week": 7,
      "year": 2024,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Who among the following inspired V D Savarkar\u2019s ideas on nation and nationalism?",
      "options": [
        "Vivekananda",
        "Mazzini",
        "Mahatma Gandhi",
        "Ernest Renan"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Mazzini",
      "week": 7,
      "year": 2024,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Read the following two statements and choose the correct option from below:\nI. Savarkar did not negate the right of minorities to co-exist, but he made it conditional on the ground of their acceptance of Hindu dominance.\nII. Savarkar supported preferential treatment to those minorities who accepted his condition of accepting the domination of Hindus.",
      "options": [
        "Only the statement I is correct.",
        "Only the statement II is correct.",
        "Both (I & II) statements are correct.",
        "Both (I & II) statements are incorrect."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Only the statement I is correct.",
      "week": 7,
      "year": 2024,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "In which of the following sessions Congress passed a Resolution on 'Fundamental Rights and Economic and Social Change'?",
      "options": [
        "Kanpur Session of 1925",
        "Madras Session of 1927",
        "Karachi Session of 1931",
        "Nagpur Session of 1920"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Karachi Session of 1931",
      "week": 8,
      "year": 2024,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following statement/s is/are correct about the Nehruvian notion of democracy?",
      "options": [
        "Nehru's conception of democracy was also related to the notion of equality.",
        "Nehru envisioned India as a liberal democratic country both in principle and in practice.",
        "Nehru's understanding of democracy entailed economic and social dimensions.",
        "All the above options are true."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "All the above options are true.",
      "week": 8,
      "year": 2024,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following sentences is incorrect regarding Nehru's views on religion?",
      "options": [
        "Nehru\u2019s rational and scientific approach made him unwilling to participate in religious dogmas and superstitions.",
        "Nehru was skeptical of any form of organized religion.",
        "Religious beliefs and practices guided Nehru's general outlook towards life.",
        "Nehru was an ardent proponent of secularism."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Religious beliefs and practices guided Nehru's general outlook towards life.",
      "week": 8,
      "year": 2024,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Read the following two statements on Gandhi and Nehru's vision of state and economic development, and choose the correct option from below\u2014\nStatement-I: Gandhi and Nehru were unanimous on their idea of the state as a soulless machine and stated that it could hardly achieve any substantive development for the people.\nStatement-II: While Gandhi supported decentralization and small-scale industries, Nehru, on the other hand, was an advocate of centralized and planned economic development.",
      "options": [
        "Only statement I is true.",
        "Only statement II is true.",
        "Both statements I and II are true",
        "None of the above statements is true."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Only statement II is true.",
      "week": 8,
      "year": 2024,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following is not one among the five tenets of Panchsheel as propounded by Nehru?",
      "options": [
        "Peaceful co-existence and respect toward the sovereignty and territorial integrity of others.",
        "Non-interference in the domestic matters of others.",
        "Mediation by a third party during conflict.",
        "Recognition of equality and mutual benefits."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Mediation by a third party during conflict.",
      "week": 8,
      "year": 2024,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "The famous speech that Nehru delivered on the eve of India\u2019s independence is known as",
      "options": [
        "Tryst with Destiny",
        "My Vision for India",
        "The Future of India",
        "Swaraj is my Birth Right"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Tryst with Destiny",
      "week": 8,
      "year": 2024,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following sentences is incorrect regarding Nehru's views on socialism?",
      "options": [
        "Democracy and socialism are complementary to each other.",
        "Socialism has nothing to do with the practice of individual freedom.",
        "Nehru added a moral concern to the idea of socialism.",
        "Nehru argued that socialism in India should not be a blind imitation of the Western model."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Socialism has nothing to do with the practice of individual freedom.",
      "week": 8,
      "year": 2024,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Nehru was the founding editor of which of the following newspapers?",
      "options": [
        "National Herald",
        "Hindustan Times",
        "The Hindu",
        "Indian Express"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "National Herald",
      "week": 8,
      "year": 2024,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "According to Nehru, which of the following does not form the basic elements of the principle of secularism?",
      "options": [
        "The state should follow a policy of neutrality in religious matters.",
        "Secularization of all areas of life.",
        "The state should accord equal status to all religions.",
        "Total restriction on following any religious practices."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Total restriction on following any religious practices.",
      "week": 8,
      "year": 2024,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Read the following two statements and choose the correct option from the options given below\u2014\nStatement-I: Nehru had a broader understanding of democracy, and it also emphasized the social and economic dimensions.\nStatement-II: However, in his early life, Nehru\u2019s idea of democracy was limited to political democracy alone.",
      "options": [
        "Only statement I is true.",
        "Only statement II is true.",
        "Both the statements are true.",
        "None of the above statements is true."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Both the statements are true.",
      "week": 8,
      "year": 2024,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Why did Jawaharlal Nehru oppose the idea of the Union of Democracies proposed by American scholar Clarence K Streit?",
      "options": [
        "It excluded nations like China and India",
        "It included some nations that were imperialist and fascist",
        "Nehru believed that no democratic union is possible without ruling out colonialism and imperialism",
        "All of the above"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "All of the above",
      "week": 9,
      "year": 2024,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following is not a tenet of the Panchsheel Agreement 1954?",
      "options": [
        "Mutual respect for each other\u2019s territorial integrity and sovereignty",
        "Mutual non-interference in each other\u2019s internal affairs",
        "Mutual non-aggression",
        "China becoming a member of the Non-Alignment Movement"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "China becoming a member of the Non-Alignment Movement",
      "week": 9,
      "year": 2024,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Who among the following is the author of Foreign Elements in the Hindu Population?",
      "options": [
        "B R Ambedkar",
        "D R Bhandarkar",
        "Jawaharlal Nehru",
        "V D Savarkar"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "D R Bhandarkar",
      "week": 9,
      "year": 2024,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following was not a purpose of Bahishkrit Hitakarini Sabha formed by B R Ambedkar?",
      "options": [
        "To spread education among depressed classes",
        "To join electoral politics",
        "To promote socio-political awareness among Dalits",
        "To raise awareness about their grievances"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "To join electoral politics",
      "week": 9,
      "year": 2024,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "According to Ambedkar, in a democratic system, which of the following methods could be regarded as the \u2018grammar of anarchy\u2019?",
      "options": [
        "Civil disobedience",
        "Non-Cooperation",
        "Satyagraha",
        "All of the above"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "All of the above",
      "week": 9,
      "year": 2024,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "B R Ambedkar considered which among the following as the biggest stumbling block in making India a united political community.",
      "options": [
        "Caste",
        "Capitalism",
        "Religion",
        "Class"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Caste",
      "week": 9,
      "year": 2024,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following statements does not explain Nehru\u2019s views on nationalism and internationalism?",
      "options": [
        "Nehru considered cooperation among the nations necessary for their survival and progress",
        "Nehru believed that nationalism and internationalism could co-exist",
        "Nehru advocated eliminating war as it creates an environment of mutual hatred and fear",
        "Nehru was a vocal critic of the idea of nation and nationalism"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Nehru was a vocal critic of the idea of nation and nationalism",
      "week": 9,
      "year": 2024,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "On which fundamental issue did Ambedkar disagree with the leadership of the Indian National Congress?",
      "options": [
        "The issue of partition",
        "The issue of development",
        "The issue of women",
        "The issue of untouchability"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "The issue of untouchability",
      "week": 9,
      "year": 2024,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following political parties was founded by B R Ambedkar?",
      "options": [
        "Swatantra Party",
        "Praja Socialist Party",
        "Republican Party of India",
        "Independent Labour Party"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Independent Labour Party",
      "week": 9,
      "year": 2024,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "The Mahad Satyagraha in 1927, led by B R Ambedkar, aimed at:",
      "options": [
        "Asserting untouchables\u2019 rights to access public tanks and wells",
        "Securing voting rights for the Mahad caste",
        "Attaining a separate electorate for the Dalits",
        "None of the above"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Asserting untouchables\u2019 rights to access public tanks and wells",
      "week": 9,
      "year": 2024,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Eleanor Zelliot viewed Ambedkar as the performer of three roles; which of the following is not one among them?",
      "options": [
        "the caste leader",
        "an eminent lawyer",
        "a national stateman",
        "an untouchable spokesman"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "an eminent lawyer",
      "week": 10,
      "year": 2024,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following is an element of constitutional morality?",
      "options": [
        "Freedom and self-restraint.",
        "Recognition of plurality.",
        "Being sceptical of any personification of authority.",
        "All of the above"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "All of the above",
      "week": 10,
      "year": 2024,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which among the following is not a cardinal principle of social democracy, according to Ambedkar?",
      "options": [
        "Fraternity",
        "Liberty",
        "Equality",
        "Secularism"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Secularism",
      "week": 10,
      "year": 2024,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following is not a work of Pandita Ramabai?",
      "options": [
        "The High-Caste Hindu Woman",
        "Stri Purush Tulana",
        "Stri Dharma Neeti",
        "A Testimony of Our Inexhaustible Treasure"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Stri Purush Tulana",
      "week": 10,
      "year": 2024,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following institutions is not founded by Ramabai?",
      "options": [
        "Arya Mahila Samaj",
        "Mukti Sadan",
        "Sharda Sadan",
        "Seva Sadan"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Seva Sadan",
      "week": 10,
      "year": 2024,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Who stated Ramabai \u2018lived a life that was a prototype of feminist aspirations to succeeding generations of Indian women, but to her own generation her career appeared confusing, inconsistent, and even contradictory\u2019?",
      "options": [
        "Meera Kosambi",
        "Gauri Viswanathan",
        "V Geetha",
        "Nivedita Menon"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Gauri Viswanathan",
      "week": 10,
      "year": 2024,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which statements do not explain Ambedkar's understanding of democracy?",
      "options": [
        "For Ambedkar, democracy is the means and ends of forming an ideal society.",
        "In his view, democracy is not merely a form of government but also a mode of associated living where everybody is treated with respect.",
        "He stated that political democracy is incomplete without social and economic democracy and that all three are closely associated.",
        "He regarded that scientific outlook and rationality are not necessarily linked to the practice of democracy."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "He regarded that scientific outlook and rationality are not necessarily linked to the practice of democracy.",
      "week": 10,
      "year": 2024,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Who among the following regarded Ramabai's conversion to Christianity a radical act challenging the upper caste Hindu patriarchal system?",
      "options": [
        "Bal Gangadhar Tilak",
        "Kanshi Ram",
        "B.R. Ambedkar",
        "Jyotirao Phule"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Jyotirao Phule",
      "week": 10,
      "year": 2024,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is Ramabai\u2019s idea of true religion?",
      "options": [
        "Religion is about acting according to one\u2019s conscience.",
        "Religion is about following sacred scriptures and priestly class",
        "Ancient Hinduism is the true religion.",
        "Christianity is the true religion."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Religion is about acting according to one\u2019s conscience.",
      "week": 10,
      "year": 2024,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following does Ambedkar emphasize as crucial for preserving and strengthening democracy in India?",
      "options": [
        "embracing extra-constitutional methods in politics",
        "fostering hero-worship towards leaders",
        "upholding political democracy alongside social and economic democracy",
        "All of the above"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "upholding political democracy alongside social and economic democracy",
      "week": 10,
      "year": 2024,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following were the two worldviews that Lohia distinguished between while conceptualizing his idea of real modernity?",
      "options": [
        "Indigenous worldview and Eurocentric worldview",
        "Eurocentric worldview and Indian worldview",
        "Side-looking worldview and Forward-looking worldview",
        "Backward-looking worldview and Forward-looking worldview"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Side-looking worldview and Forward-looking worldview",
      "week": 11,
      "year": 2024,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which among the following is not one of the three ways that Pandita Ramabai argued for uplifting the conditions of marginalized upper-caste Hindu women?",
      "options": [
        "Performance of religious rituals",
        "Self-reliance",
        "Education",
        "Native women teachers"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Performance of religious rituals",
      "week": 11,
      "year": 2024,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Who among the following is not a founding member of the Congress Socialist Party?",
      "options": [
        "Jayaprakash Narayan",
        "Acharya Narendra Deva",
        "Ram Manohar Lohia",
        "Jawaharlal Nehru"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Jawaharlal Nehru",
      "week": 11,
      "year": 2024,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Ram Manohar Lohia is regarded as an intellectual within which of the following traditions of thought?",
      "options": [
        "Socialism",
        "Spirituality",
        "Capitalism",
        "Environmentalism"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Socialism",
      "week": 11,
      "year": 2024,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Lohia stated that Gandhians can be categorized into three types. Which of the following terms was not articulated by him?",
      "options": [
        "Priestly Gandhian",
        "Governmental Gandhian",
        "Heretic Gandhian",
        "Spiritual Gandhian"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Spiritual Gandhian",
      "week": 11,
      "year": 2024,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following statements does not represent the political ideas of Ram Manohar Lohia?",
      "options": [
        "He argued for indigenous solution to Indian problems.",
        "He was critical of both capitalism and communism.",
        "He formulated a very distinct Indian version of socialism.",
        "He did not consider caste as the root cause of social and economic inequality in India."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "He did not consider caste as the root cause of social and economic inequality in India.",
      "week": 11,
      "year": 2024,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following is not one of the \u2018three sins\u2019 that, according to Yogendra Yadav, Lohia committed, leading to his marginalization in Indian political discourse?",
      "options": [
        "Lohia\u2019s criticism of Nehru",
        "His vigorous and voluble campaign against English",
        "His public questioning of upper-caste dominance and support to advance the caste-based affirmative actions",
        "Lohia's criticism of Capitalism and Communism"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Lohia's criticism of Capitalism and Communism",
      "week": 11,
      "year": 2024,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following statements is incorrect regarding Lohia\u2019s idea of the \u2018Principle of immediacy\u2019?",
      "options": [
        "The ethical justification of each action is based on the present rather than the distant future.",
        "Each action would have ethical justification intrinsic to itself.",
        "This principle would save people from the politics of greed or fear.",
        "None of the statements is incorrect."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "None of the statements is incorrect.",
      "week": 11,
      "year": 2024,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Who is considered as a bridge between Gandhi\u2019s and Ambedkar\u2019s political thought concerning the questions of caste and modernity?",
      "options": [
        "Ram Manohar Lohia",
        "Pandita Ramabai",
        "Vinoba Bhave",
        "Acharya Narendra Deva"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Ram Manohar Lohia",
      "week": 11,
      "year": 2024,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Among the following, which one is an autobiographical account by Pandita Ramabai?",
      "options": [
        "A Testimony of Our Inexhaustible Treasure",
        "Stri Dharma Niti",
        "The High-Caste Hindu Woman",
        "None of the above"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "A Testimony of Our Inexhaustible Treasure",
      "week": 11,
      "year": 2024,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following books is not written by Ram Manohar Lohia?",
      "options": [
        "The Caste System",
        "Marx, Gandhi and Socialism",
        "The Wheel of History",
        "Socialism: Utopian and Scientific"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Socialism: Utopian and Scientific",
      "week": 12,
      "year": 2024,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following is not part of Lohia\u2019s intellectual responses to the language question?",
      "options": [
        "He advocated Hindustani to be the language of the Union.",
        "He moved towards a two-department thesis to include the Hindi and non-Hindi sections in the government.",
        "He proposed a multi-lingual centre involving 14 official languages.",
        "He proposed using only Hindi and English, advocating a ban on other Indian languages at the national level."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "He proposed using only Hindi and English, advocating a ban on other Indian languages at the national level.",
      "week": 12,
      "year": 2024,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following is not correct regarding Lohia's views on caste?",
      "options": [
        "He recognized caste as one of the primary forms of inequality in the Indian society.",
        "He advocated for eliminating caste as mere reforms were considered inadequate by him.",
        "He believed that there was an oscillation between caste and class.",
        "He believed in violent anti-Brahmanism"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "He believed in violent anti-Brahmanism",
      "week": 12,
      "year": 2024,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Sapt Kranti or Seven Revolution concept was propounded by:",
      "options": [
        "Jay Prakash Narayan",
        "B R Ambedkar",
        "Ram Manohar Lohia",
        "Deen Dayal Upadhyaya"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Ram Manohar Lohia",
      "week": 12,
      "year": 2024,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following is not associated with Lohia\u2019s idea of a four-pillar state (Chaukhamba Raj)?",
      "options": [
        "Village",
        "Nation",
        "Centre",
        "Province"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Nation",
      "week": 12,
      "year": 2024,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "According to Lohia, which of the following is not one of the defining characteristics of the ruling class in India?",
      "options": [
        "High Caste",
        "English Education",
        "Wealth",
        "Membership in the Congress party"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Membership in the Congress party",
      "week": 12,
      "year": 2024,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which among the following statements does not explain Lohia\u2019s critique of English?",
      "options": [
        "He critiqued the domination of the English language",
        "He abhorred English as a language",
        "According to him, the exclusion of Indian languages has led to the exclusion of Indian masses from power echelons of Indian politics and administration.",
        "He was concerned about the domination of the English language as it damages Indian political thinking and reduces it to derivative thinking"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "He abhorred English as a language",
      "week": 12,
      "year": 2024,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which among the following is the presidential speech delivered by Lohia at the Socialist Party Convention in 1952:",
      "options": [
        "Doctrinal Foundations of Socialism",
        "Doctrinal Foundations of Communism",
        "Caste and Social Democracy",
        "Political Participation of Dalits"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Doctrinal Foundations of Socialism",
      "week": 12,
      "year": 2024,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Lohia recognized the double oppression of women from depressed classes and suggested four critical areas of work to improve their conditions. Which among the following options encompasses those solutions?",
      "options": [
        "Preferential treatment in politics and employment",
        "Equality in educational and property rights",
        "Re-examination of the institutions of marriage",
        "All of the above"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "All of the above",
      "week": 12,
      "year": 2024,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following is not an element of Lohia\u2019s political thought?",
      "options": [
        "Critique of the model of development followed by both the Soviet-style Socialism and Capitalism",
        "Twin origins of Capitalism and Colonialism",
        "Inclusion of women of every caste in the category of the Shudras to uncover the extent of their marginalization in Indian society",
        "Linguistic cultural chauvinism"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Linguistic cultural chauvinism",
      "week": 12,
      "year": 2024,
      "subject": "mipt"
    },
    {
      "question": "During facing operation in a conventional lathe the cutting velocity 46 mm",
      "options": [
        "Increases with feed",
        "Decreases with feed",
        "Unrelated to feed",
        "None of these"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Unrelated to feed",
      "week": 0,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "On a lathe, you change settings in the machine to double the rotational speed of the spindle. This will also",
      "options": [
        "Double the feed (mm/rev) of the tool",
        "Halve the feed (mm/rev) of the tool",
        "Not affect the tool feed (mm/rev) at all",
        "Depends on whether the feed is longitudinal (mm/rev) or cross feed (mm/rev)"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Not affect the tool feed (mm/rev) at all",
      "week": 0,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one is not a cutting tool material?",
      "options": [
        "High speed steel",
        "Tungsten carbide",
        "Stainless steel",
        "Ceramic"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Stainless steel",
      "week": 0,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is not true in case of CNC machining centre (Milling).",
      "options": [
        "Machining is performed by writing a code in the computer",
        "3D (complex) surfaces can be machined",
        "Many types of operations can be performed in a single setup of workpiece",
        "It cannot be used for non-metallic materials."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "It cannot be used for non-metallic materials.",
      "week": 0,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "Feed used in thread cutting usually has the following relation with feed used in straight turning.",
      "options": [
        "Higher",
        "Equal",
        "Lower",
        "Unrelated"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Lower",
      "week": 0,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "In up milling operation,",
      "options": [
        "direction of rotation of cutter is same as direction of table movement",
        "direction of rotation of cutter is opposite to direction of table movement",
        "there is no such relation between directions of cutter and table movement",
        "none of the above"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "direction of rotation of cutter is opposite to direction of table movement",
      "week": 0,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "A job of diameter 100 mm is being turned using a cutting speed of 30 m/min. The corresponding feed is",
      "options": [
        "0.1 mm/rev",
        "10 mm/min",
        "300 \u03bcm",
        "not known"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "0.1 mm/rev",
      "week": 0,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "Minimum number of axis in CNC turning centre (Lathe) and CNC machining centre (Milling) respectively are",
      "options": [
        "2 and 3",
        "3 and 3",
        "3 and 2",
        "4 and 4"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "2 and 3",
      "week": 0,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "A perfect square on the end of a round shaft can be milled by mounting it on",
      "options": [
        "A differential",
        "A compound rest",
        "An index plate",
        "A dividing head"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "A dividing head",
      "week": 0,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "The arbor of the milling machine is used to hold",
      "options": [
        "Spindle",
        "Cutting tool",
        "Workpiece",
        "Mandrel"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Cutting tool",
      "week": 0,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is correct in context of miniaturization?",
      "options": [
        "Low accuracy and sensitivity",
        "High cost to performance ratio",
        "Faster device",
        "High energy required for excitation"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Faster device",
      "week": 1,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is MCU?",
      "options": [
        "Mechanical Control Unit",
        "Mechanical Central Unit",
        "Machine Control Unit",
        "Machine Central Unit"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Machine Control Unit",
      "week": 1,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following is a hybrid machining process?",
      "options": [
        "ECM",
        "EDM",
        "LBM",
        "ECDM"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "ECDM",
      "week": 1,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following is a material removal process?",
      "options": [
        "Forming",
        "Welding",
        "3D Printing",
        "Grinding"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Grinding",
      "week": 1,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "The feature tolerance of an object is 0.001mm and its size is 10 mm, then its relative accuracy will be",
      "options": [
        "0.01",
        "10^4",
        "10.001",
        "10^-4"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "10^-4",
      "week": 1,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "Most widely used workpiece material in MEMS based process is",
      "options": [
        "Steel",
        "Silicon",
        "Copper",
        "Aluminum"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Silicon",
      "week": 1,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "Tool used in ultra-precision machining is",
      "options": [
        "WC",
        "HSS",
        "Natural Diamond Tool",
        "CBN"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Natural Diamond Tool",
      "week": 1,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following is a high production rate process?",
      "options": [
        "Mechanical micro machining",
        "MEMS based processes",
        "Ultra precision machining",
        "Additive manufacturing processes"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "MEMS based processes",
      "week": 1,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following path is a 3D machining or movement? (A \u2013 Starting point and D \u2013 Target point)?",
      "options": [
        "A\u2014G\u2014D",
        "A\u2014B\u2014D",
        "A\u2014F\u2014D",
        "A\u2014D"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "A\u2014D",
      "week": 1,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "Machine tool feedback device gives information of",
      "options": [
        "Position and velocity",
        "Cutting temperature",
        "Condition of cutting tool",
        "Vibration"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Position and velocity",
      "week": 1,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "Small things are less affected by",
      "options": [
        "Mass",
        "Inertia",
        "Heat Storage",
        "All of the above",
        "Only (a) and (b)",
        "Only (a) and (c)"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "All of the above",
      "week": 2,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "Surface tension is scaled with length at",
      "options": [
        "l^3",
        "l^2",
        "l^1",
        "l^5"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "l^1",
      "week": 2,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one of the following is scaled with length at l^1?",
      "options": [
        "Area",
        "Surface tension",
        "Resistance",
        "Moment of inertia"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Resistance",
      "week": 2,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "When the radius of the pipe is scaled down proportionally,",
      "options": [
        "Volumetric Flow and pressure drop per unit length both increase",
        "Volumetric Flow decreases and pressure drop per unit length increases",
        "Volumetric Flow and pressure drop per unit length both decrease",
        "Volumetric Flow increases and pressure drop per unit length decreases"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Volumetric Flow decreases and pressure drop per unit length increases",
      "week": 2,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "Main driving factor in scaling law is",
      "options": [
        "Weight to volume ratio",
        "Surface area to volume ratio",
        "Length to surface area ratio",
        "Surface finish to tolerance ratio"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Surface area to volume ratio",
      "week": 2,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is less effective at small scale",
      "options": [
        "Electrostatic forces",
        "Surface tension",
        "Inertial forces",
        "All the above",
        "Both (a) and (b)",
        "Both (a) and (c)"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Inertial forces",
      "week": 2,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "A square cantilever beam as shown in Figure below is scaled down proportionally (L and b) from 8 to 0.2. Maximum bending stress at the constraint",
      "options": [
        "Decreases 40 times",
        "Increases 40 times",
        "Decreases 1600 times",
        "Increases 1600 times"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Increases 1600 times",
      "week": 2,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "When the radius of the pipe is scaled down from 5 mm to 0.5 mm, rate of volumetric flow?",
      "options": [
        "Decreases 10 times",
        "Increases 10 times",
        "Increases 10000 times",
        "Decreases 10000 times"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Decreases 10000 times",
      "week": 2,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "Small uncut chip thickness is responsible for",
      "options": [
        "High Cutting Temperature",
        "High Shear Yield Strength of workpiece",
        "Low friction coefficient",
        "All of the above",
        "Only (a) and (c)",
        "Only (b) and (c)"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "High Shear Yield Strength of workpiece",
      "week": 2,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "Size effect has influence on",
      "options": [
        "Chip Thickness",
        "Chip formation",
        "Cutting Force",
        "All of the above",
        "Only (a) and (c)",
        "Only (b) and (c)"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "All of the above",
      "week": 2,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "In micro machining, generally the ratio of uncut chip thickness to cutting edge radius is",
      "options": [
        "Infinite",
        "Less than or equal to 1",
        "Very Large",
        "Zero"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Less than or equal to 1",
      "week": 3,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following step of failure of ductile material is shown in below figure?",
      "options": [
        "Inclusion",
        "Void growth",
        "Void Nucleation",
        "Necking between voids"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Necking between voids",
      "week": 3,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following material removal mechanism has significant effect on surface quality deterioration?",
      "options": [
        "Shearing",
        "Ploughing",
        "Rubbing",
        "Extrusion"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Rubbing",
      "week": 3,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which plane of Silicon is the strongest?",
      "options": [
        "100",
        "110",
        "101",
        "111"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "111",
      "week": 3,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following is the unit of specific cutting energy?",
      "options": [
        "J/mm^3",
        "J/mm^2",
        "N/mm",
        "W/mm^3"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "J/mm^3",
      "week": 3,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "Micro cutting of grains having different orientations would result in",
      "options": [
        "High fluctuation of cutting force",
        "Tool breakage",
        "High surface roughness",
        "All of the above",
        "Only (a) and (b)",
        "Only (a) and (c)"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "All of the above",
      "week": 3,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is minimum uncut chip thickness?",
      "options": [
        "It is the minimum thickness of the uncut chip to avoid shearing of material during machining",
        "It is the minimum thickness of the uncut chip to reduce the tool wear",
        "It is the minimum thickness of the uncut chip to reduce built-up edge formation",
        "It is the minimum thickness of the uncut chip to remove material in the form of chip"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "It is the minimum thickness of the uncut chip to remove material in the form of chip",
      "week": 3,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one is the correct sequence of material removal mechanism with increase in the rake angle on negative side?",
      "options": [
        "Shearing  Extrusion  Ploughing  Rubbing",
        "Shearing Ploughing Extrusion Rubbing",
        "Shearing Rubbing Ploughing Extrusion",
        "Extrusion  Shearing  Ploughing  Rubbing"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Shearing  Extrusion  Ploughing  Rubbing",
      "week": 3,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is not correct with reference to anisotropic material?",
      "options": [
        "Material properties are different in different planes",
        "Material properties are different in crystal orientations",
        "Force and energy required do not change when machining in different directions",
        "Shear stress is different in different planes and directions."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Force and energy required do not change when machining in different directions",
      "week": 3,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "Match the following and choose correct option\nA Shearing I Displacement of material by plastic upheaval\nB Extrusion II Lowest rake angle on negative size\nC Ploughing III Significant friction force\nD Rubbing IV Similar to grinding",
      "options": [
        "A-III, B-IV, C- I, D-II",
        "A-IV, B-I, C- II, D-III",
        "A-II, B-IV, C- I, D-III",
        "A-II, B-I, C- IV, D-III"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "A-II, B-IV, C- I, D-III",
      "week": 3,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the effect on cutting force in case of micro machining due to the reduction in uncut chip thickness?",
      "options": [
        "Increases proportionally",
        "Decreases proportionally",
        "Does not increase proportionally",
        "Does not decrease proportionally"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Does not decrease proportionally",
      "week": 4,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following problem is unlikely to occur due to burr formation?",
      "options": [
        "Improper part mating",
        "Accelerated device wear",
        "Decreased cost of production",
        "Decreased device performance"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Decreased cost of production",
      "week": 4,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following parameter is less responsible for burr formation?",
      "options": [
        "Cutting Speed",
        "Feed Rate",
        "Temperature",
        "Chip Thickness"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Temperature",
      "week": 4,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following is a deburring process?",
      "options": [
        "Ultrasonic wet peening",
        "Electrochemical polishing",
        "Both (a) and (b)",
        "Cylindrical grinding",
        "Both (b) and (d)"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Both (a) and (b)",
      "week": 4,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following is a short frequency component?",
      "options": [
        "Waviness",
        "Profile",
        "Roughness",
        "Lay"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Roughness",
      "week": 4,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following instrument can be used for the surface roughness measurement of the complete region shown in below figure?",
      "options": [
        "Atomic Force Microscope",
        "Optical Microscope",
        "Stylus Method",
        "Both (a) and (b)",
        "Both (a) and (c)"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Stylus Method",
      "week": 4,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following is correct sequence of burr formation before crack propagation?",
      "options": [
        "Continuous cutting Pre-Initiation Initiation Pivoting Burr Development",
        "Pre-Initiation Initiation Continuous cutting  Pivoting Burr Development",
        "Continuous cutting Pivoting Pre-Initiation Initiation Burr Development",
        "Pivoting Continuous cutting  Pre-Initiation Initiation Burr Development"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Continuous cutting Pre-Initiation Initiation Pivoting Burr Development",
      "week": 4,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "In the figure given below, size of the burrs will be more at the following location",
      "options": [
        "1",
        "2",
        "3",
        "4"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "3",
      "week": 4,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following type of burr is shown in below figure?",
      "options": [
        "Tear Burr",
        "Cut-off Burr",
        "Rollover Burr",
        "Poisson Burr"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Tear Burr",
      "week": 4,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "Select the correct sequence of processes with reference to increase in the specific cutting energy",
      "options": [
        "Grinding  Micro machining  Conventional machining  Tensile testing",
        "Tensile testing  Micro machining  Conventional machining  Grinding",
        "Tensile testing  Conventional machining  Micro machining  Grinding",
        "Grinding  Micro machining  Tensile testing  Conventional machining"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Tensile testing  Conventional machining  Micro machining  Grinding",
      "week": 4,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "Elastic Recovery is dependent on",
      "options": [
        "Size of cutting edge radius",
        "Microstructure and hardness",
        "Both (a) and (b)",
        "Neither (a) nor (b)"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Both (a) and (b)",
      "week": 5,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following is not correct about machining at micro scale?",
      "options": [
        "High specific cutting energy",
        "Difficulty in modeling",
        "Tool breakage",
        "Ease in sensing and monitoring"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Ease in sensing and monitoring",
      "week": 5,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following is a moving body of a machine tool?",
      "options": [
        "Machine Base",
        "Column",
        "Spindle box housing",
        "Work tables"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Work tables",
      "week": 5,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "The major design issue in the context of the design of the machine as a system is",
      "options": [
        "Structural Configuration",
        "Structural Connectivity",
        "Both (a) and (b)",
        "Neither (a) nor (b)"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Both (a) and (b)",
      "week": 5,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "The resolution of feedback encoder should be at least ______ than the machine controller?",
      "options": [
        "10 times lower",
        "10 times better",
        "100 times lower",
        "100 times better"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "10 times better",
      "week": 5,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following is correct about resolution?",
      "options": [
        "If the system resolution is n, then all motions are integer multiples of n^2",
        "If the system resolution is n, then all motions are integer multiples of \u221an",
        "If the system resolution is n, then all motions are integer multiples of n",
        "If the system resolution is n, then all motions are integer multiples of n^n"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "If the system resolution is n, then all motions are integer multiples of n",
      "week": 5,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "A vacuum holder helps to,",
      "options": [
        "Evacuate the microchips by sucking it away time to time",
        "Hold the cutting fluid at the machining zone for a longer period",
        "Handle the micro components without making any permanent deformations",
        "Hold the tool monitoring systems at position for online monitoring"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Handle the micro components without making any permanent deformations",
      "week": 5,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one of the below cannot be used to monitor the machining process in real time?",
      "options": [
        "Dynamometer",
        "Touch probe",
        "Acoustic emission sensor",
        "Accelerometer"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Touch probe",
      "week": 5,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "Bidirectional repeatability is difficult to achieve in axis movement due to",
      "options": [
        "Hysteresis of mechanical movement",
        "Linear movement of drive",
        "Low accuracy of the slide movement",
        "Low resolution of the slide movement"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Hysteresis of mechanical movement",
      "week": 5,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is resolution with reference to terms of machine tool?",
      "options": [
        "The least variation in the dimensions of the machined component and the desired value.",
        "How fast the tool or workpiece can reach to the desired location during command execution.",
        "The least increment of movement, the machine is capable to produce.",
        "It is related to the tolerance of the machined component."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "The least increment of movement, the machine is capable to produce.",
      "week": 5,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following is correct about closed loop structure?",
      "options": [
        "Good thermal stability",
        "Easy access to work zone",
        "Strong ridged structural loop",
        "All of the above",
        "Only (a) and (b)",
        "Only (a) and (c)"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "All of the above",
      "week": 6,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "CMM stands for",
      "options": [
        "Co-ordinate Machine Measurement",
        "Centre Measuring Machine",
        "Co-ordinate Measuring Machine",
        "Centre Machine Measurement"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Co-ordinate Measuring Machine",
      "week": 6,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following is correct match of the numbers marked on the figure given below?",
      "options": [
        "1-Leading Edge 2-Stagnant Edge 3-Bleeding Edge",
        "1- Stagnant Edge 2- Leading Edge 3-Bleeding Edge",
        "1-Leading Edge 2- Bleeding Edge 3- Stagnant Edge",
        "1- Bleeding Edge 2- Leading Edge 3- Stagnant Edge"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "1- Stagnant Edge 2- Leading Edge 3-Bleeding Edge",
      "week": 6,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "The sensitive directions in case of Milling Machine are",
      "options": [
        "X-axis and Y-axis",
        "X-axis and Z-axis",
        "Y-axis and Z-axis",
        "X-axis, Y-axis and Z-axis"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "X-axis, Y-axis and Z-axis",
      "week": 6,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "What are the different components of error in a linear movement?",
      "options": [
        "1 position error, 2 straightness error, 2 roll error and 1 tilt error",
        "1 position error, 2 straightness error, 1 roll error and 2 tilt error",
        "2 position error, 1 straightness error, 2 roll error and 1 tilt error",
        "2 position error, 1 straightness error, 1 roll error and 2 tilt error"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "1 position error, 2 straightness error, 1 roll error and 2 tilt error",
      "week": 6,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "The degree of freedom for bolt and nut combination is",
      "options": [
        "Translation and Rotation (Independent)",
        "Only translation",
        "Only rotation",
        "Translation and Rotation (Coupled)"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Translation and Rotation (Coupled)",
      "week": 6,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "When travelling in X- direction, Flatness can be defined as",
      "options": [
        "Displacement error along the X-axis",
        "Displacement error along the Y-axis",
        "Displacement error along the Z-axis",
        "Both (a) and (b)",
        "Both (a) and (c)"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Displacement error along the Z-axis",
      "week": 6,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "Kinematic errors are not related to",
      "options": [
        "Imperfect Geometry",
        "Alignment and dimension of the machine tools",
        "Wear or material aging",
        "Range of the spindle speed"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Range of the spindle speed",
      "week": 6,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "When travelling in X- direction, Straightness can be defined as",
      "options": [
        "Displacement error along the X-axis",
        "Displacement error along the Y-axis",
        "Displacement error along the Z-axis",
        "Both (a) and (b)",
        "Both (a) and (c)"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Displacement error along the Y-axis",
      "week": 6,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "Drift error in the machine tool is due to",
      "options": [
        "Aging of the components",
        "Improper mating of the components",
        "Thermal expansion of the components",
        "Failure of the components"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Aging of the components",
      "week": 6,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following is a preferable material for making structure of micro machine tool?",
      "options": [
        "Metal",
        "Granite",
        "Ceramic",
        "Polymer concrete"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Polymer concrete",
      "week": 7,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following is the least important material property of the machine frame?",
      "options": [
        "Young\u2019s modulus",
        "Shear modulus",
        "Poisson\u2019s ratio",
        "Thermal conductivity"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Poisson\u2019s ratio",
      "week": 7,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "Increasing order of Young\u2019s modulus of different material which are used for making machine structure is:",
      "options": [
        "Elastomers<Non-technical ceramics<Technical ceramics< Polymers",
        "Elastomers<Technical ceramics<Non-technical ceramics< Polymers",
        "Elastomers<Polymers<Composite<Technical ceramics",
        "Elastomers< Polymers < Technical ceramics< Non-technical ceramics"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Elastomers<Polymers<Composite<Technical ceramics",
      "week": 7,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "Specific energy requirement for making the high strength material will be",
      "options": [
        "Low",
        "High",
        "In between low and high",
        "Specific energy requirement is not the criteria for making high strength material"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "High",
      "week": 7,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "What you will do to reduce the local strain in the component?",
      "options": [
        "Reduce thickness of the wall",
        "Increase thickness of the wall",
        "Reduce the weight of the component",
        "Increase the weight of the component"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Increase thickness of the wall",
      "week": 7,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one of the following statement is true?",
      "options": [
        "Polymer concrete is heavier than C.I.",
        "C.I. has better thermal stability than Polymer concrete",
        "Polymer concrete has superior dynamic and static rigidity",
        "C.I. has better damping capacity than Polymer concrete"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Polymer concrete has superior dynamic and static rigidity",
      "week": 7,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "Axis of the guideways should have",
      "options": [
        "Low velocity as well as stiff bearing",
        "High velocity as well as stiff bearing",
        "High acceleration as well as stiff bearing",
        "Low acceleration as well as stiff bearing"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "High acceleration as well as stiff bearing",
      "week": 7,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the drawback of the granite when it is used for making machine tool?",
      "options": [
        "Low damping",
        "Low wear resistance",
        "Moisture absorbing capacity",
        "Presence of residual stress"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Moisture absorbing capacity",
      "week": 7,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one of the following guideways is more preferable for taking load in up-down as well as left-right directions?",
      "options": [
        "Hydrostatic",
        "Hydrodynamics",
        "Linear",
        "Box"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Linear",
      "week": 7,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "Basic static load rating of the roller is roughly defined as:",
      "options": [
        "Total permanent deformation is the half of the diameter of the roller",
        "Total permanent deformation is 1/1000 of the diameter of the roller",
        "Total permanent deformation is 1/10000 of the diameter of the roller",
        "Total permanent deformation is 1/100000 of the diameter of the roller"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Total permanent deformation is 1/10000 of the diameter of the roller",
      "week": 7,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "The function of precision laser system in MMC is to determine",
      "options": [
        "Only diameter of the tool",
        "Only length of the tool",
        "Both diameter and length of the tool",
        "Rake and clearance angle of the tool"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Both diameter and length of the tool",
      "week": 8,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one of the following factors affect air bearing life the most?",
      "options": [
        "Speed of rotation",
        "External load",
        "Acceleration",
        "Cleanliness of air"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Cleanliness of air",
      "week": 8,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "Mode of failure of air bearing",
      "options": [
        "Spalling wear",
        "Smearing wear",
        "Erosion wear",
        "Fretting wear"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Erosion wear",
      "week": 8,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "The variation of radial stiffness of air bearing with respect to shaft angular position is",
      "options": [
        "Non uniform",
        "Uniform",
        "Triangular",
        "Trapezium"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Uniform",
      "week": 8,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following bearing offers the highest friction & has the lowest cost?",
      "options": [
        "Air bearing",
        "Hydrostatic bearing",
        "Roller bearing",
        "Cylindrical bearing"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Roller bearing",
      "week": 8,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "On which part of the linear motor magnet is present?",
      "options": [
        "Rotor",
        "Stator",
        "Forcer",
        "Coil"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Stator",
      "week": 8,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "The maximum speed of a linear motor is governed by",
      "options": [
        "Bus voltage",
        "Speed of the control electronics",
        "Resolution",
        "All of the above"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "All of the above",
      "week": 8,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "The stiffness of the linear motor does not depend upon",
      "options": [
        "Peak force of the motor",
        "Resolution of the feedback",
        "Current available",
        "Speed of the travel"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Speed of the travel",
      "week": 8,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "The problem of heating in the linear drive is due to",
      "options": [
        "Thermal heating",
        "Mechanical friction",
        "Both of the above",
        "Electrical power supply"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Electrical power supply",
      "week": 8,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which statement is/are true for MMC (Micro Machining Center)?",
      "options": [
        "It has high moisture retention capacity and low damping coefficient",
        "It has high moisture retention capacity and high damping coefficient",
        "It has low moisture retention capacity and low damping coefficient",
        "It has low moisture retention capacity and high damping coefficient"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "It has low moisture retention capacity and high damping coefficient",
      "week": 8,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is 4 in 4 Bit encoder?",
      "options": [
        "It has 4 LEDs",
        "It has 4 transmitters",
        "Both (a) and (b)",
        "It has 4 tracks"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "It has 4 tracks",
      "week": 9,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following components or mechanisms is not the part of the belt driven spindle?",
      "options": [
        "Tooling system",
        "Drawbar mechanism",
        "Tool release system",
        "Linear encoder"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Linear encoder",
      "week": 9,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "Spindle bearing should not provide",
      "options": [
        "High rotational speed",
        "Low transfer torque",
        "High power to the cutting tool",
        "Reasonable loading"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Low transfer torque",
      "week": 9,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following statement(s) is/are true?",
      "options": [
        "Angular contact bearing provide precision",
        "Tapered bearing is used for high load application",
        "Both (a) and (b)",
        "Tapered bearing has lower stiffness over ball bearings"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Both (a) and (b)",
      "week": 9,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following bearing is highly accurate and used in high speed spindle?",
      "options": [
        "ABEC 1",
        "ABEC 5",
        "ABEC 7",
        "ABEC 9"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "ABEC 9",
      "week": 9,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following statement(s) is/are true?",
      "options": [
        "To have greater radial load carrying capacity bearing should have high contact angle",
        "To have greater radial load carrying capacity bearing should have low contact angle",
        "To have greater bending load carrying capacity bearing should have high contact angle",
        "To have greater axial load carrying capacity bearing should have low contact angle"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "To have greater radial load carrying capacity bearing should have low contact angle",
      "week": 9,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following statement(s) is/are true?",
      "options": [
        "Low contact angle of a spindle is primarily used in drilling",
        "Low contact angle of a spindle is primarily used in milling",
        "High contact angle of a spindle is primarily used in shaping",
        "High contact angle of a spindle is primarily used in planning"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Low contact angle of a spindle is primarily used in milling",
      "week": 9,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the importance of the bearing preloading?",
      "options": [
        "To provide excess play by applying axial or thrust forces to a bearing",
        "To remove excess play by applying more friction to a bearing",
        "To provide excess play by applying radial and thrust forces to a bearing",
        "To remove excess play by applying axial or thrust forces to a bearing"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "To remove excess play by applying axial or thrust forces to a bearing",
      "week": 9,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "Excessive preloading of the bearing doesn\u2019t result in",
      "options": [
        "Increased heat generation",
        "Excessive stress",
        "Higher chances of fatigue",
        "Decreased torque"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Decreased torque",
      "week": 9,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the purpose(s) of duplex bearing?",
      "options": [
        "To provide high rotational speed",
        "To provide high feed rate during machining",
        "To provide less friction",
        "To provide load sharing and high stiffness"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "To provide load sharing and high stiffness",
      "week": 9,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "Races and ball in ball bearing are made up of which of the following material?",
      "options": [
        "Ceramic",
        "Carbide",
        "Steel",
        "Cast iron"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Steel",
      "week": 10,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "One of the mechanisms of the bearing failure is",
      "options": [
        "Hot welding of raceway material to the ball",
        "Cold welding of ball material to the raceway",
        "Hot welding between balls",
        "Cold welding between balls"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Cold welding of ball material to the raceway",
      "week": 10,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "Air bearing spindle provides",
      "options": [
        "Low torque, low speed",
        "High speed, high torque",
        "High torque, low speed",
        "High speed, low torque"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "High speed, low torque",
      "week": 10,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "How you will reduce the warping of the aerostatic spindle?",
      "options": [
        "Increase temperature gradient in the spindle",
        "Decrease temperature gradient in the spindle",
        "Increase pressure gradient in the spindle",
        "Decrease pressure gradient in the spindle"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Decrease temperature gradient in the spindle",
      "week": 10,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following tool retention system is best for high speed application?",
      "options": [
        "HSK",
        "BT",
        "ISO",
        "CAT"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "HSK",
      "week": 10,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following is not the characteristic of 3 surface contact holder of tool retention system?",
      "options": [
        "High speed",
        "High dynamic stiffness",
        "High static stiffness",
        "High runout"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "High runout",
      "week": 10,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following is not a micro tool fabrication process?",
      "options": [
        "Electro Discharge Machining (EDM)",
        "Focused Ion Beam (FIB) Machining",
        "Abrasive jet machining (AJM)",
        "Laser Beam Machining (LBM)"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Abrasive jet machining (AJM)",
      "week": 10,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "In micro-tool fabrication by Wire Electric Discharge Grinding (WEDG)",
      "options": [
        "Wire is made of aluminum and electrode is of tungsten carbide",
        "Wire is made of copper and electrode is of ceramic",
        "Wire is made of copper and electrode is of tungsten carbide",
        "Wire is made of aluminum and electrode is of ceramic"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Wire is made of copper and electrode is of tungsten carbide",
      "week": 10,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "ELID process uses",
      "options": [
        "In-process dressing of the grinding wheel to maintain uniform protrusion of abrasive particles",
        "In-process monitoring of the status of the abrasive particles",
        "In-process dressing of the copper electrode (cathode) to maintain uniform protrusion of abrasive particles",
        "In-process monitoring of the forces acting on the workpiece"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "In-process dressing of the grinding wheel to maintain uniform protrusion of abrasive particles",
      "week": 10,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "Micro tools having diameter less than 50 \u00b5m generally fabricated without helix angle",
      "options": [
        "To reduce the wastage of the material in the form of chips during fabrication",
        "To improve the surface finish on the machined component",
        "To improve their rigidity",
        "To reduce burr formation"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "To improve their rigidity",
      "week": 10,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which statement is true?",
      "options": [
        "HSS cutter is harder than carbide cutter",
        "HSS cutter can bend more than carbide cutter",
        "HSS cutter has long life than carbide cutter under the same operating conditions",
        "HSS cutter does not required coolant during machining operation"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "HSS cutter can bend more than carbide cutter",
      "week": 11,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the major issue of tool breakage in micro machining?",
      "options": [
        "Chip clogging",
        "Higher rotational speed",
        "Small depth of cut",
        "Low feed rate"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Chip clogging",
      "week": 11,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "Hammering vibration is produce when using",
      "options": [
        "End mill cutter without coating",
        "End mill cutter with axial runout",
        "Two flutes end mill cutter",
        "Four flutes end mill cutter"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Two flutes end mill cutter",
      "week": 11,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the problem in using small machine tool for micro machining applications?",
      "options": [
        "Small machine tools are costly",
        "It is difficult to get small size sensors and actuators for monitoring and control of the small machine tool",
        "It is difficult to make and assemble components while building the small machine tool",
        "It is difficult to learn the machining operation in small size machine tool"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "It is difficult to get small size sensors and actuators for monitoring and control of the small machine tool",
      "week": 11,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "In diamond turning,",
      "options": [
        "X and Z movement is given by the cutting tool",
        "X and Z movement is given by the spindle head",
        "X movement is given by the cutting tool and Z movement is given by the spindle head",
        "X movement is given by the spindle head and Z movement is given by the cutting tool"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "X movement is given by the spindle head and Z movement is given by the cutting tool",
      "week": 11,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "The diamond turning can be classified as facing and fly cutting based on the",
      "options": [
        "Number of axis",
        "Type of coordinate system",
        "Type of machining operation",
        "Type of tooling system"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Type of machining operation",
      "week": 11,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "In micromachining, generally an end mill cutter having _____ flutes are used.",
      "options": [
        "2",
        "3",
        "4",
        "5"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "2",
      "week": 11,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "Built up edge in micro milling",
      "options": [
        "Decreases surface finish",
        "Increases deflection",
        "Increases material removal rate",
        "Increases tool life"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Increases deflection",
      "week": 11,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "Diamond turning is generally used for finishing of",
      "options": [
        "Cast iron",
        "Mild steel",
        "Copper",
        "Tungsten carbide"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Copper",
      "week": 11,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "Two axes with T slide is associated with",
      "options": [
        "X-Z axis diamond turning machine",
        "R-\u03f4 axis diamond turning machine",
        "X-Y axis diamond turning machine",
        "Y-Z axis diamond turning machine"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "X-Z axis diamond turning machine",
      "week": 11,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "In ultra-precision machining, surface finish (Ra) is typically in the range of",
      "options": [
        "<10\u00b5m",
        ">10 \u00b5m",
        "<20nm",
        ">20nm"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "<20nm",
      "week": 12,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "Depth of cut (uncut chip thickness) in ultra-precision machining is in the range of",
      "options": [
        "1-10 \u00b5m",
        "10-100 \u00b5m",
        "0.1-10 \u00b5m",
        "0.01-0.1 \u00b5m"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "0.1-10 \u00b5m",
      "week": 12,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "Material removal rate in the soft loop finishing technique depends on",
      "options": [
        "Pressure",
        "Velocity",
        "Preston coefficient",
        "All of the above",
        "Only (a) and (c)",
        "Only (b) and (c)"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "All of the above",
      "week": 12,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one of the following cannot be measured by the tool setting device?",
      "options": [
        "X-Z offset of the cutting tool",
        "Tool nose radius",
        "Position of the center of the nose radius",
        "Waviness of the cutting edge"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Waviness of the cutting edge",
      "week": 12,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "When machining of concave surface by diamond turning using large nose radius,",
      "options": [
        "Small cutting edge length comes into contact with workpiece",
        "Long cutting edge length comes into contact with workpiece",
        "Workpiece needs to be rotated at high speed",
        "Workpiece needs to be rotated at low speed"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Long cutting edge length comes into contact with workpiece",
      "week": 12,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "Tool with small nose radius can be used for machining of",
      "options": [
        "External feature",
        "Fragile workpiece",
        "Hard material",
        "Composite"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Fragile workpiece",
      "week": 12,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "In diamond turning, workpiece is gripped by",
      "options": [
        "3 jaws chuck",
        "4 jaws chuck",
        "Vacuum chuck",
        "Self-centric chuck"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Vacuum chuck",
      "week": 12,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the sequence of basic composition of a sensing system?",
      "options": [
        "Transform -- Sensor -- Signal processing -- Decision making",
        "Sensor -- Transform -- Decision making -- Signal processing",
        "Transform -- Sensor -- Decision making -- Signal processing",
        "Sensor -- Transform -- Signal processing -- Decision making"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Sensor -- Transform -- Signal processing -- Decision making",
      "week": 12,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "In which case, the amplitude of AE signal will be high?",
      "options": [
        "Crack propagation",
        "Isotropy",
        "Plastic deformation",
        "Ductile failure"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Crack propagation",
      "week": 12,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following instrument has very high precision level (<1 nm)",
      "options": [
        "Accelerometer",
        "Encoders",
        "Acoustic emission",
        "Load cells"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Acoustic emission",
      "week": 12,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "micromachine"
    },
    {
      "question": "Wilhelm Wundt and his students used a technique known as _________ to study mental states.",
      "options": [
        "behaviorism",
        "intensity measurement",
        "componentialism",
        "introspection"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "introspection",
      "week": 1,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "Cognitive Psychology"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which psychologist extensively tested his own memory to develop theories of cognition?",
      "options": [
        "Aristotle",
        "Wundt",
        "Ebbinghaus",
        "Chomsky"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Ebbinghaus",
      "week": 1,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "Cognitive Psychology"
    },
    {
      "question": "All connectionist models share the assumption that:",
      "options": [
        "a central processor directs the flow of information",
        "processing occurs in parallel",
        "knowledge is stored in various storehouses",
        "processing occurs serially"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "processing occurs in parallel",
      "week": 1,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "Cognitive Psychology"
    },
    {
      "question": "The term “limited capacity processors” suggests that:",
      "options": [
        "computers have limited memory storage",
        "neurons can only fire at a certain rate",
        "human beings can only do so many things at once",
        "processing in the brain occurs in parallel"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "human beings can only do so many things at once",
      "week": 1,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "Cognitive Psychology"
    },
    {
      "question": "A traditional “school” within psychology that had as its goal the identification of the simplest possible units of the mind:",
      "options": [
        "functionalism",
        "structuralism",
        "behaviorism",
        "componentialism"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "structuralism",
      "week": 1,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "Cognitive Psychology"
    },
    {
      "question": "Cognitive psychology is broad, and thus overlaps with many other fields including neuroscience, philosophy, and ______.",
      "options": [
        "botany",
        "astronomy",
        "linguistics",
        "mining"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "linguistics",
      "week": 1,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "Cognitive Psychology"
    },
    {
      "question": "William James's ideas regarding psychological phenomena centered around the idea of",
      "options": [
        "the sea of the subconscious",
        "a stream of consciousness",
        "a stream of subconsciousness",
        "a sea of consciousness"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "a stream of consciousness",
      "week": 1,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "Cognitive Psychology"
    },
    {
      "question": "A body of knowledge structured according to what its proponents consider important, which guides research topics and research methods, is called a ___________.",
      "options": [
        "hypothesis",
        "methodology",
        "paradigm",
        "metaphor"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "paradigm",
      "week": 1,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "Cognitive Psychology"
    },
    {
      "question": "The analysis of information processing systems is of special interest to _____ psychology.",
      "options": [
        "behavioral",
        "biological",
        "psychoanalytic",
        "cognitive"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "cognitive",
      "week": 1,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "Cognitive Psychology"
    },
    {
      "question": "If you think of cognitive processing as a type of information processing, then the brain is the ______ and the cognitive processes themselves are the ______.",
      "options": [
        "response; stimulus",
        "hardware; software",
        "software; hardware",
        "stimulus; response"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "hardware; software",
      "week": 1,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "Cognitive Psychology"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following processes the sensations coming into each sense organ, allowing us to understand and interpret the sensations we receive?",
      "options": [
        "environment",
        "sensory system",
        "stimulus",
        "brain"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "sensory system",
      "week": 2,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "Cognitive Psychology"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of these psychological approaches focuses on how humans use principles of organization to understand our surroundings?",
      "options": [
        "perception-action",
        "gestalt",
        "top-down",
        "computational"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "gestalt",
      "week": 2,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "Cognitive Psychology"
    },
    {
      "question": "The two best studied forms of perception are:",
      "options": [
        "visual and auditory",
        "visual and olfactory",
        "visual and haptic",
        "auditory and olfactory"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "visual and auditory",
      "week": 2,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "Cognitive Psychology"
    },
    {
      "question": "Reversible figures illustrate the principle of:",
      "options": [
        "bottom-up processing",
        "figure-ground organization",
        "size constancy",
        "retinal imagery"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "figure-ground organization",
      "week": 2,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "Cognitive Psychology"
    },
    {
      "question": "A stencil provides a good analogy for the theory of:",
      "options": [
        "top-down processing",
        "template matching",
        "good continuation",
        "featural analysis"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "template matching",
      "week": 2,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "Cognitive Psychology"
    },
    {
      "question": "Gibson's theory of direct perception is in direct opposition to the ______ approach to perception.",
      "options": [
        "connectionist",
        "constructivist",
        "bottom-up",
        "gestalt"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "constructivist",
      "week": 2,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "Cognitive Psychology"
    },
    {
      "question": "Prototype matching theory argues that precepts are compared to ______ in memory.",
      "options": [
        "idealized representations",
        "abstract dot patterns",
        "gestalt principles",
        "lists of features"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "idealized representations",
      "week": 2,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "Cognitive Psychology"
    },
    {
      "question": "___________ are to visual perception what phonemes are to language, according to Biederman.",
      "options": [
        "templates",
        "distal stimuli",
        "geons",
        "receptors"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "geons",
      "week": 2,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "Cognitive Psychology"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of these help us estimate objects' size and distance to aid in our perception?",
      "options": [
        "stimuli",
        "sensations",
        "cues",
        "neurons"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "cues",
      "week": 2,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "Cognitive Psychology"
    },
    {
      "question": "You are eating a meal at an open-air restaurant a few hundred yards from the ocean. You hear a constant whooshing sound. According to the likelihood principle, what would you assume caused the noise?",
      "options": [
        "an earthquake",
        "a series of airplanes landing",
        "traffic a few miles away",
        "waves crashing on the beach"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "waves crashing on the beach",
      "week": 2,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "Cognitive Psychology"
    },
    {
      "question": "Noticing a red flower among a field of purple flowers illustrates ______.",
      "options": [
        "the attention capture phenomenon",
        "the cocktail party effect",
        "the bottleneck of attention",
        "a shadowing task"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "the attention capture phenomenon",
      "week": 3,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "Cognitive Psychology"
    },
    {
      "question": "According to Treisman, if you listen to two competing messages simultaneously, you are more likely to pick up information from the second message if that message ______.",
      "options": [
        "relates to the other message",
        "was spoken more slowly",
        "includes a spotlight",
        "is louder"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "relates to the other message",
      "week": 3,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "Cognitive Psychology"
    },
    {
      "question": "Stroop interference lessens when:",
      "options": [
        "participants are given more practice at naming colors",
        "participants are encouraged to focus carefully",
        "participants are given more practice at reading color names",
        "participants are better readers"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "participants are given more practice at naming colors",
      "week": 3,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "Cognitive Psychology"
    },
    {
      "question": "When listening to a conversation, your attention is momentarily diverted when you hear your name spoken in a different conversation across the room. This is an example of the:",
      "options": [
        "Stroop effect",
        "cocktail party effect",
        "dichotic listening phenomenon",
        "attenuation effect"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "cocktail party effect",
      "week": 3,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "Cognitive Psychology"
    },
    {
      "question": "Broadbent, in proposing his filter theory of attention, argued that an attentional filter lets some information through and blocks out the rest. This filter is based upon:",
      "options": [
        "the meaning of the message",
        "a physical characteristic of the message, such as its location",
        "the importance of the message",
        "the number of repetitions of the message"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "a physical characteristic of the message, such as its location",
      "week": 3,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "Cognitive Psychology"
    },
    {
      "question": "Our attention has been said to involve a ______ that filters out everything except the information we are attending to.",
      "options": [
        "net",
        "bottleneck",
        "switchboard",
        "bridge"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "bottleneck",
      "week": 3,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "Cognitive Psychology"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of these is known to influence the cocktail party effect?",
      "options": [
        "a person's level of extroversion or introversion",
        "a person's intelligence",
        "the salience of the message",
        "cultural differences in filtering abilities"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "the salience of the message",
      "week": 3,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "Cognitive Psychology"
    },
    {
      "question": "According to ____ theory, we never actually acquire unattended material at all.",
      "options": [
        "capacity",
        "bottleneck",
        "schema",
        "attenuation"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "schema",
      "week": 3,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "Cognitive Psychology"
    },
    {
      "question": "Children with attention deficit hyperactivity disorder (ADHD):",
      "options": [
        "are more likely to be girls than boys",
        "cannot sustain vigilance on repetitive or dull tasks",
        "cannot switch attention from one task to another",
        "cannot devote mental resources to tasks"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "cannot sustain vigilance on repetitive or dull tasks",
      "week": 3,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "Cognitive Psychology"
    },
    {
      "question": "According to Treisman, people tend to process:",
      "options": [
        "only as much as is necessary to separate the attended from the unattended message",
        "at the highest possible level given the amount of background distraction",
        "only to the level of linguistic characteristics, separating it into words",
        "only to the level of physical characteristics"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "only as much as is necessary to separate the attended from the unattended message",
      "week": 3,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "Cognitive Psychology"
    },
    {
      "question": "Remembering your phone number in sequences such as xxx-xxx-xxxx and your Social Security number in sequences such as xxx-xx-xxxx are examples of ______.",
      "options": [
        "short-term memory",
        "encoding",
        "sensory memory",
        "chunking"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "chunking",
      "week": 4,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "Cognitive Psychology"
    },
    {
      "question": "The briefest form of memory is ______ memory.",
      "options": [
        "long-term",
        "working",
        "short-term",
        "sensory"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "sensory",
      "week": 4,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "Cognitive Psychology"
    },
    {
      "question": "The suffix effect relates to which type of memory?",
      "options": [
        "iconic",
        "echoic",
        "short term",
        "long term"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "echoic",
      "week": 4,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "Cognitive Psychology"
    },
    {
      "question": "The fact that the size of the memory set does affect search time in short-term memory suggests that:",
      "options": [
        "search is both self-terminating and serial",
        "search is a serial process",
        "search is a parallel process",
        "search is exhaustive"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "search is a serial process",
      "week": 4,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "Cognitive Psychology"
    },
    {
      "question": "Some experts describe memory as a ______, while others believe it is a ______.",
      "options": [
        "checklist; blueprint",
        "secret; journey",
        "structure; process",
        "ball of string; pool of water"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "structure; process",
      "week": 4,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "Cognitive Psychology"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of these is a component of the memory formation process?",
      "options": [
        "retrieval",
        "interference",
        "modality",
        "inspiration"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "retrieval",
      "week": 4,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "Cognitive Psychology"
    },
    {
      "question": "Unattended information is stored briefly in:",
      "options": [
        "sensory memory",
        "short-term memory",
        "long-term memory",
        "secondary memory"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "sensory memory",
      "week": 4,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "Cognitive Psychology"
    },
    {
      "question": "In the absence of rehearsal, short-term memory tends to:",
      "options": [
        "last about 8 seconds",
        "last about 20 seconds",
        "decay slowly over 24 hours",
        "last for an unlimited amount of time"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "last about 20 seconds",
      "week": 4,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "Cognitive Psychology"
    },
    {
      "question": "The concept of fluid intelligence is highly related to:",
      "options": [
        "working memory capacity",
        "echoic memory capacity",
        "iconic memory capacity",
        "interference"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "working memory capacity",
      "week": 4,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "Cognitive Psychology"
    },
    {
      "question": "One basic physiological mechanism for learning is the ____ rule, which states that if a synapse between two neurons is repeatedly activated at about the same time the postsynaptic neuron fires, the chemistry of the synapse changes.",
      "options": [
        "Baddeley",
        "Hebb",
        "Tulving",
        "Carlson"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Hebb",
      "week": 4,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "Cognitive Psychology"
    },
    {
      "question": "Ebbinghaus's forgetting curve demonstrates that:",
      "options": [
        "Forgetting is rapid at first and then levels off",
        "forgetting is slow at rst and then speeds up",
        "forgetting occurs at a steady pace, beginning immediately after learning",
        "no forgetting occurs until 24 hours after learning"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Forgetting is rapid at first and then levels off",
      "week": 5,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "Cognitive Psychology"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following would be a part of your declarative memory system?",
      "options": [
        "being able to name a hybrid car",
        "knowing how to react to a red light",
        "knowing how to drive a car",
        "knowing how to ride a bicycle"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "being able to name a hybrid car",
      "week": 5,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "Cognitive Psychology"
    },
    {
      "question": "A schema for a routine event, such as going to the dentist, is called a:",
      "options": [
        "script",
        "category",
        "exemplar",
        "prototype"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "script",
      "week": 5,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "Cognitive Psychology"
    },
    {
      "question": "Information such as the name of the person who sat in front of you in the fifth grade is stored in:",
      "options": [
        "sensory memory",
        "short-term memory",
        "working memory",
        "long-term memory"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "long-term memory",
      "week": 5,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "Cognitive Psychology"
    },
    {
      "question": "The term “anterograde amnesia” refers to:",
      "options": [
        "the loss of the ability to form new memories.",
        "the loss of the ability to recall old events.",
        "the loss of short-term memory.",
        "the loss of all memory ability."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "the loss of the ability to form new memories.",
      "week": 5,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "Cognitive Psychology"
    },
    {
      "question": "The term “retrograde amnesia” refers to:",
      "options": [
        "the loss of the ability to form new memories.",
        "the loss of the ability to recall old events.",
        "the loss of short-term memory.",
        "the loss of sensory memory."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "the loss of the ability to recall old events.",
      "week": 5,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "Cognitive Psychology"
    },
    {
      "question": "When we cannot retrieve information from memory, we say that _____ has occurred.",
      "options": [
        "forgetting",
        "a memory trace",
        "sensory decay",
        "encoding failure"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "forgetting",
      "week": 5,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "Cognitive Psychology"
    },
    {
      "question": "The results of the Brown–Peterson short-term memory task can be explained by:",
      "options": [
        "decay",
        "interference",
        "both decay and interference",
        "neither decay nor interference"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "both decay and interference",
      "week": 5,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "Cognitive Psychology"
    },
    {
      "question": "The calling to mind of previously stored information is known as",
      "options": [
        "retrieval",
        "encoding",
        "storage",
        "forgetting"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "retrieval",
      "week": 5,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "Cognitive Psychology"
    },
    {
      "question": "You have just listened to a list of 20 words. When asked to recall these words in any order, you are LEAST LIKELY to recall the",
      "options": [
        "first word",
        "second word",
        "10th word",
        "20th word"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "10th word",
      "week": 5,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "Cognitive Psychology"
    },
    {
      "question": "According to the notion of cognitive economy, a characteristic like “has wings” would be stored along with which of the following semantic memory nodes?",
      "options": [
        "bird",
        "ostrich",
        "robin",
        "all of these"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "bird",
      "week": 6,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "Cognitive Psychology"
    },
    {
      "question": "Contrary to the predictions of hierarchical models, Rips, Shoben, and Smith have found that people can verify the statement “A pig is an animal”:",
      "options": [
        "faster than “A pig is a mammal.”",
        "faster than “A dog is an animal.”",
        "faster than “A pig is actually very clean.”",
        "faster than “A pig is a bird.”"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "faster than “A pig is a mammal.”",
      "week": 6,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "Cognitive Psychology"
    },
    {
      "question": "According to research by Collins and Quillian, the statement “Siamese cats have blue eyes” will be verified:",
      "options": [
        "slower than “Siamese cats give birth to live young.”",
        "faster than “Siamese cats give birth to live young.”",
        "in the same amount of time as “Siamese cats give birth to live young.”",
        "slower than “Siamese cats have tails.”"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "faster than “Siamese cats give birth to live young.”",
      "week": 6,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "Cognitive Psychology"
    },
    {
      "question": "Collins and Loftus's spreading activation theory differs from the hierarchical network theory in that:",
      "options": [
        "it dispenses with the idea of cognitive economy.",
        "it relies on the assumption of hierarchical structure.",
        "it cannot account for the typicality effect.",
        "it makes stronger predictions than hierarchical models."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "it dispenses with the idea of cognitive economy.",
      "week": 6,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "Cognitive Psychology"
    },
    {
      "question": "ACT models distinguish among three types of memory systems:",
      "options": [
        "working memory, episodic memory, and declarative memory",
        "semantic memory, episodic memory, and procedural memory",
        "procedural memory, declarative memory, and semantic memory",
        "working memory, declarative memory, and procedural memory"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "working memory, declarative memory, and procedural memory",
      "week": 6,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "Cognitive Psychology"
    },
    {
      "question": "According to ACT models, _______ memory represents information in if–then production rules.",
      "options": [
        "working",
        "procedural",
        "episodic",
        "semantic"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "procedural",
      "week": 6,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "Cognitive Psychology"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following would be a part of your declarative memory system?",
      "options": [
        "being able to name a hybrid car",
        "knowing how to react to a red light",
        "knowing how to drive a car",
        "knowing how to ride a bicycle"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "being able to name a hybrid car",
      "week": 6,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "Cognitive Psychology"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following is FALSE regarding a connectionist training “epoch”?",
      "options": [
        "It begins by generating a random output.",
        "Connection weights are initially set at random levels.",
        "Generated output patterns are compared with target patterns.",
        "Back propagation occurs over many trials."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "It begins by generating a random output.",
      "week": 6,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "Cognitive Psychology"
    },
    {
      "question": "Studies of semantic memory have shown that in a lexical decision task, people are faster at responding to the stimulus “bread” if it is paired with a stimulus such as:",
      "options": [
        "rencle",
        "dog",
        "xqkrf",
        "butter"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "butter",
      "week": 6,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "Cognitive Psychology"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following would be a part of your procedural memory system?",
      "options": [
        "knowing that the Baseball Hall of Fame is in Cooperstown, New York",
        "knowing the lifetime batting average of Ted Williams",
        "knowing how to swing a baseball bat",
        "being able to remember the ball and strike count of the current pitch"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "knowing how to swing a baseball bat",
      "week": 6,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "Cognitive Psychology"
    },
    {
      "question": "A ________ is a mental representation of some object, event, or pattern.",
      "options": [
        "category",
        "concept",
        "script",
        "memory"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "concept",
      "week": 7,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "Cognitive Psychology"
    },
    {
      "question": "“Characteristic features” and “family resemblance” are important aspects of the _________ view of concepts.",
      "options": [
        "classical",
        "prototype",
        "exemplar",
        "schema"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "prototype",
      "week": 7,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "Cognitive Psychology"
    },
    {
      "question": "If “soda” is a basic-level category, then ______ would be a subordinate level.",
      "options": [
        "soft drink",
        "beverage",
        "drink",
        "Coca-Cola"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Coca-Cola",
      "week": 7,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "Cognitive Psychology"
    },
    {
      "question": "According to the ______ view of concepts, people categorize new instances by comparing them to representations of previously stored instances.",
      "options": [
        "classical",
        "prototype",
        "exemplar",
        "schema"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "exemplar",
      "week": 7,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "Cognitive Psychology"
    },
    {
      "question": "The _____ view of concepts argues that concepts include representations of at least some individual instances and not only abstract summaries.",
      "options": [
        "classical",
        "prototype",
        "schemata",
        "both exemplar and schemata"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "both exemplar and schemata",
      "week": 7,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "Cognitive Psychology"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following is true regarding schemata?",
      "options": [
        "A schema refers to something smaller and more specific than a concept.",
        "Schemata are passive rather than active.",
        "A schema contains only fixed parts, never variables.",
        "Schemata can indicate relationships among various pieces of information."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Schemata can indicate relationships among various pieces of information.",
      "week": 7,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "Cognitive Psychology"
    },
    {
      "question": "The ______ view of concepts argues that a person uses his/her theories about the way the world works to justify the classification of instances in the same category.",
      "options": [
        "prototype",
        "exemplar",
        "schema",
        "knowledge-based"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "knowledge-based",
      "week": 7,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "Cognitive Psychology"
    },
    {
      "question": "The schema view of concept formation assumes that:",
      "options": [
        "there are clear boundaries among individual schemata.",
        "there is cognitive economy among concepts.",
        "information is abstracted across instances.",
        "no information is stored about actual instances."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "information is abstracted across instances.",
      "week": 7,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "Cognitive Psychology"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following is a good example of a basic level of categorization?",
      "options": [
        "musical instrument",
        "piano",
        "electronic keyboard",
        "grand piano"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "piano",
      "week": 7,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "Cognitive Psychology"
    },
    {
      "question": "If “sandwich” is a basic-level category, then ______ would be a superordinate level.",
      "options": [
        "soup",
        "sub",
        "panini",
        "food"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "food",
      "week": 7,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "Cognitive Psychology"
    },
    {
      "question": "Several mnemonic devices, including the method of loci, the pegword method, and the method of interacting images, have in common their reliance on:",
      "options": [
        "verbal rehearsal",
        "creating a story",
        "visual imagery",
        "connecting new information to well-known information"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "visual imagery",
      "week": 8,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "Cognitive Psychology"
    },
    {
      "question": "According to the dual-coding hypothesis, which of the following word pairs would be easiest to remember?",
      "options": [
        "fire-inspiration",
        "ferret-catalog",
        "freedom-honesty",
        "cat-liberty"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "ferret-catalog",
      "week": 8,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "Cognitive Psychology"
    },
    {
      "question": "In Paivio's study of paired-associate learning, subjects learned four types of word pairs: I. concrete-concrete (for example, book-table) II. concrete-abstract (for example, book-freedom) III. abstract-concrete (for example, freedom-table) IV. abstract-abstract (for example, freedom-honesty) Which of the following accurately portrays participants' recall of the four types of pairs, from highest recall to lowest?",
      "options": [
        "I, III, II, IV",
        "I, II, III, IV",
        "II, III, I, IV",
        "IV, III, II, I"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "I, II, III, IV",
      "week": 8,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "Cognitive Psychology"
    },
    {
      "question": "The relational-organizational hypothesis is supported by:",
      "options": [
        "the effectiveness of the method of loci.",
        "the fact that concrete words are recalled better than abstract words.",
        "the fact that noninteractive images do not facilitate recall whereas interactive images do facilitate recall.",
        "the effectiveness of the pegword method."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "the fact that noninteractive images do not facilitate recall whereas interactive images do facilitate recall.",
      "week": 8,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "Cognitive Psychology"
    },
    {
      "question": "Some theorists believe that there is a single code for all types of information; this code is known as a _______ representation.",
      "options": [
        "visual",
        "pictorial",
        "verbal",
        "propositional"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "propositional",
      "week": 8,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "Cognitive Psychology"
    },
    {
      "question": "Behaviorists objected to the study of visual imagery because:",
      "options": [
        "it cannot be investigated with sufficient scientific control.",
        "there are too many individual differences in people's abilities to visualize.",
        "behaviorists prefer to study animals and animals have no imagery abilities.",
        "we can only study visual imagery and not auditory images, olfactory images, etc."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "it cannot be investigated with sufficient scientific control.",
      "week": 8,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "Cognitive Psychology"
    },
    {
      "question": "Kosslyn compared people's verification times for statements like “Cats have claws” (high association, small visual part of a cat) to “Cats have heads” (low association, large visual part of a cat). He found that people were:",
      "options": [
        "faster at verifying “claws” whether or not they used visual imagery.",
        "faster at verifying “heads” whether or not they used visual imagery.",
        "faster at verifying “heads” when they used imagery, “claws” when they did not.",
        "faster at verifying “claws” when they used imagery, “heads” when they did not."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "faster at verifying “heads” when they used imagery, “claws” when they did not.",
      "week": 8,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "Cognitive Psychology"
    },
    {
      "question": "Finke's principle of _____ states that mental imagery allows us to retrieve information that was not intentionally stored.",
      "options": [
        "perceptual equivalence",
        "transformational equivalence",
        "implicit encoding",
        "structural encoding"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "implicit encoding",
      "week": 8,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "Cognitive Psychology"
    },
    {
      "question": "Your mental map of your campus is probably:",
      "options": [
        "larger than reality.",
        "smaller than reality.",
        "more regular, with more straight lines and right angles, than reality.",
        "less regular, with fewer straight lines and right angles, than reality."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "more regular, with more straight lines and right angles, than reality.",
      "week": 8,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "Cognitive Psychology"
    },
    {
      "question": "Cooper's studies of the mental rotation of complex polygons indicated that:",
      "options": [
        "people rotated more complex polygons in the same amount of time as simpler polygons.",
        "people took longer to rotate more complex polygons.",
        "people actually took less time to rotate more complex polygons.",
        "people were unable to mentally rotate a polygon with greater than 10 points with more than chance accuracy."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "people rotated more complex polygons in the same amount of time as simpler polygons.",
      "week": 8,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "Cognitive Psychology"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following is/are generally agreed upon as necessary criteria/criterion for claiming that a communication system is a language?",
      "options": [
        "regularity",
        "productivity",
        "referentiality",
        "both regularity and productivity"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "both regularity and productivity",
      "week": 9,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "Cognitive Psychology"
    },
    {
      "question": "Bird songs and bee dances are not considered to be languages because:",
      "options": [
        "they do not use words.",
        "they do not have a formal grammar.",
        "they cannot express infinite combinations of ideas.",
        "they do not have a permanent (written) form."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "they cannot express infinite combinations of ideas.",
      "week": 9,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "Cognitive Psychology"
    },
    {
      "question": "The smallest unit of language that carries a consistent meaning is called a:",
      "options": [
        "feature.",
        "phoneme.",
        "phonetic.",
        "morpheme."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "morpheme.",
      "week": 9,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "Cognitive Psychology"
    },
    {
      "question": "English speakers hear a distinction between “l” and “r” sounds; speakers of some Chinese dialects do not hear this distinction. This example illustrates a difference in the ______ aspects of the two languages.",
      "options": [
        "phonetic",
        "phonological",
        "semantic",
        "syntactic"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "phonetic",
      "week": 9,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "Cognitive Psychology"
    },
    {
      "question": "Studies of sentence comprehension have shown all of the following EXCEPT:",
      "options": [
        "Exact wording of a clause is preserved in memory while that clause is actively being processed.",
        "After a sentence has been processed, exact wording is discarded and only the general meaning is preserved in memory.",
        "We typically do not consciously notice ambiguities in sentences.",
        "We do not process exact wording in memory; we only process meaning."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "We do not process exact wording in memory; we only process meaning.",
      "week": 9,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "Cognitive Psychology"
    },
    {
      "question": "“What's for dinner?” “Food.” The second speaker is breaking Grice's maxim of",
      "options": [
        "quantity.",
        "quality.",
        "relation.",
        "manner."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "quantity.",
      "week": 9,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "Cognitive Psychology"
    },
    {
      "question": "Fodor's modularity hypothesis proposes that:",
      "options": [
        "language processing actually encompasses several subskills (modules).",
        "in understanding language, we separate sentences and phrases into individual units known as modules.",
        "thought processes are dependent upon the language we use to think.",
        "certain language processes operate independently of other cognitive processes such as memory and attention."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "certain language processes operate independently of other cognitive processes such as memory and attention.",
      "week": 9,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "Cognitive Psychology"
    },
    {
      "question": "Whorf's linguistic relativity hypothesis:",
      "options": [
        "asserts that thought is dependent upon language.",
        "is supported by studies of color perception.",
        "asserts that thought is dependent upon language, and is supported by studies of color perception.",
        "asserts that thought is dependent upon language, and is not supported by studies of color perception."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "asserts that thought is dependent upon language, and is not supported by studies of color perception.",
      "week": 9,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "Cognitive Psychology"
    },
    {
      "question": "Damage to Broca's area often leads to:",
      "options": [
        "expressive aphasia.",
        "receptive aphasia.",
        "inability to comprehend written language.",
        "both expressive aphasia and inability to comprehend written language."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "expressive aphasia.",
      "week": 9,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "Cognitive Psychology"
    },
    {
      "question": "The word “bat” is considered to be lexically ambiguous because it has two possible meanings.",
      "options": [
        "True",
        "False"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "True",
      "week": 9,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "Cognitive Psychology"
    },
    {
      "question": "A(n) _____ problem has a clear goal, a small set of starting information, and rules about how to attain the goal.",
      "options": [
        "classic",
        "laboratory",
        "well-defined",
        "introspective"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "well-defined",
      "week": 10,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "Cognitive Psychology"
    },
    {
      "question": "The problem-solving technique of _____ involves comparing the goal with the starting point, thinking of possible ways to overcome the distance between them, and choosing the best one.",
      "options": [
        "generate-and-test",
        "means-end analysis",
        "reasoning by analogy",
        "mental set"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "means-end analysis",
      "week": 10,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "Cognitive Psychology"
    },
    {
      "question": "The General Problem Solver (GPS) is a computer program that solves problems in crypt arithmetic and logic using:",
      "options": [
        "means-end analysis.",
        "generate-and-test.",
        "reasoning by analogy.",
        "introspection."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "means-end analysis.",
      "week": 10,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "Cognitive Psychology"
    },
    {
      "question": "_____ is a very important technique for solving the Towers of Hanoi problem.",
      "options": [
        "Means-end analysis",
        "Generate-and-test",
        "Working backward",
        "Reasoning by analogy"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Working backward",
      "week": 10,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "Cognitive Psychology"
    },
    {
      "question": "A tendency to adopt a certain framework, strategy, or procedure, which can become an obstacle to successful problem solving, is called:",
      "options": [
        "mental set.",
        "functional fixedness.",
        "well-defined thinking.",
        "ill-defined thinking."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "mental set.",
      "week": 10,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "Cognitive Psychology"
    },
    {
      "question": "The string problem often generates _____ when participants do not think to use the screwdriver as a pendulum.",
      "options": [
        "functional fixedness",
        "mental set",
        "incomplete representations",
        "reasoning by analogy"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "functional fixedness",
      "week": 10,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "Cognitive Psychology"
    },
    {
      "question": "_____ involves appropriate novelty in generating solutions.",
      "options": [
        "Intelligence",
        "Genius",
        "Creativity",
        "Mental disorder"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Creativity",
      "week": 10,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "Cognitive Psychology"
    },
    {
      "question": "Research on the incubation effect has shown that:",
      "options": [
        "most empirical studies support the positive effects of incubation.",
        "incubation effects are only found with very long incubation intervals.",
        "incubation actually has a negative effect on performance.",
        "participants who take physical and mental breaks rarely show increased ability to solve problems."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "participants who take physical and mental breaks rarely show increased ability to solve problems.",
      "week": 10,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "Cognitive Psychology"
    },
    {
      "question": "The prefrontal cortex is involved in the ability to plan and solve problems.",
      "options": [
        "True",
        "False"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "True",
      "week": 10,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "Cognitive Psychology"
    },
    {
      "question": "The detailed, concurrent, and nonjudgmental observation of the contents of your consciousness is called:",
      "options": [
        "thinking.",
        "daydreaming.",
        "problem solving.",
        "introspection."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "introspection.",
      "week": 10,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "Cognitive Psychology"
    },
    {
      "question": "Deductive reasoning involves which of the following?",
      "options": [
        "going from general to specific statements",
        "conclusions that add new information to what is given",
        "going from specific to general statements",
        "going from specific to specific statements"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "going from general to specific statements",
      "week": 11,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "Cognitive Psychology"
    },
    {
      "question": "When it is improbable (but not impossible) for an argument's premises to be true and its conclusions false, the argument has:",
      "options": [
        "deductive validity.",
        "deductive strength.",
        "inductive validity.",
        "inductive strength."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "inductive strength.",
      "week": 11,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "Cognitive Psychology"
    },
    {
      "question": "If a person has five letters in his or her name, then s/he is a Glirple. I can now validly assume that:",
      "options": [
        "Shawn is a Glirple.",
        "anyone who is a Glirple must have five letters in his/her name.",
        "anyone who is not a Glirple cannot be named Susan.",
        "Shawn is a Glirple, and anyone who is not a Glirple cannot be named Susan."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Shawn is a Glirple, and anyone who is not a Glirple cannot be named Susan.",
      "week": 11,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "Cognitive Psychology"
    },
    {
      "question": "In completing Wason's four-card task, participants usually:",
      "options": [
        "turn over the two cards that are necessary and sufficient to test the rule.",
        "turn over all four cards, when only two would have been sufficient.",
        "turn over all four cards, when only one would have been sufficient.",
        "show understanding of modus ponens but neglect modus tollens."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "show understanding of modus ponens but neglect modus tollens.",
      "week": 11,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "Cognitive Psychology"
    },
    {
      "question": "People have more difficulty working with:",
      "options": [
        "quantifiers such as “all” or “no.”",
        "quantifiers such as “some.”",
        "premises that have negatives in them, and quantifiers such as “all” or “no.”",
        "premises that have negatives in them, and quantifiers such as “some.”"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "premises that have negatives in them, and quantifiers such as “some.”",
      "week": 11,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "Cognitive Psychology"
    },
    {
      "question": "The tendency to seek out information that supports our current beliefs is called:",
      "options": [
        "a believability effect.",
        "a content effect.",
        "a confirmation bias.",
        "syllogistic reasoning."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "a confirmation bias.",
      "week": 11,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "Cognitive Psychology"
    },
    {
      "question": "The gambler's fallacy is thought of as a special instance of:",
      "options": [
        "framing.",
        "availability.",
        "belief in the law of small numbers.",
        "hindsight."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "belief in the law of small numbers.",
      "week": 11,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "Cognitive Psychology"
    },
    {
      "question": "Let p = “Mary got an A on her exam” and q = “John got a C on his exam.” In which of the following situations is the statement “p & q” true?",
      "options": [
        "Mary and John both got A's.",
        "Mary and John both got C's.",
        "Mary got an A and John got a C.",
        "Mary got a C and John got an A."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "Mary got an A and John got a C.",
      "week": 11,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "Cognitive Psychology"
    },
    {
      "question": "“All dogs chase cats. Bingo is a dog. Therefore, Bingo chases cats.” This is an example of deductive reasoning.",
      "options": [
        "True",
        "False"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "True",
      "week": 11,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "Cognitive Psychology"
    },
    {
      "question": "The representativeness heuristic causes us to erroneously judge words with “L” as their first letter to be more common than words with “L” as their third letter.",
      "options": [
        "True",
        "False"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "False",
      "week": 11,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "Cognitive Psychology"
    },
    {
      "question": "____ is a normative model for integrating different dimensions and goals of a complex decision.",
      "options": [
        "Expected utility",
        "MAUT",
        "Framing",
        "Availability"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "MAUT",
      "week": 12,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "Cognitive Psychology"
    },
    {
      "question": "Expert decision makers may rely on intuition and mental simulation, according to the _____ model.",
      "options": [
        "recognition-primed decision-making",
        "MAUT",
        "EU",
        "elimination-by-aspects"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "recognition-primed decision-making",
      "week": 12,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "Cognitive Psychology"
    },
    {
      "question": "Expected utility is a descriptive model of human decision making.",
      "options": [
        "True",
        "False"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "False",
      "week": 12,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "Cognitive Psychology"
    },
    {
      "question": "When making a complex decision such as choosing 1 of 10 different apartments to rent,",
      "options": [
        "participants spontaneously use multiattribute utility theory.",
        "participants use the same decision strategies regardless of the number of alternatives they are choosing between.",
        "participants systematically search for all available information.",
        "participants often eliminate some alternatives on the basis of only one or a few undesirable characteristics."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "participants often eliminate some alternatives on the basis of only one or a few undesirable characteristics.",
      "week": 12,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "Cognitive Psychology"
    },
    {
      "question": "Expected utility theory is usually regarded as a ______ model of decision making.",
      "options": [
        "descriptive",
        "prescriptive",
        "normative",
        "both descriptive and prescriptive"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "normative",
      "week": 12,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "Cognitive Psychology"
    },
    {
      "question": "You are offered a chance to buy a lottery ticket. The probability of winning is 1 in 100. If you win, the prize is $100,000. According to expected value, a “fair” price for this lottery ticket would be:",
      "options": [
        "$5.",
        "$10",
        "$100",
        "$1000"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "$1000",
      "week": 12,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "Cognitive Psychology"
    },
    {
      "question": "Normative models of decision making describe:",
      "options": [
        "ideal performance under ideal circumstances.",
        "what people actually do when they make decisions.",
        "cognitive illusions.",
        "hindsight biases."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "ideal performance under ideal circumstances.",
      "week": 12,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "Cognitive Psychology"
    },
    {
      "question": "You are a participant in an experiment in which you answer a long list of general knowledge questions. After answering each question, you are asked to rate your probability of being correct. If you are like the typical participant in such experiments, you will probably be correct on what percentage of questions for which you estimated “60% probability correct”?",
      "options": [
        "55%",
        "60%",
        "70%",
        "100%"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "55%",
      "week": 12,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "Cognitive Psychology"
    },
    {
      "question": "The normative model for integrating different dimensions of a complex decision is called MAUT.",
      "options": [
        "True",
        "False"
      ],
      "correct_answer": "True",
      "week": 12,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "Cognitive Psychology"
    },
    {
      "question": "You have just spent 10 minutes trying to figure out the answer to a single problem on your math quiz. In spite of your lack of success, you continue to struggle, neglecting to continue on to other problems because you've already invested so much time and effort in this problem. You have fallen victim to:",
      "options": [
        "the sunk cost effect.",
        "a framing effect.",
        "the anchor effect.",
        "availability bias."
      ],
      "correct_answer": "the sunk cost effect.",
      "week": 12,
      "year": 2025,
      "subject": "Cognitive Psychology"
    }
  ]